<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

	<title>Planet Sage</title>
	<link rel="self" href="http://planet.sagemath.org/atom.xml"/>
	<link href="http://planet.sagemath.org"/>
	<id>http://planet.sagemath.org/atom.xml</id>
	<updated>2018-03-20T10:12:02+00:00</updated>
	<generator uri="http://www.planetplanet.org/">Planet/2.0 +http://www.planetplanet.org</generator>

	<entry>
		<title type="html">Free Computational Mathematics</title>
		<link href="http://opendreamkit.org/2019/02/11/FreeComputationalMathematicsConference/"/>
		<id>http://opendreamkit.org/2019/02/11/FreeComputationalMathematicsConference</id>
		<updated>2018-03-19T23:01:26+00:00</updated>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This is an announcement for a large one week dissemination conference
organized by OpenDreamKit at the CIRM premises near Marseille, France.
With OpenDreamKit approaching its end (august 2019), this will our
main public closing event.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://conferences.cirm-math.fr/1978.html&quot;&gt;Webpage on the CIRM website for registrations&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>
		<author>
			<name>The OpenDreamKit consortium</name>
			<email>contact@opendreamkit.org</email>
			<uri>http://opendreamkit.org/</uri>
		</author>
		<source>
			<title type="html">OpenDreamKit</title>
			<link rel="self" href="http://opendreamkit.org/atom.xml"/>
			<id>http://opendreamkit.org/</id>
			<updated>2018-03-19T23:01:26+00:00</updated>
		</source>
	</entry>

	<entry>
		<title type="html">Interfacing (math) software with low level libraries</title>
		<link href="http://opendreamkit.org/2018/03/19/cernay-2018/"/>
		<id>http://opendreamkit.org/2018/03/19/cernay-2018</id>
		<updated>2018-03-19T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://opendreamkit.org&quot;&gt;OpenDreamKit&lt;/a&gt; is organizing a
&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/OpenDreamKit/OpenDreamKit/issues/251&quot;&gt;workshop on Interfacing (math) software with low level libraries&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
		<author>
			<name>The OpenDreamKit consortium</name>
			<email>contact@opendreamkit.org</email>
			<uri>http://opendreamkit.org/</uri>
		</author>
		<source>
			<title type="html">OpenDreamKit</title>
			<link rel="self" href="http://opendreamkit.org/atom.xml"/>
			<id>http://opendreamkit.org/</id>
			<updated>2018-03-19T23:01:26+00:00</updated>
		</source>
	</entry>

	<entry>
		<title type="html">Toward versatile JupyterHub deployments, with the Binder and JupyterHub convergence</title>
		<link href="http://opendreamkit.org/2018/03/15/jupyterhub-binder-convergence/"/>
		<id>http://opendreamkit.org/2018/03/15/jupyterhub-binder-convergence</id>
		<updated>2018-03-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<content type="html">&lt;h1 id=&quot;about-this-document&quot;&gt;About this document&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nowadays, many institutions run a &lt;a href=&quot;http://jupyterhub.org&quot;&gt;JupyterHub&lt;/a&gt;
server, providing their members with easy access to &lt;a href=&quot;http://jupyter.org&quot;&gt;Jupyter&lt;/a&gt;-based
virtual environments (a.k.a. notebook servers), preinstalled with a
stack of computational software, tailored to the typical needs of the
institution’s members. Meanwhile, since a few years ago,
&lt;a href=&quot;http://mybinder.org&quot;&gt;Binder&lt;/a&gt; lets any user on the internet define,
run, and share temporary virtual environments equipped with an
arbitrary software stack (&lt;a href=&quot;https://jupyter.org/try&quot;&gt;examples&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Fall 2017, Binder was revamped as BinderHub, a lightweight layer on
top of JupyterHub. The next step in this convergence is to bring
together the best of both worlds: think persistent authenticated
&lt;a href=&quot;http://mybinder.org&quot;&gt;Binder&lt;/a&gt;; or
&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jupyter/repo2docker&quot;&gt;repo2docker&lt;/a&gt; enabled
&lt;a href=&quot;http://jupyterhub.org&quot;&gt;JupyterHub&lt;/a&gt;. For now, let’s call them &lt;em&gt;versatile
JupyterHub deployments&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This document brainstorms this convergence process: it sets up the
ground with a scenario and assumptions for a typical institution-wide
JupyterHub deployment, proposes specifications from a user perspective,
and describes some typical use cases that would be enabled by such
specifications. It further discusses security aspects and what remains
to be implemented, before concluding with more advanced features and
open questions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This document started as a collection of private notes
reflecting on in-development
&lt;a href=&quot;http://jupytercloud.lal.in2p3.fr/&quot;&gt;JupyterHub deployment at Paris-Saclay&lt;/a&gt;
and &lt;a href=&quot;https://jupyterhub.fedcloud-tf.fedcloud.eu/&quot;&gt;EGI&lt;/a&gt; respectively,
with &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/OpenDreamKit/OpenDreamKit.github.io/commits/master/_posts/2018-03-15-jupyterhub-binder-convergence.md&quot;&gt;some additional contributions&lt;/a&gt;.
They were largely informed by many discussions at
March 2018’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://pad.unistra.fr/p/jupyterhub-dev&quot;&gt;JupyterHub coding sprint in Orsay&lt;/a&gt;
that involved dev-ops
of those deployments and two of the main JupyterHub and BinderHub
devs: Min Ragan Kelley and Chris Holdgraf. It was also inspired by
some of &lt;a href=&quot;https://cocalc.com&quot;&gt;cocalc&lt;/a&gt; features. Silly ideas reflecting
here are mine, hard work is theirs; thank you all!!!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This document is meant for brainstorming; please
&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/OpenDreamKit/OpenDreamKit.github.io/tree/master/_posts/2018-03-15-jupyterhub-binder-convergence.md&quot;&gt;hop in and edit&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;typical-scenario&quot;&gt;Typical scenario&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An institution – typically a university, a national lab, a
transnational research infrastructure such as the &lt;a href=&quot;http://xfel.eu&quot;&gt;European
XFEL&lt;/a&gt;, or transational infrastructure provider like
&lt;a href=&quot;http://egi.eu&quot;&gt;EGI&lt;/a&gt; – wishes to provide its members and users with a
Jupyter service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The service lets user spawn and access personal or collaborative
virtual environments: namely a web interface to a light weight virtual
machine, in which they can use Jupyter notebooks, run calculations,
etc. In the remainder of this document we will use JupyterHub’s
terminology and call such
virtual environments &lt;em&gt;notebook servers&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To cater for a large variety of use cases in teaching and research,
the main aim of the upcoming specifications is to make the service as
versatile as possible. In particular, it should empower the users to
customize the service (available software stack, storage setup, …),
without a need for administrator intervention.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;assumptions&quot;&gt;Assumptions&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The institution has access to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;An authentication service (Single Sign-On)&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Examples: Paris-Sud’ Adonis internal SSO, the federated “Recherche
et Enseignement Supérieur” authentication service of Renater, EGI
CheckIn, …&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Computing resources&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Examples: a local cluster, access to a externalized cloud (GC, AWS,
Azure, …)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A shared volume service using the above authentication service&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;E.g. a local NextCloud service, or …&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;(Optional) a forge&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Examples: a local gitlab service, github, … if private
repositories are needed, the forge presumably will need the same
authentication service&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;specifications--user-story&quot;&gt;Specifications / User Story&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;main-page-of-the-service&quot;&gt;Main page of the service&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After authentication, the user faces a page that is similar to
binder’s main page:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A form to describe and launch the desired persistent notebook
server.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;For the sake of simplicity, the form could optionally start hidden,
and be replaced by two items: “Choose preconfigured notebook server”
/ “Create my own notebook server”.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Links to documentation&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Warnings about potential security concerns, to inform the user
choices.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Alternatively, such warnings could be displayed in a later security
confirmation dialog “with the given configuration, a malicious
image/collaborator could …; do you trust it? Proceed/Edit
Configuration/Cancel/Don’t ask again”&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Institutional credits (service provided by …)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The form consists of:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The usual binder items:&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;the description of the computing environment: a repo-to-docker-style git repo+branch+…&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;the file/url to open on startup&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;…&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;a UI to get a URL/badge referencing the machine&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Persistence and access options:&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;server_name: name to give to the server&lt;/p&gt;

        &lt;p&gt;If server_name is not specified, create a random server name?&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;mount options: [[mount point, volume url], […]]&lt;/p&gt;

        &lt;p&gt;This assumes that the user has appropriate credentials to access
the given volumes through the authentication service&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;collaborators=[….]: (optional) a white list of other users of this jupyterhub that can access this server&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;a flag allowing public ‘temporary read-only’ access (meaning
that the container and all changes are thrown away at the end of
the session; and that any ‘mounted’ data sources are read-only
during the session)&lt;/p&gt;

        &lt;p&gt;alternatively&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;credentials: whether to pass the user credentials into the container (as environment variable, or file)&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;resources scaling (optional): memory, number of processors,
duration (time or time of inactivity after which the server will
be automatically stopped / destroyed)&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;behavior-upon-clicking-launch&quot;&gt;Behavior upon clicking Launch:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If a notebook server with the given name already exists and the
 parameters are not changed (or not set): connect to that server,
 restarting it if needed&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If the parameters have been changed, update the existing server when
possible? Or should the user just delete the server?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Otherwise, create and launch&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;behavior-upon-following-a-server-urlbadge&quot;&gt;Behavior upon following a server URL/badge:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Display the authentication page (if not yet authenticated)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Display a security confirmation dialog as above (if origin is not within the
 jupyterhub), with a description of the configuration and origin.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As above after clicking “Launch”&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;some-use-cases&quot;&gt;Some use cases&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;local-binder-better-name-binderhome&quot;&gt;Local binder (better name? [Binder@home?])&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Scenarios:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Luc, a researcher, discovered a nice computing environment
on Binder. Maybe a notebook demonstrating an interesting workflow to
analyze data. He wants to use it more intensively on his own data.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Lucy has found a notebook &amp;amp; binder environment published with a
paper, and she wants to re-execute the notebook to reproduce the
published results and start her research in the field. However, no
binder (compute) resources are available in the cloud. The
computation takes 20 minutes on a standard PC and she would like to
run this calculation on her local server.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Setup:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They recreate the same environment on their local server (for example
by just changing the server name in the binder URL).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More advanced scenario to explore: Lucy would like to use her Desktop
PC because that resource is readily available and idles 99% of the
time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;easy-sharing-of-computational-environments&quot;&gt;Easy sharing of computational environments&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Scenarios:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Sarah, a power user, is using some specialized stack of software on
a daily basis; maybe she authored some of it. She wants her
colleagues in her lab to try out that software.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Paul organizes a training session for his colleagues.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Alice has authored notebooks that she wants to share with her
colleagues. Maybe the notebooks automatize some complicated
processes and present them in the form of interactive web
applications built using &lt;a href=&quot;http://jupyter.org/widgets&quot;&gt;Jupyter widgets&lt;/a&gt;
(&lt;a href=&quot;https://mybinder.org/v2/gh/binder-examples/appmode/master?urlpath=apps%2Findex.ipynb&quot;&gt;demo&lt;/a&gt;).
Think of a wizard to setup parameters and data, run a computation,
and visualize the results.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Setup:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They prepare a notebook server with the appropriate software stack
installed configured and access to the user’s shared home directory.
Maybe they provide some document. They then just have to share the URL
with their colleagues. No lengthy software installation. The
colleagues can then start working right away, in their own
environment, using their own data, saving their work in their home
directory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In all cases, the explicit description of the computing environment
(and the use of open source software!) eases:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the publication of the same computational environment / notebooks
elsewhere, e.g. on a public Binder;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the installation the same software on the user’s personal computer.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;collaboration&quot;&gt;Collaboration&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Scenario: Alice and Bob want to collaborate on some data analysis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Setup:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They create a shared volume. Then either:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;They set up each their own notebook server, and let them share the
same volume.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Alice sets up a single server, with Bob as collaborator. Within the
server, they are considered as the same user.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this stage, they should not edit the same notebook simultaneously.
However the stable version of JupyterLab, due sometime in 2018, should
enable real-time collaboration in both setups, thanks to
a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Conflict-free_replicated_data_type&quot;&gt;CRDT&lt;/a&gt;
file format for notebooks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;class-management&quot;&gt;Class management&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Scenario: using the server for a class’ computer labs and assignments&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Desired features:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Full customizability of the computing environment by the teacher;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Support for live manipulation of the class notes;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Support for submission, collection and auto-grading of assignments;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Access from the computer labs or outside (home, …);&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Possibility to either use the server, needing only a web browser (no
software installation required; supports phones, tablets, …), or
install and run the software locally.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Prerequisites:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A JupyterHub instance, configured as above, accessible from the teachers and students;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A forge such as gitlab or github, accessible from JupyterHub&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A shared drive service (e.g. next cloud/nsf/…), serving home directories,
and letting teachers setup shared volumes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A shared authentication (e.g. SSO), so that notebook servers in JupyterHub can access
the shared drive.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Some web server&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Procedure for the teacher(s):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Set up a shared volume for the whole class&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Prepare a computing environment in a git repository on the forge.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Typically includes: computational software, [nbgrader] + configuration, …&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Prepare the course material typically in a git repository on the forge
(the same one or another)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Use JupyterHub’s form UI to setup (and test) a full description of the student’s
notebook servers, with mounting of the home directory (or subdirectory thereof?) and shared volume.
Possibly add the teacher(s) as collaborator(s) ???
Get the corresponding URL.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Possibly prepare a variant thereof for teachers of the class.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Set up a web page for the class, with hyperlink(s) to the above URL.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;There can typically be an hyperlink for each session pointing directly
to the exercises for that particular session.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fetching the class material:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Option 1: manually download from the web (wget in the terminal, or web upload, …) or shared volume&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Option 2: use &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/data-8/nbgitpuller&quot;&gt;nbgitpuller&lt;/a&gt; from the command line&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Option 3: use &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jupyter/nbgrader&quot;&gt;nbgrader&lt;/a&gt;, either from the command line or with the UI to get the files from the shared volume&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Option 4: automatize the above using a notebook server extension such as that for nbgitpuller&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Submitting assignments:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Use nbgrader, either from the command line or with the UI to push the files to the shared volume&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To explore: integration with local e-learning platforms like Moodle,
typically using &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.imsglobal.org/activity/learning-tools-interoperability&quot;&gt;LTI&lt;/a&gt;,
in particular for class management and grades reporting.
There already exists an &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jupyterhub/ltiauthenticator&quot;&gt;LTI authenticator for Jupyter&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;security-concerns&quot;&gt;Security concerns&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A malicious image description, image, or collaborator can:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Take any action within the image being built or within the notebook server&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Waste computing resources (cpu/memory);&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;With internet: connect to any website, without specific priviledges
(e.g. participate to a DOS attack); abuse computing resources, e.g.
for bitcoining. The image building almost certainly needs internet
access.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;With persistent storage and internet access: access and leak
information from the storage; e.g. private information from the user;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;With read-write persistent storage: corrupt the storage (e.g. the user’s home directory)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;With credentials: take any action on behalf of the user in any
service that use the same authentication.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;implementation-status&quot;&gt;Implementation status&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of the features are already there. Here are some of the missing steps:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Extending binder’s form as described above;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Implementing the logic to mount shared volumes;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Instructions / scripts for setting up a local docker registry;&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;The current Binder installation tutorial assumes that a docker
registry is already available; e.g. that provided by google cloud
services.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;For a smaller setup using the same host for both building images and
running notebook servers, no docker registry is needed. In this
case, JupyterHub could just run repo2docker locally before launching
the notebook server. repo2docker however does not implement image
caching; so a simplified version of the image cache mechanism of
Binder needs to be implemented.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;alternatives&quot;&gt;Alternatives&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It should be noted that there is basically no coupling between
JupyterHub/Binder and Jupyter. The former is merely a general purpose
web service for provisioning web-based virtual environments. For
example, JupyterHub/Binder has also been used to serve R-Studio based
virtual environments. Reciprocally, there are alternative services to
do such provisioning from which to get inspiration, like
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.simulagora.com/&quot;&gt;Simulagora&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;advanced-features--open-questions&quot;&gt;Advanced features &amp;amp; open questions&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;redirection&quot;&gt;Redirection&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main form could contain an additional item:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;URL input / dropdown menu to choose another jupyterhub instances to
redirect to.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Use cases:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A user finds a nice image on binder; he wants to customize it to
run it on his institution’s jupyterhub; possibly adding persistent
storage to it. Or reciprocally: a user wants to share on binder a
local image of his.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;An institution wants to advertise other jupyterhub instances; this
could e.g. be used by a single entry point for federating a
collection of instances (e.g. all French academic JupyterHub’s).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;marketplace-of-images&quot;&gt;Marketplace of images&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the URL mechanism, any (power) user can prepare a dedicated image
and share it with his collaborators. Images can be more or less
specific: from just a computing environment to a fully specified
machine, with mount points, …&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks to the above there is no need for a tightly coupled Marketplace.
Nevertheless it may be useful to have one location (or more) for
collecting and publicizing links to popular images. Some minimal
coupling may be needed if one would want to sort the images according
to their popularity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note: at this stage, a user cannot produce an image by setting up a
machine “by hand” and save its state. The construction must be fully
scripted. On the plus side, this encourages users to script their
images, making them more reproducible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;National and international initiatives such as the &lt;a href=&quot;http://opendreamkit.org/2017/12/06/EOSC/&quot;&gt;European Open
Science Cloud&lt;/a&gt; may help
providing such a catalog of relevant Jupyter notebooks/images.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;default-volume-configuration&quot;&gt;Default volume configuration&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Choose good defaults, if at all possible compatible with binder.
Main question: where should the files provided by the binder
environment be copied? In a subdirectory of the persistent home? In
the home directory, with the persistent home being mounted in a
subdirectory thereof?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;intensive-use-and-resource-management--accounting&quot;&gt;Intensive use and resource management / accounting&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The above has been written with casual use in mind. For extensive use,
some form of accounting and controlling of the resources used would be needed. For
example, for LAL’s cloud we may want to have some form of bridge
between the OpenStack dashboard and the hub. UI to be designed. Could
the user provision a machine using the dashboard, and then specify on
JupyterHub that the container shall be run on that machine?&lt;/p&gt;</content>
		<author>
			<name>The OpenDreamKit consortium</name>
			<email>contact@opendreamkit.org</email>
			<uri>http://opendreamkit.org/</uri>
		</author>
		<source>
			<title type="html">OpenDreamKit</title>
			<link rel="self" href="http://opendreamkit.org/atom.xml"/>
			<id>http://opendreamkit.org/</id>
			<updated>2018-03-19T23:01:26+00:00</updated>
		</source>
	</entry>

	<entry>
		<title type="html">Research Software Engineer position opening at Université Paris-Sud</title>
		<link href="http://opendreamkit.org/2018/02/21/position-paris-sud/"/>
		<id>http://opendreamkit.org/2018/02/21/position-paris-sud</id>
		<updated>2018-02-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This is an announcement for a research software engineer position
opening at Université Paris-Sud, working on web-based user interfaces
and semantic interoperability layers for mathematical computational
systems and databases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;time-line&quot;&gt;Time line&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Interviews in March 2018 for a recruitment as soon as possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;salary&quot;&gt;Salary&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a full-time position, and depending on the applicant’s past
experience, between 2000€ and 3000€ of monthly “salaire net” (salary
after non-wage labour cost but before income tax). Equivalently, what
this salary represents for is a “salaire brut” of up to 46200€ yearly.
We have secured funding until the end of the project (August 2019).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;location&quot;&gt;Location&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The research software engineer will work at the
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.lri.fr&quot;&gt;Laboratoire de Recherche en Informatique&lt;/a&gt; of
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.u-psud.fr&quot;&gt;Université Paris Sud&lt;/a&gt;, in the
Orsay-Bures-Gif-Saclay campus, 25 km South-West of Paris city centre.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;mission-and-activities&quot;&gt;Mission and activities&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Paris Sud is the leading site of OpenDreamKit, with eight participants
involved in all the work packages. The research software engineer will
join that team and support its efforts in WP4 and WP6, targeting
respectively Jupyter-based user interfaces and interoperability for
mathematical computational systems and databases. A common theme is how
to best exploit the mathematical knowledge embedded in the systems.
For some context, see e.g. the &lt;a href=&quot;http://opendreamkit.org/2017/10/15/WP6-Usecase/&quot;&gt;recent
publications&lt;/a&gt; describing
the Math-In-The-Middle approach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More specifically, a successful candidate will be expected to
contribute significantly to some of the following tasks (see also
&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/OpenDreamKit/OpenDreamKit/raw/master/Proposal/proposal-www.pdf&quot;&gt;OpenDreamKit’s Proposal&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Dynamic documentation and exploration system (Task 4.5)&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Introspection has become a critical tool in interactive computation,
allowing user to explore, on the fly, the properties and
capabilities of the objects under manipulation. This challenge
becomes particularly acute in systems like Sage where large parts of
the class hierarchy is built dynamically, and static documentation
builders like Sphinx cannot anymore render all the available
information.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;In this task, we will investigate how to further enhance the user
experience. This will include:&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;On the fly generation of Javadoc style documentation, through
introspection, allowing e.g. the exploration of the class
hierarchy, available methods, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Widgets based on the HTML5 and web component standards to display
graphical views of the results of SPARQL queries, as well as populating data
structures with the results of such queries,&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;D4.16: Exploratory support for semantic-aware interactive Jupyter widgets
providing views on objects of the underlying computational or
database components. Preliminary steps are demonstrated in the
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.larchenvironment.com/&quot;&gt;Larch Environment&lt;/a&gt; project (see
demo videos) and
&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jbandlow/sage-explorer&quot;&gt;sage-explorer&lt;/a&gt;. The
ultimate aim would be to automatically generate LMFDB-style
interfaces.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Whenever possible, those features will be implemented generically
for any computation kernel by extending the Jupyter protocol with
introspection and documentation queries.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Memoisation and production of new data (Task 6.9)&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Many CAS users run large and intensive computations, for which they
want to collect the results while simultaneously working on software
improvements. GAP retains computed attribute values of objects
within a session; Sage currently has a limited &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;cached_method&lt;/code&gt;.
Neither offers storage that is persistent across sessions or
supports publication of the result or sharing within a
collaboration. We will use, extend and contribute back to, an
appropriate established persistent memoisation infrastructure, such
as &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;python-joblib&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;redis-simple-cache&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;dogpile.cache&lt;/code&gt;, adding
features needed for storage and use of results in mathematical
research. We will design something that is simple to deploy and
configure, and makes it easy to share results in a controlled
manner, but provides enough assurance to enable the user to rely on
the data, give proper credit to the original computation and rerun
the computation if they want to.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Knowledge-based code infrastructure (Task 6.5)&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Over the last decades, computational components, and in particular
Axiom, MuPAD, \GAP, or \Sage, have embedded more and more
mathematical knowledge directly inside the code, as a way to better
structure it for expressiveness, flexibility, composability,
documentation, and robustness. In this task we will review the
various approaches taken in these software (e.g. categories and
dynamic class hierarchies) and in proof assistants like Coq
(e.g. static type systems), and compare their respective strength
and weaknesses on concrete case studies. We will also explore
whether paradigms offered by recent programming languages like Julia
or Scala could enable a better implementation. Based on this we will
suggest and experiment with design improvements, and explore
challenges such as the compilation, verification, or
interoperability of such code.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;skills-and-background-requirements&quot;&gt;Skills and background requirements&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Degree in mathematics or computer science; PhD appreciated but not required;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Strong programming experience with languages such as Python, Scala,
Javascript, etc; experience with web technologies in general and the
&lt;a href=&quot;http://jupyter.org/&quot;&gt;Jupyter&lt;/a&gt; stack in particular appreciated;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Experience in software design and practical implementation in large
software projects; experience with computational mathematics
software (e.g. &lt;a href=&quot;http://sagemath.org&quot;&gt;SageMath&lt;/a&gt;) appreciated;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Experience in open-source development (collaborative development
tools, interaction with the community, …);&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Strong communication skills;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Fluency in oral and written English; speaking French is not a
prerequisite.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;context&quot;&gt;Context&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The position will be funded by
&lt;a href=&quot;http://opendreamkit.org&quot;&gt;OpenDreamKit&lt;/a&gt;, a
&lt;a href=&quot;https://ec.europa.eu/programmes/horizon2020/&quot;&gt;Horizon 2020&lt;/a&gt;
European &lt;a href=&quot;https://ec.europa.eu/programmes/horizon2020/en/h2020-section/european-research-infrastructures-including-e-infrastructures&quot;&gt;Research Infrastructure&lt;/a&gt;
project that will run for four years, starting from September&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;This project brings together the open-source computational
mathematics ecosystem – and in particular
&lt;a href=&quot;http://linalg.org/&quot;&gt;LinBox&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href=&quot;http://mpir.org&quot;&gt;MPIR&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href=&quot;http://sagemath.org/&quot;&gt;SageMath&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.gap-system.org/&quot;&gt;GAP&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href=&quot;http://pari.math.u-bordeaux.fr/&quot;&gt;PARI/GP&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href=&quot;http://lmfdb.org/&quot;&gt;LMFDB&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.singular.uni-kl.de/&quot;&gt;Singular&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href=&quot;https://mathhub.info/&quot;&gt;MathHub&lt;/a&gt;,
and the
&lt;a href=&quot;http://jupyter.org/&quot;&gt;IPython/Jupyter&lt;/a&gt; interactive computing
environment.
– toward building a
flexible toolkit for
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.2020-horizon.com/e-Infrastructures-for-virtual-research-environments-%28VRE%29-i1490.html&quot;&gt;Virtual Research Environments&lt;/a&gt;
for mathematics. Lead by Université Paris-Sud, this project involves
about 50 people spread over 15 sites in Europe, with a total budget of
about 7.6 million euros.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Within this ecosystem, the applicant will work primarily on the free
open-source mathematics software system
&lt;a href=&quot;http://sagemath.org&quot;&gt;Sagemath&lt;/a&gt;. Based on the
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.python.org&quot;&gt;Python&lt;/a&gt; language and many existing open-source
math libraries, SageMath is developed since 10 years by a worldwide
community of 300 researchers, teachers and engineers, and has reached
1.5M lines of code.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The applicant will work within one of the largest teams of SageMath
developers, composed essentially of researchers in mathematics and
computer science, at the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.lri.fr/&quot;&gt;Laboratoire de Recherche en
Informatique&lt;/a&gt; (LRI) and in nearby institutions.
The LRI also hosts a strong team working on proof systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;applications&quot;&gt;Applications&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To apply for this position, please send an e-mail to
upsud-recruitement-research-engineer at opendreamkit.org
by March 10, with the following documents (in English) attached:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;cover_letter.pdf: a cover letter explaining your interest in this particular position;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;CV.pdf: a CV, highlighting among other things your skills and
background and your contributions to open source software;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;degree.pdf: copy of your most recent degree including (if
applicable) the reviewers reports;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;reference letters: files reference_letter_.pdf or contact information of potential referees.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Applications sent after March 10 will be considered until the
position is filled.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
		<author>
			<name>The OpenDreamKit consortium</name>
			<email>contact@opendreamkit.org</email>
			<uri>http://opendreamkit.org/</uri>
		</author>
		<source>
			<title type="html">OpenDreamKit</title>
			<link rel="self" href="http://opendreamkit.org/atom.xml"/>
			<id>http://opendreamkit.org/</id>
			<updated>2018-03-19T23:01:26+00:00</updated>
		</source>
	</entry>

	<entry xml:lang="en-US">
		<title type="html">Google Summer of Code</title>
		<link href="http://matroidunion.org/?p=2319"/>
		<id>http://matroidunion.org/?p=2319</id>
		<updated>2018-02-19T14:52:39+00:00</updated>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;As you might know, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sagemath.org/&quot;&gt;SageMath&lt;/a&gt; is a software system for mathematical computation. Built on Python, it has extensive libraries for numerous areas of mathematics. One of these areas is Matroid Theory, as has been exhibited &lt;a href=&quot;http://matroidunion.org/?cat=7&quot;&gt;several times&lt;/a&gt; on this blog.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://summerofcode.withgoogle.com&quot;&gt;Google Summer of Code&lt;/a&gt; is a program where Google pays students to work on open-source software during the summer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once again, SageMath has been selected as a mentoring organization for the Google Summer of Code. We&amp;#8217;ve had students work on aspects of the Matroid Theory functionality for the past four years. Maybe this year, YOU can join those illustrious ranks! Check out the &lt;a href=&quot;https://summerofcode.withgoogle.com/organizations/6294052148871168/&quot;&gt;call for proposals&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://wiki.sagemath.org/GSoC/2018&quot;&gt;ideas list&lt;/a&gt;. Read the instructions on both pages carefully. Applications open on March 12, so it&amp;#8217;s a good idea to start talking to potential mentors and begin writing your proposal!&lt;/p&gt;</content>
		<author>
			<name>The Matroid Union</name>
			<uri>http://matroidunion.org</uri>
		</author>
		<source>
			<title type="html">SageMath – The Matroid Union</title>
			<subtitle type="html">A blog for and by the matroid community</subtitle>
			<link rel="self" href="http://matroidunion.org/?feed=rss2&amp;cat=7"/>
			<id>http://matroidunion.org/?feed=rss2&amp;cat=7</id>
			<updated>2018-03-20T10:12:00+00:00</updated>
		</source>
	</entry>

	<entry>
		<title type="html">Remote project meeting</title>
		<link href="http://opendreamkit.org/2018/02/06/project-meeting/"/>
		<id>http://opendreamkit.org/2018/02/06/project-meeting</id>
		<updated>2018-02-06T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This is an online project meeting to review all achievements since March 2017.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://opendreamkit.org/meetings/2018-02-01-SteeringCommitteeMeeting/ProgressReports/&quot;&gt;Progress reports&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content>
		<author>
			<name>The OpenDreamKit consortium</name>
			<email>contact@opendreamkit.org</email>
			<uri>http://opendreamkit.org/</uri>
		</author>
		<source>
			<title type="html">OpenDreamKit</title>
			<link rel="self" href="http://opendreamkit.org/atom.xml"/>
			<id>http://opendreamkit.org/</id>
			<updated>2018-03-19T23:01:26+00:00</updated>
		</source>
	</entry>

	<entry>
		<title type="html">Expérimentation mathématique et combinatoire avec Sage</title>
		<link href="http://opendreamkit.org/2018/01/23/ENS/"/>
		<id>http://opendreamkit.org/2018/01/23/ENS</id>
		<updated>2018-01-23T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Viviane Pons gave a two hours lecture on mathematical experimentation, research and open-source mathematical software development for a seminar organized by the students of the prestigious school &lt;em&gt;Ecole Normale supérieure de Lyon&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lri.fr/~pons/docs/2018_ENS.pdf&quot;&gt;Slides&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/VivianePons/public-notebooks/blob/master/2018-01-22-ENSLyon.ipynb&quot;&gt;Sage Jupyter Notebook&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content>
		<author>
			<name>The OpenDreamKit consortium</name>
			<email>contact@opendreamkit.org</email>
			<uri>http://opendreamkit.org/</uri>
		</author>
		<source>
			<title type="html">OpenDreamKit</title>
			<link rel="self" href="http://opendreamkit.org/atom.xml"/>
			<id>http://opendreamkit.org/</id>
			<updated>2018-03-19T23:01:26+00:00</updated>
		</source>
	</entry>

	<entry>
		<title type="html">Low latency local CoCalc and SageMath on the Google Pixelbook: playing with Crouton, Gallium OS, Rkt, Docker</title>
		<link href="http://sagemath.blogspot.com/2018/01/low-latency-local-cocalc-and-sagemath.html"/>
		<id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-6365588202025292315.post-2384880310944100833</id>
		<updated>2018-01-01T22:29:07+00:00</updated>
		<content type="html">I just got &lt;a href=&quot;https://cocalc.com/&quot;&gt;CoCalc&lt;/a&gt; fully working locally on my Google Pixelbook Chromebook! I want this, since (1) I was inspired by a recent &lt;a href=&quot;https://danluu.com/input-lag/&quot;&gt;blog post about computer latency&lt;/a&gt;, and (2) I'm going to be traveling a lot next week (the &lt;a href=&quot;http://jointmathematicsmeetings.org/jmm&quot;&gt;JMM in San Diego&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;-- come see me at the Sage booth), and may have times without Internet during which I want to work on &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/sagemathinc/cocalc&quot;&gt;CoCalc's development&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;separator&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://3.bp.blogspot.com/-7rPrp2EoRZ0/WkslLBSY-oI/AAAAAAABaUY/0W8HlSBPxagb2ygA-u6X-7o_t88FF7MLACLcBGAs/s1600/Screenshot%2B2018-01-01%2Bat%2B9.50.25%2BPM.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img border=&quot;0&quot; height=&quot;267&quot; src=&quot;https://3.bp.blogspot.com/-7rPrp2EoRZ0/WkslLBSY-oI/AAAAAAABaUY/0W8HlSBPxagb2ygA-u6X-7o_t88FF7MLACLcBGAs/s400/Screenshot%2B2018-01-01%2Bat%2B9.50.25%2BPM.png&quot; width=&quot;400&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;I first tried &lt;a href=&quot;https://termux.com/&quot;&gt;Termux&lt;/a&gt;, which is a &quot;Linux in Android&quot; userland that runs on the Pixelbook (via Android), but there were way, way too many problems for CoCalc, which is a very complicated application, so this was out. The only option was to enable ChromeOS dev mode.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;I next considered partitioning the hard drive, installing Linux natively (in addition to ChromeOS), and dual booting. However, it seems the canonical option is &lt;a href=&quot;https://galliumos.org/&quot;&gt;Gallium OS&lt;/a&gt; and it nobody has got that to work with Pixelbook yet (?). In fact, it appears that Gallium OS development made have stopped a year ago (?). Bummer. So I gave up on that approach...&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The next option was to try &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/dnschneid/crouton&quot;&gt;Crouton&lt;/a&gt; + Docker, since we have a &lt;a href=&quot;https://hub.docker.com/u/sagemathinc/&quot;&gt;CoCalc Docker image&lt;/a&gt;. Unfortunately, it seems currently impossible to use Docker with the standard ChromeOS kernel.&amp;nbsp; The next thing I considered was to use Crouton + &lt;a href=&quot;https://coreos.com/rkt/&quot;&gt;Rkt&lt;/a&gt;, since there are &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.vantol.org/running-docker-containers-on-a-chromebook-with-rkt/&quot;&gt;blog posts&lt;/a&gt; claiming Rkt can run vanilla Docker containers on Crouton.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;I setup Crouton, installed the cli-extra chroot, and easily &lt;a href=&quot;https://coreos.com/rkt/docs/latest/distributions.html#deb-based&quot;&gt;installed Rkt&lt;/a&gt;. I learned how &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@adriaandejonge/moving-from-docker-to-rkt-310dc9aec938&quot;&gt;Rkt is different than Docker&lt;/a&gt;, and tried a bunch of simple standard Docker containers, which worked. However, when I tried running the &lt;a href=&quot;https://hub.docker.com/r/sagemathinc/cocalc-dev/&quot;&gt;(huge) CoCalc Docker container&lt;/a&gt;, I hit major performance issues, and things broke down. If I had the 16GB Chromebook and more patience, maybe this would have worked. But with only 8GB RAM, it really wasn't feasible.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The next idea was to just use Crouton Linux directly (so no containers), and fix whatever issues arose. I did this, and it worked well, with CoCalc giving me a very nice local browser-based interface to my Crouton environment. Also, since we've spent so much time optimizing CoCalc to be fast over the web, it feels REALLY fast when used locally. I made some changes to the CoCalc sources and added &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/sagemathinc/cocalc/tree/master/src/dev/minimal&quot;&gt;a directory&lt;/a&gt;, to hopefully make this easier if anybody else tries. This is definitely not a 1-click solution.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Finally, for &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sagemath.org/&quot;&gt;SageMath&lt;/a&gt; I first tried &lt;a href=&quot;https://launchpad.net/~aims/+archive/ubuntu/sagemath&quot;&gt;the Ubuntu PPA&lt;/a&gt;, but realized it is hopelessly out of date. I then downloaded and extracted the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sagemath.org/download-linux.html&quot;&gt;Ubuntu 16.04 binary&lt;/a&gt; and it worked fine. Of course, I'm also building Sage from source (I'm the founder of SageMath after all), but that takes a long time...&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;separator&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://3.bp.blogspot.com/-lKz_gMDc3rQ/WkslQxLprUI/AAAAAAABaUc/2x74Krpa9lQGV8DjQV2m71NIzu-C8YEtgCLcBGAs/s1600/Screenshot%2B2018-01-01%2Bat%2B10.14.26%2BPM.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img border=&quot;0&quot; height=&quot;258&quot; src=&quot;https://3.bp.blogspot.com/-lKz_gMDc3rQ/WkslQxLprUI/AAAAAAABaUc/2x74Krpa9lQGV8DjQV2m71NIzu-C8YEtgCLcBGAs/s400/Screenshot%2B2018-01-01%2Bat%2B10.14.26%2BPM.png&quot; width=&quot;400&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;separator&quot;&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;Anyway, Crouton works really, really well on the Pixelbook, especially if you do not need to run Docker containers.</content>
		<author>
			<name>William Stein</name>
			<email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
			<uri>http://sagemath.blogspot.com/</uri>
		</author>
		<source>
			<title type="html">Sage: Open Source Mathematics Software</title>
			<subtitle type="html">This is my blog about things related to Sage.</subtitle>
			<link rel="self" href="http://sagemath.blogspot.com/feeds/posts/default"/>
			<id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-6365588202025292315</id>
			<updated>2018-03-08T00:05:15+00:00</updated>
		</source>
	</entry>

	<entry>
		<title type="html">State of the European Open Science Cloud and strategy of OpenDreamKit (draft)</title>
		<link href="http://opendreamkit.org/2017/12/06/EOSC/"/>
		<id>http://opendreamkit.org/2017/12/06/EOSC</id>
		<updated>2017-12-06T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;During the last week of November two events related to the European Open Science Cloud (EOSC) took place in Brussels: the &lt;a href=&quot;https://eoscpilot.eu/eosc-stakeholder-forum-shaping-future-eosc&quot;&gt;EOSC stakeholder forum&lt;/a&gt; on 28-29 November and the 2017 edition of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.digitalinfrastructures.eu/&quot;&gt;DI4R (Digital Infrastructures for Research)&lt;/a&gt;. These two events were closely related in regard with the momentum period 2018-2020 for the Scientific Community and the advancement of open and digital science.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-vision&quot;&gt;The vision&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The European Open Science Cloud (EOSC) is currently a process to build a digital platform that is inspired by the F.A.I.R. principle. &lt;strong&gt;F.A.I.R. stands for: Findable, Accessible, Interoperable and Reusable.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;FAIR is the idea between the recent actions taken by the European Commission and various funding agencies in favour of open data and open science.
The EOSC platform, also called the EOSC-Hub, intends &lt;em&gt;in fine&lt;/em&gt; to make possible to the whole European scientific Community and beyond: exchange of data, easy access to knowledge and access to all useful infrastructures for all scientific disciplines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The word “Open” in EOSC must be understood in every possible way. It means (not exhaustively) that the platform will :&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;promote open source&lt;/strong&gt; software and open access culture&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;make data &lt;strong&gt;as open as possible but as closed as necessary&lt;/strong&gt; in regard with confidentiality and IPR (Intellectual Property Rights) concerns,&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;be a &lt;strong&gt;mix of paid and free services and/or software&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;be open to &lt;strong&gt;all users&lt;/strong&gt;: research centres, public bodies, companies, citizens&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;be accessible &lt;strong&gt;worldwide&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;gather all infrastructures and technologies that are of help for scientists from &lt;strong&gt;all possible disciplines&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Technically speaking, the general idea is to federate existing and yet to appear services, and to make these services &lt;strong&gt;interoperable with one another&lt;/strong&gt;. Services and software can concern for example data and computation hosting, authentication, indexing, collaborative tools, data and service catalogues, etc. Thanks to the interoperability the researchers will be able to discover, navigate, use and re-use, data and combine them suing a various number of infrastructures. The interpretation of data is (or at last should be in our reading) quite broad here: it includes metadata and provenance, data models, tools and generally knowledge required to make sense of the data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://opendreamkit.org/public/images/EOSC-photo-big.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;EOSC photo&quot; class=&quot;img-responsive&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The core role of EOSC-Hub is to coordinate, foster interoperability, develop glue services, and generally speaking steer the efforts toward the needs of researchers. The outcome of the process is still unknown but the ambition is grand. Indeed, an EU official compared the EOSC to the internet. The WWW has been and still is a process, and it has changed the face of the Earth. &lt;strong&gt;The ambition of the EOSC is to change the way we do Science.&lt;/strong&gt;
An explanatory video is &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?time_continue=141&amp;v=SC4-O8BmI4I&quot;&gt;available here.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The EOSC will eventually be linked to the future pan-European HPC, as well as with the future European Data Infrastructure (EDI) which are funded alongsie the EOSC by the European Commission. The EDI and the EOSC may at the end of the day merge, since differences of purpose for each is not yet fully clear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://opendreamkit.org/public/images/EOSC-sketch.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;EOSC sketch&quot; class=&quot;img-responsive&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;political-support-and-public-funding&quot;&gt;Political support and public funding&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The EOSC is part of two strategies of the European Commission: the &lt;a href=&quot;https://ec.europa.eu/digital-single-market/en/policies/shaping-digital-single-market&quot;&gt;Digital Single Market&lt;/a&gt; on one hand and the &lt;a href=&quot;http://ec.europa.eu/research/era/index_en.htm&quot;&gt;European Research Area&lt;/a&gt; on the other hand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The EOSC is the combination of the two, as &lt;strong&gt;it aims at creating a single research community without country or technical barriers&lt;/strong&gt; (interoperability between software and services).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In its &lt;a href=&quot;http://ec.europa.eu/research/participants/data/ref/h2020/wp/2018-2020/main/h2020-wp1820-infrastructures_en.pdf&quot;&gt;Work Programme 2018-2020 for European Research Infrastructures&lt;/a&gt;, the European Commission has put 375 million Euros on the table for “implementing the European Open Science Cloud”. It was initially planned to open a topic of &lt;strong&gt;79M€ for adding other services and infrastructures to the EOSC, but it was postponed after 2020&lt;/strong&gt; for the 9th Framework Programme for research and Innovation. According to Augusto Burgueño Arjon, Head of the Unit “eInfrastructure &amp;amp; Science Cloud” at the DG Communication and Networks at the European Commission, &lt;strong&gt;it is not yet decided what this fund will be used for as it will depend on the evolution of the EOSC-Hub&lt;/strong&gt;. AS according to the Commission and main supporters &lt;strong&gt;there is no room for failure&lt;/strong&gt;, the next 3 years will be crucial. If EOSC implementation is a success, the first half of FP9 will focus on aggregating remaining infrastructures and services while the second half of FP9 will focus on sustaining and scaling the EOSC.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Member States are pushing forward the EOSC as well. Germany and the Netherlands issued in May 2017 a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.government.nl/documents/reports/2017/05/30/joint-position-paper-on-the-european-open-science-cloud&quot;&gt;joint position paper&lt;/a&gt; on the EOSC, which France &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/VidalFrederique/status/936650264899178497&quot;&gt;officially joined&lt;/a&gt; on the 01/12/2017. Furthermore 13 Member States have of to date signed an agreement to start a pan-European HPC programme. This new infrastructure will follow Prace and will be closely connected to EOSC.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;infrastructures-involved&quot;&gt;Infrastructures involved&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Outside of public institutions there are 6 major players pushing forward the EOSC:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.egi.eu/&quot;&gt;EGI&lt;/a&gt; (federation of cloud providers and data centres)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://eudat.eu/&quot;&gt;EUDAT&lt;/a&gt; (data services),&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.openaire.eu/&quot;&gt;OpenAire&lt;/a&gt; (open publication services),&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.geant.org/&quot;&gt;Géant&lt;/a&gt; (network services)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.indigo-datacloud.eu/&quot;&gt;Indigo Data-Cloud&lt;/a&gt; (cloud services for science)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Together they built a consortium of 74 partners coordinated by EGI, in order to answer the call H2020-EINFRA-12-2017(a) within the Work Programme 2018-2020. This project named “EOSC-Hub project” will receive 30M€ by the Commission for the 2018-2020 period. Beneficiaries include Research Infrastructures, national e-Infrastructure providers, SMEs and academic institutions. This consortium will be focused on and addressing issues of the EOSC such as interoperability, adoption of open standards and protocols, governance structure etc&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed, our impression is that - while the vision is clear - &lt;strong&gt;the design and realisation of this vision has no clear shape yet&lt;/strong&gt;: many ideas and components are floating around, some fully or half realised but simultaneously many questions remain unanswered or have not even been asked yet. This state of affairs is not surprising: the vision is grand and has the potential to disrupt (positively) the way in which research is carried out today; the actors are human beings, scientists, institutes, funding bodies and states all with their own priorities and constraints.
Furthermore, &lt;strong&gt;there are real technical challenges in putting this “Cloud” together, and there are also cultural challenges to move more and more research activities towards Open Science&lt;/strong&gt;. Existing metrics for academics and research institutions do not generally incentivise open science; which makes change of behaviour difficult. The biggest challenge for the EOSC is then maybe the challenge of skills and habit because as it was heard from an EU official: &lt;strong&gt;“if we do all this and no one is using it, it will be worthless”.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some infrastructures and services were presented during the DI4R conference as “EOSC building blocks”. The presentations are all available following &lt;a href=&quot;https://indico.egi.eu/indico/event/3455/timetable/#all&quot;&gt;this link&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two presentations attracted our attention:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://help.hubzero.org/&quot;&gt;Hubzero&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://indico.egi.eu/indico/event/3455/session/7/contribution/137/material/slides/0.pdf&quot;&gt;presentation&lt;/a&gt;: open source platform for scientific and educational collaboration&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://indico.egi.eu/indico/event/3455/session/7/contribution/137/material/slides/0.pdf&quot;&gt;Presentation&lt;/a&gt; introducing to FAIR: nothing new but explains principles for EOSC&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Contributions are open on Github to &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/FAIRMetrics/Metrics&quot;&gt;help develop FAIR metrics&lt;/a&gt; for EOSC.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;opendreamkit-and-the-eosc&quot;&gt;OpenDreamKit and the EOSC&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It seems that no e-infrastructure or service presented at the events specifically targets math-based research and teaching, so there could be some room for components of the OpendreamKit VRE.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;partnership-with-egi&quot;&gt;Partnership with EGI&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed there is an &lt;strong&gt;existing collaboration between EGI and OpenDreamKit&lt;/strong&gt; for the deployment of JupyterHub in EGI services. This collaboration will become official in the next weeks with the signature of a Memorandum of Understanding between the two parties.
Depending on the success of this joint work and of the need of the EOSC post-2020, the collaboration could be extended.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;lobby&quot;&gt;Lobby&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;OpenDreamKit as a consortium promoting Open Source software and Open Data in the name of large communities can take lobbying actions to have an impact on the shape of the future EOSC. The following actions can and will be taken:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Become a stakeholder of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://ec.europa.eu/research/openscience/index.cfm?pg=open-science-cloud&quot;&gt;EOSC&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1) Endorse the principles of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://ec.europa.eu/research/openscience/pdf/eosc_declaration.pdf#view=fit&amp;pagemode=none&quot;&gt;EOSC declaration&lt;/a&gt; by sending an official statement by mail&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2) Commit to take some of the specific actions forward&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Endorsement and commitment must be sent at &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:RTD-EOSC@EC.EUROPA.EU&quot;&gt;RTD-EOSC@EC.EUROPA.EU&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contact experts implied in the EOSC:&lt;/strong&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;From External Board of EOSC working for the Commission: several experts including Jean-François ABRAMATIC (INRIA) and the chairperson John Womersley (European Spallation Source)&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;From the External Advisory Board of the EOSC-pilot project (launched in preparation of EOSC-Hub project): the list is available &lt;a href=&quot;https://eoscpilot.eu/about/external-advisory-board&quot;&gt;on their website&lt;/a&gt;. One expert, Françoise GENOVA, is also member of the OpenDreamKit Advisory Board.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The European Commission &lt;strong&gt;Project Officer for OpenDreamKit is also deeply implied in the talks for the EOSC implementation&lt;/strong&gt;, and the Coordinator will be in close relation with her in the next months and years.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Reference: Hans fangohr’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://fangohr.github.io/blog/towards-the-european-open-science-cloud.html&quot;&gt;blogpost&lt;/a&gt; on his group page&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>
		<author>
			<name>The OpenDreamKit consortium</name>
			<email>contact@opendreamkit.org</email>
			<uri>http://opendreamkit.org/</uri>
		</author>
		<source>
			<title type="html">OpenDreamKit</title>
			<link rel="self" href="http://opendreamkit.org/atom.xml"/>
			<id>http://opendreamkit.org/</id>
			<updated>2018-03-19T23:01:26+00:00</updated>
		</source>
	</entry>

	<entry>
		<title type="html">Subgroups and lattices of Lie groups</title>
		<link href="http://opendreamkit.org/2017/11/15/lattices-in-Lie-groups/"/>
		<id>http://opendreamkit.org/2017/11/15/lattices-in-Lie-groups</id>
		<updated>2017-11-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://opendreamkit.org&quot;&gt;OpenDreamKit&lt;/a&gt; is hosting a workshop on “Subgroups and lattices of Lie groups”
to take place at the &lt;a href=&quot;http://faberresidency.cat/&quot;&gt;Faber residency&lt;/a&gt; in Olot, Spain from monday 19th
of February to Saturday 3rd of March 2018. The aim is to bring together experts in the geometry, algebra
and combinatorics together with software developers in order to improve algorithms and
functionalities of open source packages concerning Lie groups and their subgroups.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The organization page of the event is &lt;a href=&quot;https://wiki.sagemath.org/days93&quot;&gt;https://wiki.sagemath.org/days93&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
		<author>
			<name>The OpenDreamKit consortium</name>
			<email>contact@opendreamkit.org</email>
			<uri>http://opendreamkit.org/</uri>
		</author>
		<source>
			<title type="html">OpenDreamKit</title>
			<link rel="self" href="http://opendreamkit.org/atom.xml"/>
			<id>http://opendreamkit.org/</id>
			<updated>2018-03-19T23:01:26+00:00</updated>
		</source>
	</entry>

	<entry>
		<title type="html">Publishing reproducible logbooks</title>
		<link href="http://opendreamkit.org/2017/11/02/use-case-publishing-reproducible-notebooks/"/>
		<id>http://opendreamkit.org/2017/11/02/use-case-publishing-reproducible-notebooks</id>
		<updated>2017-11-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<content type="html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;scenario&quot;&gt;Scenario&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jane has written a (math) paper based on experimentations. She would
like anyone to be able to reproduce her calculations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://opendreamkit.org/public/images/use-cases-binder-logbook.png&quot;&gt; &lt;img src=&quot;http://opendreamkit.org/public/images/use-cases-binder-logbook.png&quot; alt=&quot;a binder logbook screenshot&quot; class=&quot;small-screenshot&quot; /&gt; &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;suggestion-of-solution&quot;&gt;Suggestion of solution&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Describe the experimentation as &lt;a href=&quot;http://jupyter.org&quot;&gt;Jupyter notebooks&lt;/a&gt;,
mixing prose, code, and outputs (think of them as logbooks);&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Publish them on a public repository (e.g. on
&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com&quot;&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt;);&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Make that repository &lt;a href=&quot;http://opendreamkit.org/tag/binder&quot;&gt;Binder-ready&lt;/a&gt; by describing the
software stack required; for details, see the
&lt;a href=&quot;https://mybinder.readthedocs.io/en/latest/using.html#preparing-a-repository-for-binder&quot;&gt;Binder documentation&lt;/a&gt;;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Bonus: make the paper itself active&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;To do: explore using e.g. &lt;a href=&quot;https://dlmf.nist.gov/LaTeXML/&quot;&gt;latexml&lt;/a&gt;+&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/minrk/thebelab&quot;&gt;thebe&lt;/a&gt;?.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;!-- If executing the examples requires a non-trivial install/build step,
also consider
[using a `Dockerfile`](http://mybinder.readthedocs.io/en/latest/dockerfile.html),
and auto-building the Docker image on &lt;https://hub.docker.com&gt;&lt;/https://hub.docker.com&gt;. !--&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;some-instances&quot;&gt;Some instances&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/defeo/ffisom&quot;&gt;Computing isomorphisms and embeddings of finite fields&lt;/a&gt;,
Ludovic Brieulle, Luca De Feo, Javad Doliskani, Jean-Pierre Flori and Éric Schost,
&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/1705.01221&quot;&gt;arXiv:1705.01221 [cs.SC]&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://mybinder.org/v2/gh/defeo/ffisom/master?filepath=notebooks&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://mybinder.org/badge.svg&quot; alt=&quot;launch binder&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/hivert/Jupyter-Notebooks&quot;&gt;The 0-Rook monoid and its representation theory&lt;/a&gt;,
Hivert and Gay
&lt;a href=&quot;https://mybinder.org/v2/gh/hivert/Jupyter-Notebooks/master?filepath=rook-0.ipynb&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://mybinder.org/badge.svg&quot; alt=&quot;launch binder&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;to-do&quot;&gt;To do&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Estimate the number of such instances;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Provide a template.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;time-and-expertise-required&quot;&gt;Time and expertise required&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Assuming Jane is familiar with version control and Jupyter (basic lab
skills taught at &lt;a href=&quot;http://software-carpentry.org/&quot;&gt;Software Carpentry&lt;/a&gt;,
that the experiments were prepared as notebooks, and the software
required is packaged (conda, debian, docker container, …), the
publishing part could take two hours the first time, and half an hour
later on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;whats-new-since-opendreamkit-started&quot;&gt;What’s new since OpenDreamKit started&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Apparition of &lt;a href=&quot;http://mybinder.org&quot;&gt;Binder&lt;/a&gt;;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Expansion of the &lt;a href=&quot;http://jupyter.org&quot;&gt;Jupyter&lt;/a&gt; technology;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Better packaging and interfacing of math software.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;opendreamkit-contribution&quot;&gt;OpenDreamKit contribution&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Development and contributions to Jupyter interfaces (kernels) for
math software (GAP, Pari/GP, SageMath, Singular) and C++;
see &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/OpenDreamKit/OpenDreamKit/issues/96&quot;&gt;D.47&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Contributions to the packaging of math software (GAP, Pari/GP,
SageMath, Singular, …); see
&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/OpenDreamKit/OpenDreamKit/issues/58&quot;&gt;D3.1&lt;/a&gt;
and
&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/OpenDreamKit/OpenDreamKit/issues/59&quot;&gt;D3.10&lt;/a&gt;;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Early adoption of Binder;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Contributions to the
&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/OpenDreamKit/OpenDreamKit/issues/238&quot;&gt;deployment of new Binder instances&lt;/a&gt;;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Advertising, training, providing a template (TODO!), …&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content>
		<author>
			<name>The OpenDreamKit consortium</name>
			<email>contact@opendreamkit.org</email>
			<uri>http://opendreamkit.org/</uri>
		</author>
		<source>
			<title type="html">OpenDreamKit</title>
			<link rel="self" href="http://opendreamkit.org/atom.xml"/>
			<id>http://opendreamkit.org/</id>
			<updated>2018-03-19T23:01:26+00:00</updated>
		</source>
	</entry>

	<entry>
		<title type="html">Post doc position opening at Université Paris-Sud</title>
		<link href="http://opendreamkit.org/2017/11/02/postdoc-position-paris-sud/"/>
		<id>http://opendreamkit.org/2017/11/02/postdoc-position-paris-sud</id>
		<updated>2017-11-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This is an announcement for a postdoc position opening at Université
Paris-Sud, working on the interplay between Data, Knowledge, and
Software in Mathematics, and in particular the exploitation of
mathematical knowledge for increased interoperability across
computational mathematics software and mathematical databases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;time-line&quot;&gt;Time line&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Interviews in early december, for a recruitment from early 2018 to
Fall 2019. Since we have a strong candidate for a half time position,
we will also consider candidates interested in a half-time or shorter
duration position.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;salary&quot;&gt;Salary&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a full-time month work and depending on the applicant’s past experience,
between 2000€ and 3000€ of monthly “salaire net” (salary after non-wage
abour cost but before income tax).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Equivalently, what this salary represents for is a “salaire brut”
of up to 46200€ yearly (for a full-time position).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;location&quot;&gt;Location&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The postdoc will work at the
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.lri.fr&quot;&gt;Laboratoire de Recherche en Informatique&lt;/a&gt; of
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.u-psud.fr&quot;&gt;Université Paris Sud&lt;/a&gt;, in the
Orsay-Bures-Gif-Saclay campus, 25 km South-West of Paris city centre.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;mission-and-activities&quot;&gt;Mission and activities&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;OpenDreamKit’s Work Package 6 explores the interplay between Data,
Knowledge and Software in Mathematics. In particular, it aims at
exploiting mathematical knowledge for increased interoperability
across computational mathematics software and mathematical databases
(known as the Math-In-The-Middle approach). See e.g. the &lt;a href=&quot;http://127.0.0.1:4000/2017/10/15/WP6-Usecase/&quot;&gt;recent
publications&lt;/a&gt; on that
topic, and Section 3.1.6 ``Workpackage Description’’ of the
&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/OpenDreamKit/OpenDreamKit/raw/master/Proposal/proposal-www.pdf&quot;&gt;OpenDreamKit
Proposal&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A successful candidate will be expected to do significant progress, in
close collaboration with the other OpenDreamKit participants and the
community, on some of the tasks of this Work Package:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;D6.8: Currated Math-in-the-Middle Ontology and Alignments for GAP /
Sage / LMFDB&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;T6.5: Knowledge-based code infrastructure&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Over the last decades, computational components, and in particular
Axiom, MuPAD, \GAP, or \Sage, have embedded more and more
mathematical knowledge directly inside the code, as a way to better
structure it for expressiveness, flexibility, composability,
documentation, and robustness. In this task we will review the
various approaches taken in these software (e.g. categories and
dynamic class hierarchies) and in proof assistants like Coq
(e.g. static type systems), and compare their respective strength
and weaknesses on concrete case studies. We will also explore
whether paradigms offered by recent programming languages like Julia
or Scala could enable a better implementation. Based on this we will
suggest and experiment with design improvements, and explore
challenges such as the compilation, verification, or
interoperability of such code.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The candidate will be welcome to work on closely related though more
technical tasks:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;T4.5: Dynamic documentation and exploration system&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Introspection has become a critical tool in interactive computation,
allowing user to explore, on the fly, the properties and
capabilities of the objects under manipulation. This challenge
becomes particularly acute in systems like Sage where large parts of
the class hierarchy is built dynamically, and static documentation
builders like Sphinx cannot anymore render all the available
information.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;In this task, we will investigate how to further enhance the user
experience. This will include:&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;On the fly generation of Javadoc style documentation, through
introspection, allowing e.g. the exploration of the class
hierarchy, available methods, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Widgets based on the HTML5 and web component standards to display
graphical views of the results of SPARQL queries, as well as populating data
structures with the results of such queries,&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;D4.16: Exploratory support for semantic-aware interactive widgets
providing views on objects of the underlying computational or
database components. Preliminary steps are demonstrated in the
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.larchenvironment.com/&quot;&gt;Larch Environment&lt;/a&gt; project (see
demo videos) and
&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jbandlow/sage-explorer&quot;&gt;sage-explorer&lt;/a&gt;. The
ultimate aim would be to automatically generate LMFDB-style
interfaces.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Whenever possible, those features will be implemented generically
for any computation kernel by extending the Jupyter protocol with
introspection and documentation queries.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;T6.9: Memoisation and production of new data&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Many CAS users run large and intensive computations, for which they
want to collect the results while simultaneously working on software
improvements. GAP retains computed attribute values of objects
within a session; Sage currently has a limited &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;cached_method&lt;/code&gt;.
Neither offers storage that is persistent across sessions or
supports publication of the result or sharing within a
collaboration. We will use, extend and contribute back to, an
appropriate established persistent memoisation infrastructure, such
as &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;python-joblib&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;redis-simple-cache&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;dogpile.cache&lt;/code&gt;, adding
features needed for storage and use of results in mathematical
research. We will design something that is simple to deploy and
configure, and makes it easy to share results in a controlled
manner, but provides enough assurance to enable the user to rely on
the data, give proper credit to the original computation and rerun
the computation if they want to.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;skills-and-background-requirements&quot;&gt;Skills and background requirements&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Strong experience in the design and practical implementation of
mathematics software: computational mathematics software (e.g.
&lt;a href=&quot;http://sagemath.org&quot;&gt;SageMath&lt;/a&gt;), knowledge management systems, or
proof systems;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;PhD in mathematics or computer science;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Experience in open-source development (collaborative development
tools, interaction with the community, …);&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Fluency in programming languages such as Scala, Python, Julia, etc
appreciated;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Strong communication skills;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Fluency in oral and written English; speaking French is not a
prerequisite.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;context&quot;&gt;Context&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The position will be funded by&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://opendreamkit.org&quot;&gt;OpenDreamKit&lt;/a&gt;, a
&lt;a href=&quot;https://ec.europa.eu/programmes/horizon2020/&quot;&gt;Horizon 2020&lt;/a&gt;
European &lt;a href=&quot;https://ec.europa.eu/programmes/horizon2020/en/h2020-section/european-research-infrastructures-including-e-infrastructures&quot;&gt;Research Infrastructure&lt;/a&gt;
project that will run for four years, starting from September&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;This project brings together the open-source computational
mathematics ecosystem – and in particular
&lt;a href=&quot;http://linalg.org/&quot;&gt;LinBox&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href=&quot;http://mpir.org&quot;&gt;MPIR&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href=&quot;http://sagemath.org/&quot;&gt;SageMath&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.gap-system.org/&quot;&gt;GAP&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href=&quot;http://pari.math.u-bordeaux.fr/&quot;&gt;PARI/GP&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href=&quot;http://lmfdb.org/&quot;&gt;LMFDB&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.singular.uni-kl.de/&quot;&gt;Singular&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href=&quot;https://mathhub.info/&quot;&gt;MathHub&lt;/a&gt;,
and the
&lt;a href=&quot;http://jupyter.org/&quot;&gt;IPython/Jupyter&lt;/a&gt; interactive computing
environment.
– toward building a
flexible toolkit for
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.2020-horizon.com/e-Infrastructures-for-virtual-research-environments-%28VRE%29-i1490.html&quot;&gt;Virtual Research Environments&lt;/a&gt;
for mathematics. Lead by Université Paris-Sud, this project involves
about 50 people spread over 15 sites in Europe, with a total budget of
about 7.6 million euros.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Within this ecosystem, the developer will work primarily on the free
open-source mathematics software system
&lt;a href=&quot;http://sagemath.org&quot;&gt;Sagemath&lt;/a&gt;. Based on the
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.python.org&quot;&gt;Python&lt;/a&gt; language and many existing open-source
math libraries, SageMath is developed since 10 years by a worldwide
community of 300 researchers, teachers and engineers, and has reached
1.5M lines of code.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The developer will work within one of the largest teams of SageMath
developers, composed essentially of researchers in mathematics and
computer science, at the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.lri.fr/&quot;&gt;Laboratoire de Recherche en
Informatique&lt;/a&gt; (LRI) and in nearby institutions.
The LRI also hosts a strong team working on proof systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;applications&quot;&gt;Applications&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To apply for this position, please send an e-mail to Nicolas.Thiery at
u-psud.fr before December 1st, with the following documents attached:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;cover_letter.pdf: a cover letter, in English (why are you interested in this particular position);&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;CV.pdf: a CV, highlighting among other things your skills and
background and your contributions to open source software;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;phd_reports.pdf: PhD reports (when applicable);&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;reference letters (each named reference_letter_.pdf),
or alternatively reference contact information.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Applications sent after December 1st will be considered until the
position is filled.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
		<author>
			<name>The OpenDreamKit consortium</name>
			<email>contact@opendreamkit.org</email>
			<uri>http://opendreamkit.org/</uri>
		</author>
		<source>
			<title type="html">OpenDreamKit</title>
			<link rel="self" href="http://opendreamkit.org/atom.xml"/>
			<id>http://opendreamkit.org/</id>
			<updated>2018-03-19T23:01:26+00:00</updated>
		</source>
	</entry>

	<entry>
		<title type="html">Presentation of OpenDreamKit</title>
		<link href="http://opendreamkit.org/2017/10/19/Netmath/"/>
		<id>http://opendreamkit.org/2017/10/19/Netmath</id>
		<updated>2017-10-19T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Viviane Pons presented the OpenDreamKit project and its impact for teaching to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.netmath.de/&quot;&gt;Netmath community&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lri.fr/~pons/docs/2017_Kaiserslautern.pdf&quot;&gt;Slides&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content>
		<author>
			<name>The OpenDreamKit consortium</name>
			<email>contact@opendreamkit.org</email>
			<uri>http://opendreamkit.org/</uri>
		</author>
		<source>
			<title type="html">OpenDreamKit</title>
			<link rel="self" href="http://opendreamkit.org/atom.xml"/>
			<id>http://opendreamkit.org/</id>
			<updated>2018-03-19T23:01:26+00:00</updated>
		</source>
	</entry>

	<entry>
		<title type="html">WP6 Math-in-the-Middle Integration Use Case to be Published at MACIS-2017 (two papers)</title>
		<link href="http://opendreamkit.org/2017/10/15/WP6-Usecase/"/>
		<id>http://opendreamkit.org/2017/10/15/WP6-Usecase</id>
		<updated>2017-10-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;OpenDreamKit WP6 (Data/Knowledge/Software-Bases) has reported on the first use cases in
two papers to be publised at &lt;a href=&quot;https://macis2017.sba-research.org/&quot;&gt;MACIS 2017&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/OpenDreamKit/OpenDreamKit/blob/master/WP6/MACIS17-interop/crc.pdf&quot;&gt;Knowledge-Based Interoperability for Mathematical Software Systems&lt;/a&gt; (Michael Kohlhase, Luca Defeo, Dennis Müller, Markus Pfeiffer, Florian Rabe, Nicolas M. Thiéry, Victor Vasilyxev, and Tom Wiesing) develops the Math-in-the-Middle Ontology for computational group theory and shows a three-system use case (Sage, GAP, Singular).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/OpenDreamKit/OpenDreamKit/blob/master/WP6/MACIS17-vt/crc.pdf&quot;&gt;Virtual Theories - A Uniform Interface to Mathematical Knowledge Bases&lt;/a&gt; (Tom Wiesing, Michael Kohlhase, and Florian Rabe) extends the MMT theories to “Virtual theories”, which do not have the “load-into-memory-fully” restrictions of “concrete theories” and are therefore suited for very large data sources like the &lt;a href=&quot;http://lmfdb.org&quot;&gt;LMFDB&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;http://opendreamkit.org/oeis.org&quot;&gt;OEIS&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content>
		<author>
			<name>The OpenDreamKit consortium</name>
			<email>contact@opendreamkit.org</email>
			<uri>http://opendreamkit.org/</uri>
		</author>
		<source>
			<title type="html">OpenDreamKit</title>
			<link rel="self" href="http://opendreamkit.org/atom.xml"/>
			<id>http://opendreamkit.org/</id>
			<updated>2018-03-19T23:01:26+00:00</updated>
		</source>
	</entry>

	<entry>
		<title type="html">Release: SageMath for Windows</title>
		<link href="http://opendreamkit.org/2017/10/11/SageWindows/"/>
		<id>http://opendreamkit.org/2017/10/11/SageWindows</id>
		<updated>2017-10-11T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<content type="html">&lt;h1 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the main tasks for OpenDreamKit
(&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/OpenDreamKit/OpenDreamKit/issues/50&quot;&gt;T.31&lt;/a&gt;]) is
improving portability of mathematical software across hardware platforms and
operating systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One particular such challenge, which has dogged the SageMath project
practically since its inception, is getting a fully working port of Sage on
Windows (and by extension this would mean working Windows versions of all
the CAS’s and other software Sage depends on, such as GAP, Singular, etc.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is particularly challenging, not so much because of the Sage Python
library (which has some, but relatively little system-specific code).
Rather, the challenge is in porting all of Sage’s 150+ standard
dependencies, and ensuring that they integrate well on Windows, with a
passing test suite.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although UNIX-like systems are popular among open source software developers
and some academics, the desktop and laptop market share of Windows computers
is estimated to be &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Usage_share_of_operating_systems#Desktop_and_laptop_computers&quot;&gt;more than
75%&lt;/a&gt;
and is an important source of potential users, especially students.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, for most of its existence, the only way to “install” Sage on
Windows was to run a Linux virtual machine that came pre-installed with
Sage, which is made available on Sage’s downloads page.  This is clumsy and
onerous for users–it forces them to work within an unfamiliar OS, and it
can be difficult and confusing to connect files and directories in their
host OS to files and directories inside the VM, and likewise for web-based
applications like the notebook.  Because of this Windows users can feel like
second-class citizens in the Sage ecosystem, and this may turn them away
from Sage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Attempts at Windows support almost as old as Sage itself (initial Sage
release in 2005). Microsoft offered funding to work on Windows version &lt;a href=&quot;https://groups.google.com/d/msg/sage-devel/LTWgQ_24cPs/WW25BGe7KjwJ&quot;&gt;as
far back as
2007&lt;/a&gt;
but was far too little for the amount of effort needed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additional work done was done off and on through 2012, and partial support
was possible at times. This included admirable work to try to support
building with the native Windows development toolchain (e.g. MSVC).  There
was even at one time an earlier version of a Sage installer for Windows, but
long since abandoned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, Sage development (and more importantly Sage’s dependencies)
continued to advance faster than there were resources for the work on
Windows support to keep up, and work mostly stalled after 2013.
OpenDreamKit has provided a unique opportunity to fund the kind of sustained
effort needed for Sage’s Windows support to catch up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;sage-for-windows-overview&quot;&gt;Sage for Windows overview&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As of SageMath version 8.0, Sage will be available for 64-bit versions of
Windows 7 and up.  It can be downloaded through the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sagemath.org/download-windows.html&quot;&gt;SageMath
website&lt;/a&gt;, and up-to-date
installation instructions are being developed at the &lt;a href=&quot;http://wiki.sagemath.org/SageWindows&quot;&gt;SageMath
wiki&lt;/a&gt;.  A 32-bit version had been
planned as well, but is on hold due to technical limitations that will be
discussed later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The installer contains all software and documentation making up the standard
Sage distribution, all libraries needed for Cygwin support, a bash shell,
numerous standard UNIX command-line utilities, and the
&lt;a href=&quot;https://mintty.github.io/&quot;&gt;Mintty&lt;/a&gt; terminal emulator, which is generally
more user-friendly and better suited for Cygwin software than the standard
Windows console.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is distributed in the form of a single-file executable installer, with a
familiar install wizard interface (built with the venerable
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.jrsoftware.org/isinfo.php&quot;&gt;InnoSetup&lt;/a&gt;.  The installer comes in
at just under a gigabyte, but unpacks to more than 4.5 GB in version 8.0.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://opendreamkit.org/public/images/2017-10-11-SageWindows/installer1.png&quot; alt=&quot;Sage for Windows Installer&quot; class=&quot;img-responsive&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://opendreamkit.org/public/images/2017-10-11-SageWindows/installer2.png&quot; alt=&quot;Sage for Windows Installer&quot; class=&quot;img-responsive&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because of the large number of files comprising the complete SageMath
distribution, and the heavy compression of the installer, installation can
take a fair amount of time even on a recent system.  On my Intel i7 laptop
it takes about ten minutes, but results will vary.  Fortunately, this has
not yet been a source of complaints–beta testers have been content to run
the installer in the background while doing other work–on a modern
multi-core machine the installer itself does not use overly many resources.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you don’t like it, there’s also a standard uninstall:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://opendreamkit.org/public/images/2017-10-11-SageWindows/uninstall.png&quot; alt=&quot;Sage for Windows Uninstaller&quot; class=&quot;img-responsive&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The installer include three desktop and/or start menu shortcuts:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://opendreamkit.org/public/images/2017-10-11-SageWindows/shortcuts.png&quot; alt=&quot;Sage for Windows start menu shortcuts&quot; class=&quot;img-responsive&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The shortcut titled just “SageMath 8.0” launches the standard Sage command
prompt in a text-based console. In general it integrates well enough with
the Windows shell to launch files with the default viewer for those file
types. For example, plots are saved to files and displayed automatically
with the default image viewer registered on the computer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://opendreamkit.org/public/images/2017-10-11-SageWindows/console.png&quot; alt=&quot;Sage for Windows console&quot; class=&quot;img-responsive&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Because Mintty supports &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sixel&quot;&gt;SIXEL&lt;/a&gt; mode
graphics, it may also be possible to embed plots and equations directly in
the console, but this has not been made to work yet with Sage.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“SageMath Shell” runs a bash shell with the environment set up to
run software in the Sage distribution.  More advanced users, or users who
wish to directly use other software included in the Sage distribution (e.g.
GAP, Singular) without going through the Sage interface.  Finally,
“SageMath Notebook” starts a Jupyter Notebook server with Sage configured as
the default kernel and, where possible, opens the Notebook interface in the
user’s browser.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In principle this could also be used as a development environment for doing
development of Sage and/or Sage extensions on Windows, but the current
installer is geared primarily just for users.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;rationale-for-cygwin-and-possible-alternatives&quot;&gt;Rationale for Cygwin and possible alternatives&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are a few possible routes to supporting Sage on Windows, of which
Cygwin is just one.  For example, before restarting work on the Cygwin port
I experimented with a solution that would run Sage on Windows using
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.docker.com/&quot;&gt;Docker&lt;/a&gt;.  I built an installer for Sage that would
install Docker for Windows if it was not already installed, install and
configure a pre-build Sage image for Docker, and install some desktop
shortcuts that attempted to launch Sage in Docker as transparently as
possible to the user.  That is, it would ensure that Docker was running,
that a container for the Sage image was running, and then would redirect I/O
to the Docker container.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This approach “worked”, but was still fairly clumsy and error-prone.  In
order to make the experience as transparent as possible a fair amount of
automation of Docker was needed.  This could get particularly tricky in
cases where the user also uses Docker directly, and accidentally interferes
with the Sage Docker installation.  Handling issues like file system and
network port mapping, while possible, was even more complicated.  What’s
worse, running Linux images in Docker for Windows still requires
virtualization.  On older versions this meant running VirtualBox in the
background, while newer versions require the Hyper-V hypervisor (which is
not available on all versions of Windows–particularly “Home” versions).
Furthermore, this requires hardware-assisted virtualization (HAV) to be
enabled in the user’s BIOS.  This typically does not come enabled by default
on home PCs, and users must manually enable it in their BIOS menu.  We did
not consider this a reasonable step to ask of users merely to “install
Sage”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another approach, which was looked at in the early efforts to port Sage to
Windows, would be to get Sage and all its dependencies building with the
standard Microsoft toolchain (MSVC, etc.).  This would mean both porting the
code to work natively on Windows, using the MSVC runtime, as well as
developing build systems compatible with MSVC.  There was a time when,
remarkably, many of Sage’s dependencies did meet these requirements.  But
since then the number of dependencies has grown too much, and Sage itself
become too dependent on the GNU toolchain, that this would be an almost
impossible undertaking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A middle ground between MSVC and Cygwin would be to build Sage using the
MinGW toolchain, which is a port of GNU build tools (including binutils,
gcc, make, autoconf, etc.) as well as some other common UNIX tools like the
bash shell to Windows.  Unlike Cygwin, MinGW does not provide emulation of
POSIX or Linux system APIs–it just provides a Windows-native port of the
development tools.  Many of Sage’s dependencies would still need to be
updated in order to work natively on Windows, but at the very least their
build systems would require relatively little updating–not much more than
is required for Cygwin.  This would actually be my preferred approach, and
with enough time and resources it could probably work.  However, it would
still require a significant amount of work to port some of Sage’s more
non-trivial dependencies, such as GAP and Singular, to work on Windows
without some POSIX emulation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So Cygwin is the path of least resistance.  Although bugs and shortcomings
in Cygwin itself occasionally require some effort to work around (as a
developer–users should not have to think about it), for the most part it
&lt;em&gt;just works&lt;/em&gt; with software written for UNIX-like systems.  It also has the
advantage of providing a full UNIX-like shell experience, so shell scripts
and scripts that use UNIX shell tools will work even on Windows.  However,
since it works directly on the native filesystem, there is less opportunity
for confusion regarding where files and folders are saved.  In fact, Cygwin
supports both Windows-style paths (starting with &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;C:\\&lt;/code&gt;) and UNIX-style
paths (in this case starting with &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;C:/&lt;/code&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, a note on the Windows Subsystem for Linux (WSL), which debuted
shortly after I began my Cygwin porting efforts, as I often get asked about
this: “Why not ‘just’ use the ‘bash for Windows’?”  The WSL is a new effort
by Microsoft to allow running executables built for Linux directly on
Windows, with full support from the Windows kernel for emulation of Linux
system calls (including ones like &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;fork()&lt;/code&gt;).  Basically, it aims to provide
all the functionality of Cygwin, but with full support from the kernel, and
the ability to run Linux binaries directly, without having to recompile
them.  This is great of course. So the question is asked if Sage can run in
this environment, and experiments suggest that it works pretty well
(although the WSL is still under active development and has room for
improvement).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wrote more about the WSL in a &lt;a href=&quot;http://opendreamkit.org/2016/10/04/emerging-technologies-wsl/&quot;&gt;blog
post&lt;/a&gt; last
year, which also addresses why we can’t “just” use it for Sage for Windows.
But in short: 1) The WSL is currently only intended as a developer tool:
There’s no way to package Windows software for end users such that it uses
the WSL transparently.  And 2) It’s only available on recent updates of
Windows 10–it will never be available on older Windows versions.  So to
reach the most users, and provide the most hassle-free user experience, the
WSL is not currently a solution.  However, it may still prove useful for
developers as a way to do Sage &lt;em&gt;development&lt;/em&gt; on Windows. And in the future
it may be the easiest way to install UNIX-based software on Windows as well,
especially if Microsoft ever expands its scope.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;development-challenges&quot;&gt;Development challenges&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main challenge with porting Sage to Windows/Cygwin has relatively little
to do with the Sage library itself, which is written almost entirely in
Python/Cython and involves relatively few system interfaces (a notable
exception to this is the advanced signal handling provided by
&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/sagemath/cysignals&quot;&gt;Cysignals&lt;/a&gt;, but this has been found
to work almost flawlessly on Cygwin thanks to the Cygwin developers’ heroic
efforts in emulating POSIX signal handling on Windows).  Rather, most of the
effort has gone into build and portability issues with Sage’s more than 150
dependencies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The majority of issues have been build-related issues.  Runtime issues are
less common, as many of Sage’s dependencies are primarily mathematical,
numerical code–mostly CPU-bound algorithms that have little use of
platform-specific APIs.  Another reason is that, although there are some
anomalous cases, Cygwin’s emulation of POSIX (and some Linux) interfaces is
good enough that most existing code just works as-is.  However, because
applications built in Cygwin are native Windows applications and DLLs, there
are Windows-specific subtleties that come up when building some non-trivial
software.  So most of the challenge has been getting all of Sage’s
dependencies building cleanly on Cygwin, and then &lt;em&gt;maintaining&lt;/em&gt; that support
(as the maintainers of most of these dependencies are not themselves testing
against Cygwin regularly).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, maintenance was the most difficult aspect of the Cygwin port (and
this is one of the main reasons past efforts failed–without a sustained
effort it was not possible to keep up with the pace of Sage development).  I
had a snapshot of Sage that was fully working on Cygwin, with all tests
passing, as soon as the end of summer in 2016.  That is, I started with one
version of Sage and added to it all the fixes needed for that version to
work.  However, by the time that work was done, there were many new
developments to Sage that I had to redo my work on top of, and there were
many new issues to fix.  This cycle repeated itself a number of times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;continuous-integration&quot;&gt;Continuous integration&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The critical component that was missing for creating a sustainable Cygwin
port of Sage was a &lt;em&gt;patchbot&lt;/em&gt; for Cygwin.  The Sage developers maintain a
(volunteer) army of patchbots–computers running a number of different OS
and hardware platforms that perform continuous integration testing of all
proposed software changes to Sage.  The patchbots are able, ideally, to
catch changes that break Sage–possibly only on specific platforms–before
they are merged into the main development branch.  Without a patchbot
testing changes on Cygwin, there was no way to stop changes from being
merged that broke Cygwin.  With some effort I managed to get a Windows VM
with Cygwin running reliably on UPSud’s OpenStack infrastructure, that
could run a Cygwin patchbot for Sage.  By continuing to monitor this
patchbot the Sage community can now receive prior warning if/when a change
will break the Cygwin port.  I expect this will impact only a small number
of changes–in particular those that update one of Sage’s dependencies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In so doing we are, indirectly, providing continuous integration on Cygwin
for Sage’s many dependencies–something most of those projects do not have
the resources to do on their own.  So this should be considered a service to
the open source software community at large. (I am also planning to
piggyback on the work I did for Sage to provide a Cygwin buildbot for
Python–this will be important moving forward as the official Python source
tree has been broken on Cygwin for some time, but is one of the most
critical dependencies for Sage).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;runtime-bugs&quot;&gt;Runtime bugs&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All that said, a few of the runtime bugs that come up are non-trivial as
well.  One particular source of bugs is subtle synchronization issues in
multi-process code, that arise primarily due to the large overhead of
creating, destroying, and signalling processes on Cygwin, as compared to
most UNIXes.  Other problems arise in areas of behavior that are not
specified by the POSIX standard, and assumptions are made that might hold on,
say, Linux, but that do not hold on Cygwin (but that are still
POSIX-compliant!)  For example, a difference in (undocumented, in both
cases) memory management between Linux and Cygwin made for a particularly
challenging &lt;a href=&quot;https://trac.sagemath.org/ticket/22633&quot;&gt;bug in PARI&lt;/a&gt;.
Another &lt;a href=&quot;https://trac.sagemath.org/ticket/21388&quot;&gt;interesting bug&lt;/a&gt; came up in
a test that invoked a stack overflow bug in Python, which only came up on
Cygwin due to the smaller default stack size of programs compiled for
Windows.  There are also occasional bugs due to small differences in
numerical results, due to the different implementation of the standard C
math routines on Cygwin, versus GNU libc.  So one should not come away with
the impression that porting software as complex as Sage and its dependencies
to Cygwin is completely trivial, nor that similar bugs might not arise in
the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;challenges-with-32-bit-windowscygwin&quot;&gt;Challenges with 32-bit Windows/Cygwin&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The original work of porting Sage to Cygwin focused on the 32-bit version of
Cygwin.  In fact, at the time that was the only version of Cygwin–the first
release of the 64-bit version of Cygwin was not until 2013.  When I picked
up work on this again I focused on 64-bit Cygwin–most software developers
today are working primarily on 64-bit systems, and so from many projects
I’ve worked on the past my experience has been that they have been more
stable on 64-bit systems.  I figured this would likely be true for Sage and
its dependencies as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, after getting Sage working on 64-bit Cygwin, when it came time to
test on 32-bit Cygwin I hit some significant snags.  Without going into too
many technical details, the main problem is that 32-bit Windows applications
have a user address space limited to just 2 GB (or 3 GB with a special boot
flag).  This is in fact not enough to fit all of Sage into memory at once.
The good news is that for most cases one would never try to use all of Sage
at once–this is only an issue if one tries to load every library in both
Sage, and all its dependencies, into the same address space.  In practical
use this is rare, though this limit can be hit while running the Sage test
suite.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With some care, such as reserving address space for the most likely to be
used (especially simultaneously) libraries in Sage, we can work around this
problem for the average user.  But the result may still not be 100% stable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It becomes a valid question whether it’s worth the effort.  There are
unfortunately few publicly available statistics on the current market share
of 64-bit versus 32-bit Windows versions among desktop users.  Very few new
desktops and laptops sold anymore to the consumer market include 32-bit
OSes, but it is still not too uncommon to find on some older, lower-end
laptops.  In particular, some laptops sold not too long ago with Windows 7
were 32-bit.  According to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.netmarketshare.com/operating-system-market-share.aspx?qprid=10&amp;qpcustomd=0&quot;&gt;Net Market
Share&lt;/a&gt;,
as of writing Windows 7 still makes up nearly 50% of all desktop operating
system installments.  This still does not tell us about 32-bit versus
64-bit.  The popular (&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.gamespot.com/articles/steam-reaches-new-concurrent-user-record/1100-6431895/&quot;&gt;12.5 million concurrent
users&lt;/a&gt;)
Steam PC gaming platform publishes the results of their &lt;a href=&quot;http://store.steampowered.com/hwsurvey/&quot;&gt;usage statistics
survey&lt;/a&gt;, which as of writing shows
barely over 5% of users with 32-bit versions of Windows.  However, computer
gamers are not likely to be representative of the overall market, being more
likely to upgrade their software and hardware.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So until some specific demand for a 32-bit version of SageMath for Windows
is heard, we will not likely invest more effort into it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;conclusion-and-future-work&quot;&gt;Conclusion and future work&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Focusing on Cygwin for porting Sage to Windows was definitely the right way
to go.  It took me only a few months in the summer of 2016 to get the vast
majority of the work done.  The rest was just a question of keeping up with
changes to Sage and fixing more bugs (this required enough constant effort
that it’s no wonder nobody managed to quite do it before).  Now, however,
enough issues have been addressed that the Windows version has remained
fairly stable, even in the face of ongoing updates to Sage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Porting more of Sage’s dependencies to build with MinGW and without Cygwin
might still be a worthwhile effort, as Cygwin adds some overhead in a few
areas, but if we had started with that it would have been too much effort.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the near future, however, the priority needs to be improvements to user
experience of the Windows Installer.  In particular, a better solution is
needed for installing Sage’s optional packages on Windows (preferably
without needing to compile them). And an improved experience for using Sage
in the Jupyter Notebook, such that the Notebook server can run in the
background as a Windows Service, would be nice. This feature would not be
specific to Sage either, and could benefit all users of the Jupyter Notebook
on Windows.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, I need to better document the process of doing Sage development on
Cygwin, including the typical kinds of problems that arise.  I also need to
better document how to set up and maintain the Cygwin patchbot, and how to
build releases of the Sage on Windows installer so that its maintenance does
not fall solely on my shoulders.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
		<author>
			<name>The OpenDreamKit consortium</name>
			<email>contact@opendreamkit.org</email>
			<uri>http://opendreamkit.org/</uri>
		</author>
		<source>
			<title type="html">OpenDreamKit</title>
			<link rel="self" href="http://opendreamkit.org/atom.xml"/>
			<id>http://opendreamkit.org/</id>
			<updated>2018-03-19T23:01:26+00:00</updated>
		</source>
	</entry>

	<entry>
		<title type="html">DataDog's pricing: don't make the same mistake I made</title>
		<link href="http://sagemath.blogspot.com/2016/07/datadogs-pricing-dont-make-same-mistake.html"/>
		<id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-6365588202025292315.post-6949985998313614355</id>
		<updated>2017-09-22T13:03:54+00:00</updated>
		<content type="html">(I wrote a 1-year &lt;a href=&quot;http://sagemath.blogspot.com/2017/09/datadog-dont-make-same-mistake-i-did.html&quot;&gt;followup post here.&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;I stupidly made a mistake recently by choosing to use &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.datadoghq.com/&quot;&gt;DataDog&lt;/a&gt; for monitoring the infrastructure for my startup (&lt;a href=&quot;https://cloud.sagemath.com/&quot;&gt;SageMathCloud&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;I got bit by their pricing UI design that looks similar to many other sites, but is different in a way that caused me to &lt;strong&gt;spend far more money than I expected.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;I'm writing this post so that you won't make the same mistake I did. &amp;nbsp;As a product, DataDog is of course a lot of hard work to create, and they can try to charge whatever they want. However, my problem is that &lt;strong&gt;what&lt;/strong&gt; they are going to charge was confusing and misleading to me.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;I wanted to see some nice web-based data about my new autoscaled Kubernetes cluster, so I looked around at options. DataDog looked like a new and awesomely-priced service for seeing live logging. And when I looked (not carefully enough) at the pricing, it looked like only $15/month to monitor a bunch of machines. I'm naive about the cost of cloud monitoring -- I've been using Stackdriver on Google cloud platform for years, which is completely free (for now, though that will change), and I've also used self hosted open solutions, and some quite nice solutions I've written myself. So my expectations were way out of whack.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Ever busy, I signed up for the &quot;$15/month plan&quot;:&lt;br /&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;separator&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://1.bp.blogspot.com/-NK09JkZDOD0/V5Jyf6jYy2I/AAAAAAABYNA/l_LP-NJv6hgODAvvaO868frbtJ4hP9SUQCLcB/s1600/dd-pricing.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img border=&quot;0&quot; height=&quot;225&quot; src=&quot;https://1.bp.blogspot.com/-NK09JkZDOD0/V5Jyf6jYy2I/AAAAAAABYNA/l_LP-NJv6hgODAvvaO868frbtJ4hP9SUQCLcB/s400/dd-pricing.png&quot; width=&quot;400&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;One of the people on my team spent a little time and installed datadog on all the VM's in our cluster, and also made DataDog automatically start running on any nodes in our Kubernetes cluster. That's a lot of machines.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Today I got the first monthly bill, which is for the month that just happened. The cost was $639.19 USD charged to my credit card. I was really confused for a while, wondering if I had bought a year subscription.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;separator&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://3.bp.blogspot.com/-LK7iRxeqMKI/V5JymhrBN-I/AAAAAAABYNE/lCA0YC3cfSMJ9LuTsFgsrt8vTUR4rvRIQCLcB/s1600/dd-invoice.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img border=&quot;0&quot; height=&quot;198&quot; src=&quot;https://3.bp.blogspot.com/-LK7iRxeqMKI/V5JymhrBN-I/AAAAAAABYNE/lCA0YC3cfSMJ9LuTsFgsrt8vTUR4rvRIQCLcB/s400/dd-invoice.png&quot; width=&quot;400&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;After a while I realized that the cost is per host! When I looked at the pricing page the first time, I had just saw in big letters &quot;$15&quot;, and &quot;$18 month-to-month&quot; and &quot;up to 500 hosts&quot;. I completely missed the &quot;Per Host&quot; line, because I was so naive that I didn't think the price could possibly be that high.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;I tried immediately to delete my credit card and cancel my plan, but the &quot;Remove Card&quot; button is greyed out, and it says you can &quot;modify your subscription by contacting us at success@datadoghq.com&quot;:&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;separator&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://3.bp.blogspot.com/-iohuYjKf3_A/V5JzPDN7qHI/AAAAAAABYNM/QBn6pqJ_OL0roteJIyxHWx5wajJRs4_EwCLcB/s1600/dd-cancel.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img border=&quot;0&quot; height=&quot;318&quot; src=&quot;https://3.bp.blogspot.com/-iohuYjKf3_A/V5JzPDN7qHI/AAAAAAABYNM/QBn6pqJ_OL0roteJIyxHWx5wajJRs4_EwCLcB/s400/dd-cancel.png&quot; width=&quot;400&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;So I wrote to success@datadoghq.com:&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;Dear Datadog,&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Everybody on my team was completely mislead by your&lt;br /&gt;horrible pricing description.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Please cancel the subscription for wstein immediately&lt;br /&gt;and remove my credit card from your system.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;This is the first time I've wasted this much money&lt;br /&gt;by being misled by a website in my life.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;I'm also very unhappy that I can't delete my credit&lt;br /&gt;card or cancel my subscription via your website.  It's&lt;br /&gt;like one more stripe API call to remove the credit card&lt;br /&gt;(I know -- I implemented this same feature for my site).&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;hr /&gt;And they responded:&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;Thanks for reaching out. If you'd like to cancel your&lt;br /&gt;Datadog subscription, you're able to do so by going into&lt;br /&gt;the platform under 'Plan and Usage' and choose the option&lt;br /&gt;downgrade to 'Lite', that will insure your credit card&lt;br /&gt;will not be charged in the future. Please be sure to&lt;br /&gt;reduce your host count down to the (5) allowed under&lt;br /&gt;the 'Lite' plan - those are the maximum allowed for&lt;br /&gt;the free plan.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Also, please note you'll be charged for the hosts&lt;br /&gt;monitored through this month. Please take a look at&lt;br /&gt;our billing FAQ.&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;They were right -- I was able to uninstall the daemons, downgrade to Lite, remove my card, etc. all through the website without manual intervention.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;When people have been confused with billing for &lt;a href=&quot;https://cloud.sagemath.com/&quot;&gt;my site&lt;/a&gt;, I have apologized, immediately refunded their money, and opened a ticket to make the UI clearer. &amp;nbsp;DataDog didn't do any of that.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;I wish DataDog would at least clearly state that when you use their service you are potentially on the hook for an &lt;strong&gt;arbitrarily large&lt;/strong&gt; charge for any month. Yes, if they had made that clear, they wouldn't have had me as a customer, so they are not incentivized to do so.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;A fool and their money are soon parted. I hope this post reduces the chances you'll be a fool like me. &amp;nbsp;If you chose to use DataDog, and their monitoring tools are very impressive, I hope you'll be aware of the cost.  &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;ADDED:&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;On &lt;a href=&quot;https://news.ycombinator.com/threads?id=williamstein&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Hacker News&lt;/a&gt; somebody asked: &quot;&lt;span&gt;How could their pricing page be clearer? It says per host in fairly large letters underneath it.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;I'm asking because I will be designing a similar page soon (that's also billed per host) and I'd like to avoid the same mistakes.&quot; &amp;nbsp;My answer:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;[EDIT: This pricing page by the top poster in this thread is way better than I suggest below -- https://www.serverdensity.com/pricing/]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;1.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;span&gt;VERY clearly&lt;/span&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;nbsp;state that when you sign up for the service, then you are on the hook for up to $18*500 = $9000 + tax in charges for any month. Even Google compute engine (and Amazon) don't create such a trap, and have a clear explicit quota increase process.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;div&gt;2. Instead of &quot;HUGE $15&quot; newline &quot;(small light) per host&quot;, put &quot;HUGE $18 per host&quot; all on the same line. It would easily fit. I don't even know how the $15/host datadog discount could ever really work, given that the number of hosts might constantly change and there is no prepayment.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;3. Inform users clearly in the UI at any time how much they are going to owe for that month (so far), rather than surprising them at the end. Again, Google Cloud Platform has a very clear running total in their billing section, and any time you create a new VM it gives the exact amount that VM will cost per month.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;4. If one works with a team, 3 is especially important. The reason that I had monitors on 50+ machines is that another person working on the project, who never looked at pricing or anything, just thought -- he I'll just set this up everywhere. He had no idea there was a per-machine fee.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;comment&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;c00&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;reply&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;comment&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;c00&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;u&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://news.ycombinator.com/reply?id=12146416&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D12145879%2312146416&quot;&gt;reply&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/u&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;comment&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;c00&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;</content>
		<author>
			<name>William Stein</name>
			<email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
			<uri>http://sagemath.blogspot.com/</uri>
		</author>
		<source>
			<title type="html">Sage: Open Source Mathematics Software</title>
			<subtitle type="html">This is my blog about things related to Sage.</subtitle>
			<link rel="self" href="http://sagemath.blogspot.com/feeds/posts/default"/>
			<id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-6365588202025292315</id>
			<updated>2018-03-08T00:05:15+00:00</updated>
		</source>
	</entry>

	<entry>
		<title type="html">DataDog: Don't make the same mistake I did -- a followup and thoughts about very unhappy customers</title>
		<link href="http://sagemath.blogspot.com/2017/09/datadog-dont-make-same-mistake-i-did.html"/>
		<id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-6365588202025292315.post-8893535883917863217</id>
		<updated>2017-09-22T12:32:15+00:00</updated>
		<content type="html">This is a followup to &lt;a href=&quot;http://sagemath.blogspot.com/2016/07/datadogs-pricing-dont-make-same-mistake.html&quot;&gt;my previous blog post about DataDog billing&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;TL;DR:&lt;br /&gt;- I don't recommend DataDog,&lt;br /&gt;- dealing with unhappy customers is hard,&lt;br /&gt;- monitoring for data science nerds?&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=15315028&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Hacker News Comments&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;datadog-at-google-cloud-summit&quot;&gt;DataDog at Google Cloud Summit&lt;/h2&gt;I was recently at the &lt;a href=&quot;https://cloudplatformonline.com/summit-seattle-2017.html&quot;&gt;Seattle Google Cloud Summit&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.datadoghq.com/&quot;&gt;DataDog&lt;/a&gt; was well represented, with the biggest booth and top vendor billing during the keynote. Clearly they are doing something right. I had a past &lt;a href=&quot;http://sagemath.blogspot.com/2016/07/datadogs-pricing-dont-make-same-mistake.html&quot;&gt;unpleasant experience&lt;/a&gt; with them, and I had just been auditing my records and discovered that last year DataDog had actually charged me a&lt;b&gt; lot &lt;/b&gt;more than I thought, so was kind of annoyed. Nonetheless, they kept coming up and talking to me, server monitoring is life-and-death important to me, and their actual software is very impressive in some ways.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Nick Parisi started talking with me about DataDog. He sincerely wanted to know about my past experience with monitoring and the DataDog product, which he was clearly very enthuisiastic about. So I told him a bit, and he encouraged me to tell him more, explaining that he did not work at DataDog last year, and that he would like to know what happened. So he gave me his email, and he was &lt;em&gt;very genuinely concerned and helpful&lt;/em&gt;, so I sent him an email with a link to my post, etc. I didn't receive a response, so a week later I asked why, and received a followup email from Jay Robichau, who is DataDog's Director of Sales.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;conference-call-with-datadog&quot;&gt;Conference Call with DataDog&lt;/h2&gt;Jay setup a conference call with me today at 10am (September 22, 2017). Before the call, I sent him a summary of my blog post, and also requested a refund, especially for the suprise bill they sent me nearly 6 weeks after my post.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;During the call, Jay explained that he was &quot;protecting&quot; Nick from me, and that I would mostly talk with Michelle Danis who is in charge of customer success. My expectation for the call is that we would find some common ground, and that they would at least appreciate the chance to make things right and talk with an unhappy customer. I was also curious about how a successful startup company addresses the concerns of an unhappy customer (me).&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;I expected the conversation to be difficult but go well, with me writing a post singing the praises of the charming DataDog sales and customer success people. A few weeks ago &lt;a href=&quot;https://cocalc.com/&quot;&gt;CoCalc.com&lt;/a&gt; (my employer) had a very unhappy customer who got (rightfully) angry over a miscommunication, told us he would no longer use our product, and would definitely not recommend it to anybody else. I wrote to him wanting to at least continue the discussion and help, but he was completely gone. &lt;em&gt;I would do absolutely anything I could to ensure he is a satisfied, if only he would give me the chance.&lt;/em&gt; Also, there was &lt;a href=&quot;https://cre8math.com/2017/08/27/to-processing-i/comment-page-1/&quot;&gt;a recent blog post&lt;/a&gt; from somebody unhappy with using CoCalc/Sage for graphics, and I reached out to them as best I could to at least clarify things...&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;In any case, here's what DataDog charged us as a result of us running their daemon on a few dozen containers in our Kubernetes cluster (a contractor who is not a native English speaker actually setup these monitors for us):&lt;br /&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;07/22/2016  449215JWJH87S8N4  DATADOG 866-329-4466 NY  $639.19&lt;br /&gt;08/29/2016  2449215L2JH87V8WZ DATADOG 866-329-4466 NY  $927.22&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;br /&gt;I was shocked by the 07/22 bill which spured my post, and discovered the 8/29 one only later. We canceled our subscription on July 22 (cancelling was difficult in itself).&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Michelle started the conference call by explaining that the 08/29 bill was for charges incurred before 07/22, and that &lt;strong&gt;their billing system has over a month lag&lt;/strong&gt; (and it does even today, unlike Google Cloud Platform, say). Then Michelle explained at length many of the changes that DataDog has made to their software to address the issues I (and others?) have pointed out with their pricing description and billing. She was very interested in whether I would be a DataDog customer in the future, and when I said no, she explained that they would not refund my money since the bill was not a mistake.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;I asked if they now provide a periodic summary of the upcoming bill, as Google cloud platform (say) does. She said that today they don't, though they are working on it. They do now provide a summary of usage so far in an admin page.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Finally, I explained in no uncertain terms that I felt misled by their pricing. I expected that they would understand, and pointed out that they had just described to me many ways in which they were addressing this very problem. Very surprisingly, Michelle's response was that she absolutely would not agree that there was any problem with their pricing description a year ago, and they definitely would not refund my money. She kept bringing up the terms of service. I agreed that I didn't think legally they were in the wrong, given what she had explained, just that -- as they had just pointed out -- their pricing and billing was unclear in various ways. They would not agree at all.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I can't recommend doing business with DataDog. I had very much hoped to write the opposite in this updated post. Unfortunately, their pricing and terms are still confusing today compared to competitors, and they are unforgiving of mistakes. This dog bites. &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;(&lt;strong&gt;Disclaimer:&lt;/strong&gt; I took notes during the call, but most of the above is from memory, and I probably misheard or misunderstood something. I invite comments from DataDog to set the record straight.)&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Also, for what it is worth, I definitely&amp;nbsp;&lt;b&gt;do&amp;nbsp;&lt;/b&gt;recommend Google Cloud Platform. &amp;nbsp;They put in the effort to do many things right regarding clear billing.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-do-startups-deal-with-unhappy-customers&quot;&gt;How do Startups Deal with Unhappy Customers?&lt;/h2&gt;I am very curious about how other&lt;b&gt;&lt;i&gt; startups&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/b&gt; deal with unhappy customers. At CoCalc we have had very few &quot;major incidents&quot; yet... but I want to be as prepared as possible. At the Google Cloud Summit, I went to some amazing &quot;war storries by SRE's&quot; session in which they talked about situations they had been in years ago in which their decisions meant the difference between whether they would have a company or job tomorrow or not. These guys clearly have amazing instincts for when a problem was do-or-die serious and when it wasn't. And their deep preparation &quot;in depth&quot; was WHY they were on that stage, and a big reason why older companies like Google are still around. Having a strategy for addressing very angry customers is surely just as important.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;separator&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-91tgUApR4-0/WcVgtf2unPI/AAAAAAABZbA/i2UM_kTIEiQNgKw6qXepuG0c-LKA1SiUQCK4BGAYYCw/s1600/sre.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img border=&quot;0&quot; height=&quot;170&quot; src=&quot;https://3.bp.blogspot.com/-91tgUApR4-0/WcVgtf2unPI/AAAAAAABZbA/i2UM_kTIEiQNgKw6qXepuG0c-LKA1SiUQCK4BGAYYCw/s400/sre.jpg&quot; width=&quot;400&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;center&gt; &lt;b&gt;Google SRE's&lt;/b&gt;: these guys are serious. &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;I mentioned my DataDog story to a long-time Google employee there (16 years!) and he said he had recently been involved in a similar situation with Google's Stackdriver monitoring, where the bill to a customer was $85K in a month just for Stackdriver. I asked what Google did, and he said they refunded the money, then worked with the customer to better use their tools.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;There is of course no way to please all of the people all of the time. However, I genuinely feel that I was ripped off and misled by DataDog, but I have the impression that Jay and Michelle honestly view me as some jerk trying to rip them off for $1500. &amp;nbsp; And they probably hate me for telling you about my experiences.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;So far, with CoCalc we charge customers in advance for any service we provide, so less people are surprised by a bill. &amp;nbsp;Sometimes there are problems with recurring subscriptions when a person is charged for the upcoming month of a subscription, and don't want to continue (e.g., because their course is over), we always fully refund the charge. What does your company do? Why? I do worry that our billing model means that we miss out on potential revenue.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;We all know what successful huge consumer companies like Amazon and Wal-Mart do.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;monitoring-for-data-science-nerds&quot;&gt;Monitoring for Data Science Nerds?&lt;/h2&gt;I wonder if there is interest in a service like DataDog, but targeted at Data Science Nerds, built on CoCalc, which provides hosted collaborative Jupyter notebooks with Pandas, R, etc., pre-installed. &lt;a href=&quot;https://promcon.io/2017-munich/talks/analyze-prometheus-metrics-like-a-data-scientist/&quot;&gt;This talk&lt;/a&gt; at PrometheusCon 2017 mostly discussed the friction that people face moving data from Prometheus to analyze using data science tools (e.g., R, Python, Jupyter). CoCalc provides a collaborative data science environment, so if we were to smooth over those points of friction, perhaps it could be useful to certain people. And &lt;a href=&quot;https://cocalc.com/policies/pricing.html&quot;&gt;much more efficient...&lt;/a&gt;</content>
		<author>
			<name>William Stein</name>
			<email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
			<uri>http://sagemath.blogspot.com/</uri>
		</author>
		<source>
			<title type="html">Sage: Open Source Mathematics Software</title>
			<subtitle type="html">This is my blog about things related to Sage.</subtitle>
			<link rel="self" href="http://sagemath.blogspot.com/feeds/posts/default"/>
			<id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-6365588202025292315</id>
			<updated>2018-03-08T00:05:15+00:00</updated>
		</source>
	</entry>

	<entry>
		<title type="html">Introduction to SageMath</title>
		<link href="http://opendreamkit.org/2017/08/31/eurocomb/"/>
		<id>http://opendreamkit.org/2017/08/31/eurocomb</id>
		<updated>2017-08-31T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Viviane Pons gave a Sage Introduction talk at the internation combinatorics conference &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dmg.tuwien.ac.at/eurocomb2017/&quot;&gt;Eurocomb 2017&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lri.fr/~pons/docs/2017_Eurocomb_sage.pdf&quot;&gt;Slides&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>
		<author>
			<name>The OpenDreamKit consortium</name>
			<email>contact@opendreamkit.org</email>
			<uri>http://opendreamkit.org/</uri>
		</author>
		<source>
			<title type="html">OpenDreamKit</title>
			<link rel="self" href="http://opendreamkit.org/atom.xml"/>
			<id>http://opendreamkit.org/</id>
			<updated>2018-03-19T23:01:26+00:00</updated>
		</source>
	</entry>

	<entry>
		<title type="html">Workshop on live structured documents</title>
		<link href="http://opendreamkit.org/2017/08/26/live-documents-workshop/"/>
		<id>http://opendreamkit.org/2017/08/26/live-documents-workshop</id>
		<updated>2017-08-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://opendreamkit.org&quot;&gt;OpenDreamKit&lt;/a&gt; is hosting a workshop on live structured documents
to take place at Simula Research Laboratory in Oslo, Norway
from Monday 16. October to Friday 20. October.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The workshop is dedicated to various aspects of live documents, including:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Authoring language and tools (ReST, XML, latex, …),&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Converters (Sphinx, pandoc, docbook, …),&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Infrastructure for rendering documents,&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Infrastructure for interacting with the computing backends (e.g.  &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/oreillymedia/thebe&quot;&gt;Thebe&lt;/a&gt; based on the Jupyter protocol, &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/sympy/sympy-live/&quot;&gt;sympy live&lt;/a&gt;, …),&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Online services providing computing backends (e.g. &lt;a href=&quot;https://try.jupyter.org&quot;&gt;tmpnb&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://sagecell.sagemath.org/&quot;&gt;sagecell&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://mybinder.org&quot;&gt;binder&lt;/a&gt;, …),&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Integrated collaborative authoring environments (sharelatex, SMC, texmacs, …)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Participants can register &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.eventbrite.com/e/opendreamkit-workshop-on-live-structured-documents-tickets-37364670736&quot;&gt;via eventbrite&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
		<author>
			<name>The OpenDreamKit consortium</name>
			<email>contact@opendreamkit.org</email>
			<uri>http://opendreamkit.org/</uri>
		</author>
		<source>
			<title type="html">OpenDreamKit</title>
			<link rel="self" href="http://opendreamkit.org/atom.xml"/>
			<id>http://opendreamkit.org/</id>
			<updated>2018-03-19T23:01:26+00:00</updated>
		</source>
	</entry>

	<entry>
		<title type="html">OpenDreamKit at Groups St Andrews in Birmingham</title>
		<link href="http://opendreamkit.org/2017/07/29/GroupsStAndrews/"/>
		<id>http://opendreamkit.org/2017/07/29/GroupsStAndrews</id>
		<updated>2017-07-29T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<content type="html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;opendreamkit-at-groups-st-andrews-in-birmingham&quot;&gt;OpenDreamKit at Groups St Andrews in Birmingham&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.groupsstandrews.org/&quot;&gt;Groups St Andrews&lt;/a&gt; is a conference series with
a conference every four years. This year’s Groups St Andrews will be in
Birmingham, and I will attend, bring
a &lt;a href=&quot;http://opendreamkit.org/public/groups-st-andrews-2017.pdf&quot;&gt;poster&lt;/a&gt;, give a contributed talk
about computing in permutation groups, and teach a course on GAP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post serves the main purpose of providing a page on the OpenDreamKit website
that can hold all the links that will appear on the poster, and possible further
information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;links&quot;&gt;Links&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://opendreamkit.org&quot;&gt;OpenDreamKit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://jupyter.org&quot;&gt;Jupyter&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.gap-system.org&quot;&gt;GAP&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/gap-system&quot;&gt;GAP GitHub&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/gap-packages/&quot;&gt;GAP Packages on GitHub&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/gap-packages/jupyter-kernel-gap&quot;&gt;GAP Jupyter Kernel&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://sagemath.org&quot;&gt;SageMath&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://cocalc.com&quot;&gt;CoCalc (formerly SageMathCloud&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://openmath.github.io&quot;&gt;OpenMath&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://mathhub.info&quot;&gt;MathHub&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://uniformal.github.io&quot;&gt;MMT&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://mathhub.info/MitM&quot;&gt;Maths in the Middle&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://mathhub.info/mh/mmt/graphs/tgview.html&quot;&gt;Theory Graphs&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://lmfdb.org&quot;&gt;L-Functions and Modular Forms Database&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content>
		<author>
			<name>The OpenDreamKit consortium</name>
			<email>contact@opendreamkit.org</email>
			<uri>http://opendreamkit.org/</uri>
		</author>
		<source>
			<title type="html">OpenDreamKit</title>
			<link rel="self" href="http://opendreamkit.org/atom.xml"/>
			<id>http://opendreamkit.org/</id>
			<updated>2018-03-19T23:01:26+00:00</updated>
		</source>
	</entry>

	<entry>
		<title type="html">Sphinx documentation of Cython code using &quot;binding=True&quot;</title>
		<link href="http://opendreamkit.org/2017/06/09/CythonSphinx/"/>
		<id>http://opendreamkit.org/2017/06/09/CythonSphinx</id>
		<updated>2017-06-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;One of the deliverables (&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/OpenDreamKit/OpenDreamKit/issues/87&quot;&gt;D4.13&lt;/a&gt;)
of the OpenDreamKit project is refactoring the documentation system of &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sagemath.org/&quot;&gt;SageMath&lt;/a&gt;.
The SageMath documentation is built using a heavily customized &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sphinx-doc.org/en/stable/&quot;&gt;Sphinx&lt;/a&gt;.
Many of the customizations are neccessary to support autodoc
(automatically generated documentation from docstrings) for &lt;a href=&quot;http://cython.org/&quot;&gt;Cython&lt;/a&gt; files.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks to some changes I made to Sphinx, autodoc for Cython now works provided that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You use Sphinx version 1.6 or later.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Cython code is compiled with the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;binding=True&lt;/code&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://cython.readthedocs.io/en/latest/src/reference/compilation.html#compiler-directives&quot;&gt;directive&lt;/a&gt;.
See &lt;a href=&quot;http://cython.readthedocs.io/en/latest/src/reference/compilation.html#how-to-set-directives&quot;&gt;How to set directives&lt;/a&gt;
in the Cython documentation.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A small monkey-patch is applied to &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;inspect.isfunction&lt;/code&gt;.
You can put this in your Sphinx &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;conf.py&lt;/code&gt; for example:&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt; def isfunction(obj):
     return hasattr(type(obj), &quot;__code__&quot;)

 import inspect
 inspect.isfunction = isfunction
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was used successfully for the documentation of
&lt;a href=&quot;http://cysignals.readthedocs.io/en/latest/&quot;&gt;cysignals&lt;/a&gt;
and &lt;a href=&quot;http://fpylll.readthedocs.io/en/latest/&quot;&gt;fpylll&lt;/a&gt;.
There is &lt;a href=&quot;https://trac.sagemath.org/ticket/22747&quot;&gt;ongoing work&lt;/a&gt; to do the same for SageMath.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;implementation-of-functions-in-python&quot;&gt;Implementation of functions in Python&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To understand why items 2 and 3 on the above list are needed,
we need to look at how Python implements functions.
In Python, there are two kinds of functions
(we really mean functions here, not methods or other callables):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;User-defined functions, defined with &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;def&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;lambda&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt; &amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; def foo(): pass
 &amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; type(foo)
 &amp;lt;class 'function'&amp;gt;
 &amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; type(lambda x: x)
 &amp;lt;class 'function'&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Built-in functions such as &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;len&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;repr&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;isinstance&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt; &amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; type(len)
 &amp;lt;class 'builtin_function_or_method'&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the CPython implementation, these are completely independent classes
with different behaviours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;user-defined-functions-binding-as-methods&quot;&gt;User-defined functions binding as methods&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just to give one example, built-in functions do not have a
&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;__get__&lt;/code&gt; method, which means that they do not become methods when used in a class.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s consider this class:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;class X(object):
    def printme(self):
        return repr(self)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is essentially equivalent to&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;class X(object):
    printme = (lambda self: repr(self))

&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; X().printme()
'&amp;lt;__main__.X object at 0x7fb342f960b8&amp;gt;'
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, directly putting the built-in function &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;repr&lt;/code&gt; in the class
does not work as expected:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;class Y(object):
    printme = repr

&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; Y().printme()
Traceback (most recent call last):
  File &quot;&amp;lt;stdin&amp;gt;&quot;, line 1, in &amp;lt;module&amp;gt;
TypeError: repr() takes exactly one argument (0 given)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is simply something that built-in functions do not support.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;user-defined-vs-built-in-functions&quot;&gt;User-defined vs. built-in functions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is a list of the main differences between user-defined and built-in functions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;User-defined functions are implemented in Python,
built-in functions are implemented in C.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Only user-defined functions support &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;__get__&lt;/code&gt; and can become methods
(see above).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Only user-defined functions support introspection such as
&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;inspect.getargspec()&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;inspect.getsourcefile()&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;CPython has specific optimizations for calling built-in functions.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;inspect&lt;/code&gt; module and profiling make
a difference between the two kinds of functions.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cython generates C code, so Cython functions must be built-in functions.
This has unfortunate disadvantages, such as the lack of introspection support,
which is particularly important for Sphinx.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-cython-function-type-cyfunction&quot;&gt;The Cython function type: cyfunction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Luckily, the Cython developers came up with a solution:
they invented a completely new function type (called &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;cyfunction&lt;/code&gt;),
which is implemented like built-in functions
but which behaves as much as possible like user-defined functions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By default, functions in Cython are built-in functions.
With the directive &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;binding=True&lt;/code&gt;, functions in Cython become cyfunctions.
Since cyfunctions are not specifically optimized by CPython,
this comes with a performance penalty.
More precisely, calling cyfunctions from Python is slower than
calling built-in functions from Python.
The slowdown can be significant for simple functions.
Within Cython, cyfunctions are as fast as built-in functions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since a &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;cyfunction&lt;/code&gt; is not a built-in function
nor a user-defined function (those two types are not subclassable),
the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;inspect&lt;/code&gt; module (and hence Sphinx) does not recognize it as being a function.
So, to have full inspect support for Cython functions,
we need to change &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;inspect.isfunction&lt;/code&gt;.
After various attempts, I came up with &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;hasattr(type(obj), &quot;__code__&quot;)&lt;/code&gt;
to test whether the object &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;obj&lt;/code&gt; is a function (for introspection purposes).
This will match user-defined functions and cyfunctions
but not built-in functions, nor any other Python type that I know of.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-future-a-pep-to-change-the-function-types&quot;&gt;The future: a PEP to change the function types?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have some vague plans for a Python Enhancement Proposal (PEP)
to change the implementation of the Python function types.
The goal is that Cython functions can be implemented
on top of some standard Python function type,
with all features that cyfunctions currently have,
the performance of built-in functions
and introspection support of user-defined functions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point, it is too early to say anything about the implementation
of this hypothetical future Python function type.
If anything happens, I will surely post an update.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
		<author>
			<name>The OpenDreamKit consortium</name>
			<email>contact@opendreamkit.org</email>
			<uri>http://opendreamkit.org/</uri>
		</author>
		<source>
			<title type="html">OpenDreamKit</title>
			<link rel="self" href="http://opendreamkit.org/atom.xml"/>
			<id>http://opendreamkit.org/</id>
			<updated>2018-03-19T23:01:26+00:00</updated>
		</source>
	</entry>

	<entry>
		<title type="html">RethinkDB must relicense NOW</title>
		<link href="http://sagemath.blogspot.com/2016/10/rethinkdb-must-relicense-now-what-is.html"/>
		<id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-6365588202025292315.post-6758158987467701094</id>
		<updated>2017-06-01T13:25:01+00:00</updated>
		<content type="html">&lt;h2&gt;What is RethinkDB?&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;b&gt;UPDATE:&lt;/b&gt; &amp;nbsp;Several months after I wrote this post, RethinkDB was relicensed. &amp;nbsp;For &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/sagemathinc/cocalc&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;the CoCalc project&lt;/a&gt;, it was too late, and by then we had &lt;a href=&quot;http://blog.sagemath.com/2017/02/09/rethinkdb-vs-postgres.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;already switched to PostgreSQL&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;RethinkDB is a &lt;strong&gt;INCREDIBLE&lt;/strong&gt; high quality polished open source realtime database that is easy to deploy, shard, replicate, and supports a reactive client programming model, which is useful for collaborative web-based applications. Shockingly, the 7-year old company that created RethinkDB &lt;a href=&quot;https://rethinkdb.com/blog/&quot;&gt;has just shutdown&lt;/a&gt;. I am the CEO of a company, &lt;a href=&quot;https://cloud.sagemath.com/&quot;&gt;SageMath, Inc.,&lt;/a&gt; that uses RethinkDB very heavily, so I have a strong interest in RethinkDB surviving as an independent open source project.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;three-types-of-open-source-projects&quot;&gt;Three Types of Open Source Projects&lt;/h2&gt;There are many types of open source projects. &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/rethinkdb/rethinkdb/graphs/contributors?from=2015-09-10&amp;to=2016-10-10&amp;type=c&quot;&gt;RethinkDB was&lt;/a&gt; the type of open source project where most work on RethinkDB has been fulltime focused work, done by employees of the RethinkDB company. RethinkDB is licensed under the AGPL, but the company &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.rethinkdb.com/faq/&quot;&gt;promised to make&lt;/a&gt; the software available to customers under other licenses.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Academia:&lt;/strong&gt; I started the &lt;a href=&quot;http://sagemath.org/&quot;&gt;SageMath&lt;/a&gt; open source math software project in 2005, which has &lt;a href=&quot;https://trac.sagemath.org/&quot;&gt;over 500 contributors&lt;/a&gt;, and a relatively healthy volunteer ecosystem, with about hundred contributors to each release, and many releases each year. These are mostly volunteer contributions by academics: usually grad students, postdocs, and math professors. They contribute because SageMath is directly relevant to their research, and they often contribute state of the art code that implements algorithms they have created or refined as part of their research. Sage is licensed under the GPL, and that license has worked extremely well for us. Academics sometimes even get significant grants from &lt;a href=&quot;https://groups.google.com/forum/#!topic/sage-edu/9FP4mR_Pjbc&quot;&gt;the NSF&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;http://opendreamkit.org/&quot;&gt;the EU&lt;/a&gt; to support Sage development.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Companies:&lt;/strong&gt; I also started the &lt;a href=&quot;http://cython.org/&quot;&gt;Cython&lt;/a&gt; compiler project in 2007, which has had dozens of contributors and is now the defacto standard for writing or wrapping fast code for use by Python. The developers of Cython mostly work at companies (e.g., Google) as a side project in their spare time. (Here's a &lt;a href=&quot;https://mail.python.org/pipermail/cython-devel/2016-October/004948.html&quot;&gt;message today about a new release&lt;/a&gt; from a Cython developer, who works at Google.) Cython is licensed under the Apache License.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-rethinkdb-will-become&quot;&gt;What RethinkDB Will Become&lt;/h2&gt;RethinkDB will no longer be an open source project whose development is sponsored by a single company dedicated to the project. Will it be an academic project, a company-supported project, or dead?&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;A friend of mine at Oxford University surveyed his &lt;strong&gt;academic&lt;/strong&gt; CS colleagues about RethinkDB, and they said they had zero interest in it. Indeed, from an academic research point of view, I agree that &lt;strong&gt;there is nothing interesting about RethinkDB&lt;/strong&gt;. I myself am a college professor, and understand these people! Academic volunteer open source contributors are definitely not going to come to RethinkDB's rescue. The value in RethinkDB is not in the innovative new algorithms or ideas, but in the high quality carefully debugged implementations of standard algorithms (largely the work of bad ass German programmer Daniel Mewes). The RethinkDB devs had to carefully tune each parameter in those algorithms based on extensive automated testing, user feedback, the Jepsen tests, etc.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;That leaves companies. Whether or not you like or agree with this, many companies will &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/search?q=google+agpl+will+not+touch&amp;rlz=1C5CHFA_enUS691US691&amp;oq=google+agpl+will+not+touch&amp;aqs=chrome..69i57j69i64.4391j0j7&amp;sourceid=chrome&amp;ie=UTF-8&quot;&gt;not touch AGPL licensed code&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;br /&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;em&gt;&quot;Google open source guru Chris DiBona says that the web giant continues to ban the lightning-rod AGPL open source license within the company because doing so &quot;saves engineering time&quot; and because most AGPL projects are of no use to the company.&quot;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;This is just the way it is -- it's psychology and culture, so deal with it. In contrast, companies very frequently embrace open source code that is licensed under the Apache or BSD licenses, and they keep such projects alive. The extremely popular PostgreSQL database is &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.postgresql.org/about/licence/&quot;&gt;licensed under an almost-BSD license&lt;/a&gt;. MySQL is freely licensed under the GPL, but &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.mysql.com/about/legal/licensing/oem/&quot;&gt;there are good reasons&lt;/a&gt; why people buy a commercial MySQL license (from Oracle) for MySQL. Like RethinkDB, MongoDB is AGPL licensed, but they are &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mongodb.com/community/licensing&quot;&gt;happy to sell&lt;/a&gt; a different license to companies.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;With RethinkDB today, the only option is AGPL. This very strongly discourage use by the only possible group of users and developers that have any chance to keep RethinkDB from death. If this situation is not resolved as soon as possible, I am &lt;strong&gt;extremely afraid&lt;/strong&gt; that it never will be resolved. Ever. If you care about RethinkDB, you should be afraid too. Ignoring the landscape and culture of volunteer open source projects is dangerous.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-proposal&quot;&gt;A Proposal&lt;/h2&gt;I don't know who can make the decision to relicense RethinkDB. I don't kow what is going on with investors or who is in control. I am an outsider. Here is a proposal that might provide a way out &lt;strong&gt;today&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PROPOSAL:&lt;/strong&gt; Dear RethinkDB, sell me an Apache (or BSD) license to the RethinkDB source code. Make this the last thing your company sells before it shuts down. Just do it.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=12680444&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Hacker News Discussion&lt;/a&gt;</content>
		<author>
			<name>William Stein</name>
			<email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
			<uri>http://sagemath.blogspot.com/</uri>
		</author>
		<source>
			<title type="html">Sage: Open Source Mathematics Software</title>
			<subtitle type="html">This is my blog about things related to Sage.</subtitle>
			<link rel="self" href="http://sagemath.blogspot.com/feeds/posts/default"/>
			<id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-6365588202025292315</id>
			<updated>2018-03-08T00:05:15+00:00</updated>
		</source>
	</entry>

	<entry>
		<title type="html">SageMath GSoC 2017 Projects</title>
		<link href="http://blog.harald.schil.ly/2017/05/sagemath-gsoc-2017-projects.html"/>
		<id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3473399517246044360.post-5304490995105111973</id>
		<updated>2017-05-05T18:03:53+00:00</updated>
		<content type="html">&lt;div dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;&lt;h2&gt;&lt;span&gt;6 GSoC SageMath Projects&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;span&gt;During the past couple of summers, SageMath successfully managed many &lt;a href=&quot;https://summerofcode.withgoogle.com/&quot;&gt;Google Summer of Code&lt;/a&gt; projects. This year we are again &lt;a href=&quot;https://summerofcode.withgoogle.com/organizations/5790079692832768/&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;happy to have six projects&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;h3&gt;&lt;span&gt;Implementing matroid classes and plotting improvements&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;span&gt;(Zachary Gershkoff /&amp;nbsp;Stefan van Zwam)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;blockquote class=&quot;tr_bq&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;This project seeks to implement several common matroid classes in SageMath, along with algorithms for their display and relevant computations. The graphic matroid class in particular will be implemented with a representative graph with methods for Whitney switching and minor operations. This will be accompanied by improvements to the graph theory library, with methods relevant to matroids enabled to support multigraphs. Other modules for this project include improved plotting of rank 3 matroids to eliminate false colinearities, computation of a matroid's automorphism group using SageMath's group theory libraries, and faster minor testing based on an existing trac ticket.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;h3&gt;&lt;span&gt;Expanding the Functionality of Dynamical Systems&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;span&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;Rebecca Lauren Miller / Paul Fili and Ben Hutz)&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;blockquote class=&quot;tr_bq&quot;&gt;As a member of the sage-dynamics community, researchers have compiled a wishlist for algorithms and functionality they would like added. I would like to shorten the wish list for us.For my project I will be completing some desired additions to SAGE from the Sage Dynamics Wiki. I will implement Well’s Algorithm, strengthen the numerical precision in cannonical_height, as well as implement reduced_form for higher dimensions.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Improvement of Complex Dynamics in Sage&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;(Ben Barros / Adam Towsley and Ben Hutz)&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;blockquote class=&quot;tr_bq&quot;&gt;There are three major things that I would like to implement to improve the functionality of Sage in the area Complex Dynamics. The details of the project are summarized in the following list:&lt;br /&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Complex Dynamics Graphical package: &lt;/b&gt;Integrate or implement a complex dynamics software such as Mandel into Sage. This will be done by creating an optional package for Sage. If there is enough demand, the package may become a standard package for Sage at some point.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Spider Algorithm:&lt;/b&gt; The object of the Spider Algorithm is to construct polynomials with assigned combinatorics. For example, we may want to find a polynomial that has a periodic orbit of period 7. The Spider Algorithm provides a way for us to compute this polynomial efficiently. I plan to implement this algorithm into Sage.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Coercion: &lt;/b&gt;If you have a map defined over Q, you should be able to take the image of a point over C (i.e. somewhere you have a well-defined embedding) without having to use the command &quot;change_ring()&quot;. Something similar works for polynomials in Sage but it does not work for morphisms/schemes.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Linear-time Implementation of Modular Decomposition of Undirected and Directed Graphs&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;div&gt;(Lokesh Jain / Dima Pasechnik)&lt;/div&gt;&lt;blockquote class=&quot;tr_bq&quot;&gt;This project is aimed at providing linear time implementation for modular decomposition of graphs and digraphs. Modular decomposition is decomposition of graph into modules. A module is a subset of vertices and it is a generalization of connected component in graph. Let us take for example a module X. For any vertex v ∉ X it is either connected or not connected to every vertex of X. Another property of module is that a module can be subset of another module. There are various algorithms which have been published for modular decomposition of graphs. The focus in this project is on linear time complexity algorithms which can be practically implemented. The project further aims to use the modules developed for modular decomposition to implement other functionality like skew partitions. Skew partition is partition of graph into two sets of vertices such that induced graph formed by one set is disconnected and induced graph formed by other set is complement of the first. Modular decomposition is a very important concept in Graph Theory and it has a number of use cases. For instance it has been an important tool for solving optimization and combinatorics problems.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Modular Decomposition of graphs and digraphs&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;div&gt;(Maria Ioanna Spyrakoy /&amp;nbsp;Dima Pasechnik)&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;blockquote class=&quot;tr_bq&quot;&gt;Modular decomposition of (di)graphs is a generalization of the concept of the decomposition of (di)graphs into connected components. Its current implementation in Sage relies on badly broken abandoned C code, and badly needs to be replaced by something that works and is not too slow. However, the only open-source implementations of some of these procedures are either in Java or in Perl, and thus aren't really useful for Sage.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;b&gt;Note:&lt;/b&gt; A attentive reader might notice the similarity between those projects. They will be split regarding the type of graph and be coordinated to not overlap but to augment each other.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Visualizing constructs in cluster algebras and quiver representations&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;div&gt;(Bryan Wang / Travis Scrimshaw)&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;blockquote class=&quot;tr_bq&quot;&gt;I aim to implement visualizations of several key constructs in cluster algebras and quiver representations. The first is Auslander-Reiten quivers, for at least the A_n and D_n cases. The second is labelled endomorphism quivers and mutations within a cluster category, focusing on the A_n case. The third is posets of down-mutations for the A_n case. These features will be useful not only for research purposes, but also as nice examples to play around with and learn from. Aside from these features, I am interested in implementing features for the Quantum Cluster Algebras project.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;All the best for this summer, thank you to Google for making this possible, and sorry to all those candidates who didn't make it ...&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
		<author>
			<name>Harald Schilly</name>
			<email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
			<uri>http://blog.harald.schil.ly/search/label/sage</uri>
		</author>
		<source>
			<title type="html">Harald Schilly</title>
			<link rel="self" href="http://blog.harald.schil.ly/feeds/posts/default/-/sage"/>
			<id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3473399517246044360</id>
			<updated>2018-03-08T15:22:10+00:00</updated>
		</source>
	</entry>

	<entry>
		<title type="html">Release: nbdime 0.3.0</title>
		<link href="http://opendreamkit.org/2017/05/05/nbdime-0.3.0/"/>
		<id>http://opendreamkit.org/2017/05/05/nbdime-0.3.0</id>
		<updated>2017-05-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;We are happy to announce release 0.3.0 of &lt;a href=&quot;https://nbdime.readthedocs.io&quot;&gt;nbdime&lt;/a&gt;,
continuing to improve the process of working with Jupyter notebooks in version control.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The highlight of 0.3 is much improved integration with git, making it easier than ever
to get started with nbdime in git:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;pip install --upgrade nbdime # install nbdime
nbdime config-git --global --enable # tell git to use nbdime when it sees notebooks
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and you can get nice GUI diffs directly from git refs on the command-line:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;nbdiff-web master mynotebook.ipynb
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
		<author>
			<name>The OpenDreamKit consortium</name>
			<email>contact@opendreamkit.org</email>
			<uri>http://opendreamkit.org/</uri>
		</author>
		<source>
			<title type="html">OpenDreamKit</title>
			<link rel="self" href="http://opendreamkit.org/atom.xml"/>
			<id>http://opendreamkit.org/</id>
			<updated>2018-03-19T23:01:26+00:00</updated>
		</source>
	</entry>

	<entry>
		<title type="html">Debriefing from a successful Formal Project Review by the EU Commission</title>
		<link href="http://opendreamkit.org/2017/04/26/first-project-review-debriefing/"/>
		<id>http://opendreamkit.org/2017/04/26/first-project-review-debriefing</id>
		<updated>2017-04-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;On April 26th, OpenDreamKit underwent its first formal review by the
European Commission. We presented the achievements of the first 18
months of the project, including
&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/OpenDreamKit/OpenDreamKit/issues?q=label%3AReportingPeriod1&quot;&gt;30 deliverables&lt;/a&gt;
(&lt;a href=&quot;http://opendreamkit.org/events_activities/reports/&quot;&gt;reports&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://opendreamkit.org/meetings/2017-04-26-ProjectReviewPresentations/&quot;&gt;slides&lt;/a&gt;).
Overall, &lt;strong&gt;the feedback was very positive&lt;/strong&gt;, with language such as
“enthusiast”, “brilliant”, “amazing job”, or “things have come along
fantastically”. We made a strong point in our reports and
presentations that a vast majority of what’s happening comes from the
ecosystem we support. All we do is exploit the special resources the
EU is entrusting us to knock down some tough hurdles that are
preventing the ball to roll. &lt;strong&gt;Kudos to our communities!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;debriefing-notes-i-sent-to-the-opendreamkit-participants&quot;&gt;Debriefing notes I sent to the OpenDreamKit participants&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;About twenty of us were in Brussels early this week for the
OpenDreamKit Month 18 formal review. After two days of intensive
preparation, we presented our work on Wednesday to our project officer
and reviewers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are a few points that we need to think about (not unexpected).
But otherwise the hard work we all put since the beginning of the
project came out as quite a show. The panel gave very constructive
feedback and were overall really happy. They appreciate our approach,
our work, our spirit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now is the time to enjoy that appreciation and build on that energy to
do even better in the coming years. Pass this on to our communities!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking of funding: the reviewers made a strong point that we bear a
big responsibility: apparently mathematics does not have a good press
in the high spheres these days. We were &lt;em&gt;very lucky&lt;/em&gt;, as a math
project, to be funded; it’s really because they appreciated so much
the strength of the proposal and our “clever and creative
interpretation of the call” that we made it through. “No other math
project is being funded” (this quote obviously does not apply to
ERCs; the scope is plausibly that of H2020 projects).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They now need strong ammunition to make sure that future calls leave
room for mathematics. So not only do we have to succeed because we
care so much about our aims (and should investigate followups to
pursue them further), but also for the sake of other projects
elsewhere in mathematics. We also need to proactively explain and
highlight to a wider audience what we do in collaboration with our
communities. There is very good stuff going on, let it be seen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some further thoughts needs to be put in how to achieve that. For now,
the take home message is simple: &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;If you witness something nice
happening, from a technical achievement with a wow factor to a thought
provoking anecdote, write a blog post about it&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;. See the
&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/OpenDreamKit/OpenDreamKit.github.io/blob/master/_posts/README.md&quot;&gt;instructions&lt;/a&gt;,
or even just send a brief draft text by e-mail to
&lt;a href=&quot;mailto:m.croucher@sheffield.ac.uk&quot;&gt;Mike Croucher&lt;/a&gt; with
&lt;a href=&quot;mailto:Nicolas.Thiery@u-psud.fr&quot;&gt;me&lt;/a&gt; in CC.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me conclude by thanking the whole band that came to Brussels (with
a special nod to the presenters on which we dumped the most delicate
presentations). I was frustrated as you all were spending all this
time together without tackling what we all really care most. However
we built on our image in the Commission, and used the occasion to
strengthen our group around a joint vision. This is a worthwhile long
term investment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you everybody for all the enthusiastic, dedicated and beautiful
work. It’s an honor and a pleasure to be working with such a team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Remember: pass it on to those supporting you and to your communities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cheers,
		Nicolas&lt;/p&gt;</content>
		<author>
			<name>The OpenDreamKit consortium</name>
			<email>contact@opendreamkit.org</email>
			<uri>http://opendreamkit.org/</uri>
		</author>
		<source>
			<title type="html">OpenDreamKit</title>
			<link rel="self" href="http://opendreamkit.org/atom.xml"/>
			<id>http://opendreamkit.org/</id>
			<updated>2018-03-19T23:01:26+00:00</updated>
		</source>
	</entry>

	<entry>
		<title type="html">Formal Project Review for OpenDreamKit's first reporting period (Sept. 2015 to Feb. 2017)</title>
		<link href="http://opendreamkit.org/2017/04/24/first-project-review/"/>
		<id>http://opendreamkit.org/2017/04/24/first-project-review</id>
		<updated>2017-04-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;At the occasion of its first
(&lt;a href=&quot;http://opendreamkit.org/2017/04/26/first-project-review-debriefing/&quot;&gt;very successful&lt;/a&gt;!)
&lt;a href=&quot;http://opendreamkit.org/meetings/2017-04-26-ProjectReviewPresentations/&quot;&gt;formal review&lt;/a&gt;
by the EU commission, twenty OpenDreamKit participants met on the last
week of April 2017 at the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.clora.eu/en/accueil&quot;&gt;CLORA&lt;/a&gt;
(Club of associated research organisations) headquarters in Brussels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;monday-24-tuesday-25&quot;&gt;Monday 24, Tuesday 25&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Brief Steering Committee (&lt;a href=&quot;http://opendreamkit.org/2017/04/24/brussels-steering-committee/&quot;&gt;Agenda &amp;amp; Minutes&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://mensuel.framapad.org/p/vQTnSyplRr&quot;&gt;Pad&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/OpenDreamKit/OpenDreamKit/issues/222&quot;&gt;Preparation for the review&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;wednesday-26&quot;&gt;Wednesday 26&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://opendreamkit.org/meetings/2017-04-26-ProjectReviewPresentations/&quot;&gt;Formal review&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;a href=&quot;http://opendreamkit.org/2017/04/26/first-project-review-debriefing/&quot;&gt;debriefing notes&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;thursday-27-friday-28&quot;&gt;Thursday 27, Friday 28&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/OpenDreamKit/OpenDreamKit/issues/223&quot;&gt;Coding sprints&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content>
		<author>
			<name>The OpenDreamKit consortium</name>
			<email>contact@opendreamkit.org</email>
			<uri>http://opendreamkit.org/</uri>
		</author>
		<source>
			<title type="html">OpenDreamKit</title>
			<link rel="self" href="http://opendreamkit.org/atom.xml"/>
			<id>http://opendreamkit.org/</id>
			<updated>2018-03-19T23:01:26+00:00</updated>
		</source>
	</entry>

	<entry>
		<title type="html">Steering Committee meeting before the 1st Project Review</title>
		<link href="http://opendreamkit.org/2017/04/24/brussels-steering-committee/"/>
		<id>http://opendreamkit.org/2017/04/24/brussels-steering-committee</id>
		<updated>2017-04-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<content type="html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;participants&quot;&gt;Participants&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A framadate &lt;a href=&quot;https://framadate.org/MPxYiQTu1JZjHuJp&quot;&gt;poll&lt;/a&gt; was created&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;were-present-on-the-steering-committee-day&quot;&gt;Were present on the steering committee day:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nicolas THIERY; Benoît PILORGET; Erik BRAY; Viviane PONS; Vincent DELECROIX; Michael KOHLHASE; Dennis MUELLER; Florian RABE; Tom WIESING; Clément PERNET; Wolfram DECKER; William HART; Dmitrii PASECHNIK; Marcin KOSTUR; Mike CROUCHER; Hans FANGOHR; Alexander KONOVALOV; Stephen LINTON; Luca DE FEO; John CREMONA; Paul-Olivier DEHAYE; Benjamin RAGAN-KELLEY; Jeroen DEMEYER; Konrad HINSEN&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;agenda&quot;&gt;Agenda&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Second amendment to the Grant&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;WP7: overview of the situation and of the measures taken and to be planned&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Overview of the deliverables due for M18&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Best practice for the Project Review&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;minutes&quot;&gt;Minutes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;second-amendment-to-the-grant&quot;&gt;Second amendment to the Grant&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Benoît Pilorget (BP) announced that the Second Amendment should be over in April-May. All the modifications concerning deliverables and the scientific context were accepted. The remaining blocking points were purely administrative and require some time. At the moment these notes are being written (19/05/2017), the Commission seems to have fully agreed on all terms and is about to sign the amendment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Related to this amendment, the consortium expressed their congratulations to Hans Fangohr (HF) for his new position at XFEL, in Hamburg.
All points of the amendment can be found on the github issue &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/OpenDreamKit/OpenDreamKit/issues/193&quot;&gt;#193&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;wp7-overview-of-the-situation-and-of-the-measures-taken-and-to-be-planned&quot;&gt;WP7: overview of the situation and of the measures taken and to be planned:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An open brainstorming session took place.
Resulting from the retirement of Ursula Martin, it appears that some aspects of WP7 that require research-grade  expertise in sociology will be hardly achievable as it is organised today with the current consortium. Therefore solutions must be found so that we don’t just tick the boxes but actually deliver high quality material.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Several options have been discussed:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1) Hire new staff specialised in sociology or likewise field. This solution would probably lead to the transfer of some funding within the consortium, unless it turns out enough Person-Months are planned at UOXF&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2) Subcontract the planned work not feasible. For this solution to work out, one must find an adequate subcontractor (providing enough funds are available within UOXF or the consortium) and sign an amendment to the Grant with the Commission&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;3) Rethink the scientific content (objectives, tasks, deliverables), to take into account all we have learned since the writing of the proposal, and make the best use of the available ressources and consortium expertise. This of course would require a negotiation with the EU and probably a new amendment to the grant agreement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The consortium is expecting official feedback from the Project Officer and reviewers after the formal review. In the meantime, the Coordinator and Principal Investigators of WP7 will be informally brainstorming all possibilities. Were an amendment necessary, it will be written after the current amendment for the addition of FAU Erlangen and XFEL is signed by the Commission.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;overview-of-the-deliverables-due-for-m18-and-24&quot;&gt;Overview of the deliverables due for &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/OpenDreamKit/OpenDreamKit/milestone/62?closed=1&quot;&gt;M18&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/OpenDreamKit/OpenDreamKit/milestone/65&quot;&gt;24&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a tour de table, the Coordinator ensured that all deliverables due for Month 24 (31/08/2017) have a leader and a definite working plan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;best-practice-for-the-project-review&quot;&gt;Best practice for the Project Review:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;BP reminded the consortium of the &lt;a href=&quot;http://opendreamkit.org/meetings/2017-01-19-EdinburghSteeringCommittee/Review-presentation/&quot;&gt;support slides&lt;/a&gt; for the Review that were presentend at the Edinburgh steering committee meeting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;feedback-from-the-quality-review-board&quot;&gt;Feedback from the Quality Review Board&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;HF, the chair of the Quality Review Board (QRB), expressed rough positive feedback from the first QRB meeting. A full report will be made available for all participants.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
		<author>
			<name>The OpenDreamKit consortium</name>
			<email>contact@opendreamkit.org</email>
			<uri>http://opendreamkit.org/</uri>
		</author>
		<source>
			<title type="html">OpenDreamKit</title>
			<link rel="self" href="http://opendreamkit.org/atom.xml"/>
			<id>http://opendreamkit.org/</id>
			<updated>2018-03-19T23:01:26+00:00</updated>
		</source>
	</entry>

	<entry>
		<title type="html">The story behind our website</title>
		<link href="http://opendreamkit.org/2017/04/06/website/"/>
		<id>http://opendreamkit.org/2017/04/06/website</id>
		<updated>2017-04-06T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;OpenDreamKit uses a &lt;em&gt;static website&lt;/em&gt; powered by Jekyll and GitHub. Ever wondered
what it means? &lt;a href=&quot;http://openpyviv.com/2017/04/05/static/&quot;&gt;Read this post&lt;/a&gt; to discover.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
		<author>
			<name>The OpenDreamKit consortium</name>
			<email>contact@opendreamkit.org</email>
			<uri>http://opendreamkit.org/</uri>
		</author>
		<source>
			<title type="html">OpenDreamKit</title>
			<link rel="self" href="http://opendreamkit.org/atom.xml"/>
			<id>http://opendreamkit.org/</id>
			<updated>2018-03-19T23:01:26+00:00</updated>
		</source>
	</entry>

	<entry>
		<title type="html">Report on WomenInSage</title>
		<link href="http://opendreamkit.org/2017/04/06/WomenInSage/"/>
		<id>http://opendreamkit.org/2017/04/06/WomenInSage</id>
		<updated>2017-04-06T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Last January, Viviane Pons, Jessica Striker and Jennifer Balakrishnan organized 
 the first &lt;a href=&quot;https://wiki.sagemath.org/days82&quot;&gt;WomenInSage&lt;/a&gt;
 event in Europe with OpenDreamKit. 20 women spent a week together coding and learning in a rented
house in the Paris area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://opendreamkit.org/public/images/womenInSage/group_photo.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Group picture&quot; class=&quot;img-responsive&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;the-workshop&quot;&gt;The Workshop&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;opening-event&quot;&gt;Opening event&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To open the workshop, Viviane, Jessica, and Jennifer gave a series of &lt;a href=&quot;https://wiki.sagemath.org/days82_sageintro&quot;&gt;introduction 
to Sage&lt;/a&gt; lectures at the Institut Henri Poincaré in Paris,
covering combinatorics and number theory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-week&quot;&gt;The Week&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The workshop then moved to the rented house. There, we organized
&lt;em&gt;short talk sessions&lt;/em&gt; to get to know our respective research fields and expectations
for the week. After that, we were able to split into small groups to work on many different
projects: STL export, Krummer surfaces, Kuznyechik cipher, Motzkin words, Shioda invariants,
and more. We also had presentations on &lt;em&gt;How to contribute to Sage&lt;/em&gt; (with a crash course 
on git) and &lt;em&gt;How to write a Sage package&lt;/em&gt;. Every evening, we had a &lt;em&gt;Status report&lt;/em&gt;
session to share our progress with the group. You can read our program and final status
reports on &lt;a href=&quot;https://wiki.sagemath.org/days82&quot;&gt;the event wikipage&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;special-pyladies-coding-cafe&quot;&gt;Special PyLadies coding cafe&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Viviane Pons is one of the organizer of the local Paris chapter for &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.pyladies.com/&quot;&gt;PyLadies&lt;/a&gt;.
She organized a meeting between the WomenInSage mathematician and the PyLadies developers.
We were welcomed by Algolia for an afternoon of coding-and-chatting with the PyLadies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://opendreamkit.org/public/images/womenInSage/pyladies-WIS.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Group picture with PyLadies&quot; class=&quot;img-responsive&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;impact&quot;&gt;Impact&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The data presented here come from a post-event questionnaire sent to the participants.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The gender gap is very important in the mathematic development community. In the 
OpenDreamKit project, among the 54 participants we are only 3 women. This reflects
the global situation in the field. Many mathematician women are still hesitant to join
our community and lack confidence in their abilities as developers. Organizing a
women targeted event is a way to motivate them and building up self-confidence in a safe
and casual atmosphere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The women who attended the conference had various level of programming experience
ranging from 1 (no experience) to 5 (a lot of experience).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://opendreamkit.org/public/images/womenInSage/programming-knowledge.png&quot; alt=&quot;1: 1 people, 2: 7 people, 3: 3 people , 4: 5 people, 5: 1 people&quot; class=&quot;img-responsive&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This disparity also reflected in their knowledge of Sage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://opendreamkit.org/public/images/womenInSage/sage-knowledge.png&quot; alt=&quot;1: 1 people, 2: 8 people, 3: 3 people , 4: 3 people, 5: 2 people&quot; class=&quot;img-responsive&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As for contributions, only 4 participants had contributed to Sage in the past 
which included the 3 organizers. Also, a majority of participants had never attended
a Sage Days before. Actually, 6 of them had never even heard of Sage Days and 2 
of them said they did not think it was “for them”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://opendreamkit.org/public/images/womenInSage/sage-days-attendance.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To the question “How did the fact that the event was targeted to women impact your decision to come?  (Would you have participated in a classical SageDays)”,
Many participants answered that it was indeed a factor a their decision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;cite&gt;Yes, but it helped. I didn´t feel so sure about my skills and being surrounded by women made things easier.&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;cite&gt;It was a new experience that I don’t regret at all.&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;cite&gt;I might have participated, but would have been less confident.&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;cite&gt;I have participated in and benefited from classical SageDays, but found this event to be even better at creating an atmosphere where everyone felt empowered to learn and contribute.&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;cite&gt;I made a special effort I would not have done for regular sage days.&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the participant said she would not have felt comfortable sharing a house
with men but that this event was such positive experience that she would now consider
it for other Sage days. The event helped building up the confidence of the participants, 9 of them said 
they felt more confident to attend classical Sage Days after the event.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://opendreamkit.org/public/images/womenInSage/future_sage_days.png&quot; alt=&quot;What are the chances you attend a &quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We took advantage of the diverse knowledge background of our group to work together
and learn from each other. It was an occasion for many “first times” among participants
who had very little experience with Sage:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;5 participants installed a source version of Sage for the first time (so that they could edit the source).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;3 used git for the first time.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;5 used git within Sage for the first time.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;11 got their first Trac account .&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;5 got their first contribution to a Sage ticket.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;8 are in the process of getting their first code integrated to Sage.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We worked on &lt;a href=&quot;https://trac.sagemath.org/search?q=days82&quot;&gt;14 tickets&lt;/a&gt; during the week, 
6 of those which have been merged since the conference. All participants said they
had learned new things and it would impact their careers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://opendreamkit.org/public/images/womenInSage/learn_new_things.png&quot; alt=&quot;Did you learn new things at this conference? 1:0 people, 2: 0 people, 3: 2 people, 4: 6 people, 5: 9 people&quot; class=&quot;img-responsive&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://opendreamkit.org/public/images/womenInSage/impact.png&quot; alt=&quot;Did you think what you learned will have an impact on your future research/career? 1:0 people, 2: 0 people, 3: 1 people, 4: 10 people, 5: 6 people&quot; class=&quot;img-responsive&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This also was an occasion to start projects and form more research and development collaborations for future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://opendreamkit.org/public/images/womenInSage/people.png&quot; alt=&quot;Did you meet interesting people? 1:0 people, 2: 0 people, 3: 0 people, 4: 2 people, 5: 15 people&quot; class=&quot;img-responsive&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://opendreamkit.org/public/images/womenInSage/projects.png&quot; alt=&quot;Have you started (or carried on) any project that could lead to more research and development in the future? I have started things and will try to follow up: 38.8%. I have started things and willdefinitely follow up: 35.3%. Nothing: 5.3%.&quot; class=&quot;img-responsive&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of this happened in a very casual and welcoming atmosphere. We used the common
rooms of the house to work. We cooked international, vegetarian friendly meals (some
participants had brought food and recipes from their home countries). We got to know
each other and shared more than code. All participants agreed that it was a very 
positive experience. When asked to rate the general atmosphere of the conference,
all of them gave a 5.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://opendreamkit.org/public/images/womenInSage/atmosphere.png&quot; alt=&quot;How did you like the general atmosphere of the conference? 1:0 people, 2: 0 people, 3: 0 people, 4: 0 people, 5: 17 people&quot; class=&quot;img-responsive&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As an organizer, it was also very rewarding and it motivates me to do it again. To
the question: “Any other comment you might have?”, we only got one answer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;cite&gt;All three organizers were so very generous with their time and expertise, and created a wonderful supportive environment. Thank-you!&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>
		<author>
			<name>The OpenDreamKit consortium</name>
			<email>contact@opendreamkit.org</email>
			<uri>http://opendreamkit.org/</uri>
		</author>
		<source>
			<title type="html">OpenDreamKit</title>
			<link rel="self" href="http://opendreamkit.org/atom.xml"/>
			<id>http://opendreamkit.org/</id>
			<updated>2018-03-19T23:01:26+00:00</updated>
		</source>
	</entry>

</feed>
