<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

	<title>Planet Sage</title>
	<link rel="self" href="http://planet.sagemath.org/atom.xml"/>
	<link href="http://planet.sagemath.org"/>
	<id>http://planet.sagemath.org/atom.xml</id>
	<updated>2017-10-17T22:11:37+00:00</updated>
	<generator uri="http://www.planetplanet.org/">Planet/2.0 +http://www.planetplanet.org</generator>

	<entry>
		<title type="html">WP6 Math-in-the-Middle Integration Use Case to be Published at MACIS-2017 (two papers)</title>
		<link href="http://opendreamkit.org/2017/10/15/WP6-Usecase/"/>
		<id>http://opendreamkit.org/2017/10/15/WP6-Usecase</id>
		<updated>2017-10-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;OpenDreamKit WP6 (Data/Knowledge/Software-Bases) has reported on the first use cases in
two papers to be publised at &lt;a href=&quot;https://macis2017.sba-research.org/&quot;&gt;MACIS 2017&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/OpenDreamKit/OpenDreamKit/blob/master/WP6/MACIS17-interop/crc.pdf&quot;&gt;Knowledge-Based Interoperability for Mathematical Software Systems&lt;/a&gt; (Michael Kohlhase, Luca Defeo, Dennis Müller, Markus Pfeiffer, Florian Rabe, Nicolas Thiery, Victor Vasilyxev, and Tom Wiesing) develops the Math-in-the-Middle Ontology for computational group theory and shows a three-system use case (Sage, GAP, Singular).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/OpenDreamKit/OpenDreamKit/blob/master/WP6/MACIS17-vt/crc.pdf&quot;&gt;Virtual Theories - A Uniform Interface to Mathematical Knowledge Bases&lt;/a&gt; (Tom Wiesing, Michael Kohlhase, and Florian Rabe) extends the MMT theories to “Virtual theories”, which do not have the “load-into-memory-fully” restrictions of “concrete theories” and are therefore suited for very large data sources like the &lt;a href=&quot;http://lmfdb.org&quot;&gt;LMFDB&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;http://opendreamkit.org/oeis.org&quot;&gt;OEIS&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content>
		<author>
			<name>The OpenDreamKit consortium</name>
			<email>contact@opendreamkit.org</email>
			<uri>http://opendreamkit.org/</uri>
		</author>
		<source>
			<title type="html">OpenDreamKit</title>
			<link rel="self" href="http://opendreamkit.org/atom.xml"/>
			<id>http://opendreamkit.org/</id>
			<updated>2017-10-17T17:06:20+00:00</updated>
		</source>
	</entry>

	<entry>
		<title type="html">Release: SageMath for Windows</title>
		<link href="http://opendreamkit.org/2017/10/11/SageWindows/"/>
		<id>http://opendreamkit.org/2017/10/11/SageWindows</id>
		<updated>2017-10-11T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<content type="html">&lt;h1 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the main tasks for OpenDreamKit
(&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/OpenDreamKit/OpenDreamKit/issues/50&quot;&gt;T.31&lt;/a&gt;]) is
improving portability of mathematical software across hardware platforms and
operating systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One particular such challenge, which has dogged the SageMath project
practically since its inception, is getting a fully working port of Sage on
Windows (and by extension this would mean working Windows versions of all
the CAS’s and other software Sage depends on, such as GAP, Singular, etc.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is particularly challenging, not so much because of the Sage Python
library (which has some, but relatively little system-specific code).
Rather, the challenge is in porting all of Sage’s 150+ standard
dependencies, and ensuring that they integrate well on Windows, with a
passing test suite.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although UNIX-like systems are popular among open source software developers
and some academics, the desktop and laptop market share of Windows computers
is estimated to be &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Usage_share_of_operating_systems#Desktop_and_laptop_computers&quot;&gt;more than
75%&lt;/a&gt;
and is an important source of potential users, especially students.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, for most of its existence, the only way to “install” Sage on
Windows was to run a Linux virtual machine that came pre-installed with
Sage, which is made available on Sage’s downloads page.  This is clumsy and
onerous for users–it forces them to work within an unfamiliar OS, and it
can be difficult and confusing to connect files and directories in their
host OS to files and directories inside the VM, and likewise for web-based
applications like the notebook.  Because of this Windows users can feel like
second-class citizens in the Sage ecosystem, and this may turn them away
from Sage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Attempts at Windows support almost as old as Sage itself (initial Sage
release in 2005). Microsoft offered funding to work on Windows version &lt;a href=&quot;https://groups.google.com/d/msg/sage-devel/LTWgQ_24cPs/WW25BGe7KjwJ&quot;&gt;as
far back as
2007&lt;/a&gt;
but was far too little for the amount of effort needed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additional work done was done off and on through 2012, and partial support
was possible at times. This included admirable work to try to support
building with the native Windows development toolchain (e.g. MSVC).  There
was even at one time an earlier version of a Sage installer for Windows, but
long since abandoned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, Sage development (and more importantly Sage’s dependencies)
continued to advance faster than there were resources for the work on
Windows support to keep up, and work mostly stalled after 2013.
OpenDreamKit has provided a unique opportunity to fund the kind of sustained
effort needed for Sage’s Windows support to catch up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;sage-for-windows-overview&quot;&gt;Sage for Windows overview&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As of SageMath version 8.0, Sage will be available for 64-bit versions of
Windows 7 and up.  It can be downloaded through the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sagemath.org/download-windows.html&quot;&gt;SageMath
website&lt;/a&gt;, and up-to-date
installation instructions are being developed at the &lt;a href=&quot;http://wiki.sagemath.org/SageWindows&quot;&gt;SageMath
wiki&lt;/a&gt;.  A 32-bit version had been
planned as well, but is on hold due to technical limitations that will be
discussed later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The installer contains all software and documentation making up the standard
Sage distribution, all libraries needed for Cygwin support, a bash shell,
numerous standard UNIX command-line utilities, and the
&lt;a href=&quot;https://mintty.github.io/&quot;&gt;Mintty&lt;/a&gt; terminal emulator, which is generally
more user-friendly and better suited for Cygwin software than the standard
Windows console.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is distributed in the form of a single-file executable installer, with a
familiar install wizard interface (built with the venerable
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.jrsoftware.org/isinfo.php&quot;&gt;InnoSetup&lt;/a&gt;.  The installer comes in
at just under a gigabyte, but unpacks to more than 4.5 GB in version 8.0.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://opendreamkit.org/public/images/2017-10-11-SageWindows/installer1.png&quot; alt=&quot;Sage for Windows Installer&quot; class=&quot;img-responsive&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://opendreamkit.org/public/images/2017-10-11-SageWindows/installer2.png&quot; alt=&quot;Sage for Windows Installer&quot; class=&quot;img-responsive&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because of the large number of files comprising the complete SageMath
distribution, and the heavy compression of the installer, installation can
take a fair amount of time even on a recent system.  On my Intel i7 laptop
it takes about ten minutes, but results will vary.  Fortunately, this has
not yet been a source of complaints–beta testers have been content to run
the installer in the background while doing other work–on a modern
multi-core machine the installer itself does not use overly many resources.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you don’t like it, there’s also a standard uninstall:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://opendreamkit.org/public/images/2017-10-11-SageWindows/uninstall.png&quot; alt=&quot;Sage for Windows Uninstaller&quot; class=&quot;img-responsive&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The installer include three desktop and/or start menu shortcuts:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://opendreamkit.org/public/images/2017-10-11-SageWindows/shortcuts.png&quot; alt=&quot;Sage for Windows start menu shortcuts&quot; class=&quot;img-responsive&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The shortcut titled just “SageMath 8.0” launches the standard Sage command
prompt in a text-based console. In general it integrates well enough with
the Windows shell to launch files with the default viewer for those file
types. For example, plots are saved to files and displayed automatically
with the default image viewer registered on the computer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://opendreamkit.org/public/images/2017-10-11-SageWindows/console.png&quot; alt=&quot;Sage for Windows console&quot; class=&quot;img-responsive&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Because Mintty supports &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sixel&quot;&gt;SIXEL&lt;/a&gt; mode
graphics, it may also be possible to embed plots and equations directly in
the console, but this has not been made to work yet with Sage.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“SageMath Shell” runs a bash shell with the environment set up to
run software in the Sage distribution.  More advanced users, or users who
wish to directly use other software included in the Sage distribution (e.g.
GAP, Singular) without going through the Sage interface.  Finally,
“SageMath Notebook” starts a Jupyter Notebook server with Sage configured as
the default kernel and, where possible, opens the Notebook interface in the
user’s browser.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In principle this could also be used as a development environment for doing
development of Sage and/or Sage extensions on Windows, but the current
installer is geared primarily just for users.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;rationale-for-cygwin-and-possible-alternatives&quot;&gt;Rationale for Cygwin and possible alternatives&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are a few possible routes to supporting Sage on Windows, of which
Cygwin is just one.  For example, before restarting work on the Cygwin port
I experimented with a solution that would run Sage on Windows using
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.docker.com/&quot;&gt;Docker&lt;/a&gt;.  I built an installer for Sage that would
install Docker for Windows if it was not already installed, install and
configure a pre-build Sage image for Docker, and install some desktop
shortcuts that attempted to launch Sage in Docker as transparently as
possible to the user.  That is, it would ensure that Docker was running,
that a container for the Sage image was running, and then would redirect I/O
to the Docker container.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This approach “worked”, but was still fairly clumsy and error-prone.  In
order to make the experience as transparent as possible a fair amount of
automation of Docker was needed.  This could get particularly tricky in
cases where the user also uses Docker directly, and accidentally interferes
with the Sage Docker installation.  Handling issues like file system and
network port mapping, while possible, was even more complicated.  What’s
worse, running Linux images in Docker for Windows still requires
virtualization.  On older versions this meant running VirtualBox in the
background, while newer versions require the Hyper-V hypervisor (which is
not available on all versions of Windows–particularly “Home” versions).
Furthermore, this requires hardware-assisted virtualization (HAV) to be
enabled in the user’s BIOS.  This typically does not come enabled by default
on home PCs, and users must manually enable it in their BIOS menu.  We did
not consider this a reasonable step to ask of users merely to “install
Sage”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another approach, which was looked at in the early efforts to port Sage to
Windows, would be to get Sage and all its dependencies building with the
standard Microsoft toolchain (MSVC, etc.).  This would mean both porting the
code to work natively on Windows, using the MSVC runtime, as well as
developing build systems compatible with MSVC.  There was a time when,
remarkably, many of Sage’s dependencies did meet these requirements.  But
since then the number of dependencies has grown too much, and Sage itself
become too dependent on the GNU toolchain, that this would be an almost
impossible undertaking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A middle ground between MSVC and Cygwin would be to build Sage using the
MinGW toolchain, which is a port of GNU build tools (including binutils,
gcc, make, autoconf, etc.) as well as some other common UNIX tools like the
bash shell to Windows.  Unlike Cygwin, MinGW does not provide emulation of
POSIX or Linux system APIs–it just provides a Windows-native port of the
development tools.  Many of Sage’s dependencies would still need to be
updated in order to work natively on Windows, but at the very least their
build systems would require relatively little updating–not much more than
is required for Cygwin.  This would actually be my preferred approach, and
with enough time and resources it could probably work.  However, it would
still require a significant amount of work to port some of Sage’s more
non-trivial dependencies, such as GAP and Singular, to work on Windows
without some POSIX emulation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So Cygwin is the path of least resistance.  Although bugs and shortcomings
in Cygwin itself occasionally require some effort to work around (as a
developer–users should not have to think about it), for the most part it
&lt;em&gt;just works&lt;/em&gt; with software written for UNIX-like systems.  It also has the
advantage of providing a full UNIX-like shell experience, so shell scripts
and scripts that use UNIX shell tools will work even on Windows.  However,
since it works directly on the native filesystem, there is less opportunity
for confusion regarding where files and folders are saved.  In fact, Cygwin
supports both Windows-style paths (starting with &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;C:\\&lt;/code&gt;) and UNIX-style
paths (in this case starting with &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;C:/&lt;/code&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, a note on the Windows Subsystem for Linux (WSL), which debuted
shortly after I began my Cygwin porting efforts, as I often get asked about
this: “Why not ‘just’ use the ‘bash for Windows’?”  The WSL is a new effort
by Microsoft to allow running executables built for Linux directly on
Windows, with full support from the Windows kernel for emulation of Linux
system calls (including ones like &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;fork()&lt;/code&gt;).  Basically, it aims to provide
all the functionality of Cygwin, but with full support from the kernel, and
the ability to run Linux binaries directly, without having to recompile
them.  This is great of course. So the question is asked if Sage can run in
this environment, and experiments suggest that it works pretty well
(although the WSL is still under active development and has room for
improvement).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wrote more about the WSL in a &lt;a href=&quot;http://opendreamkit.org/2016/10/04/emerging-technologies-wsl/&quot;&gt;blog
post&lt;/a&gt; last
year, which also addresses why we can’t “just” use it for Sage for Windows.
But in short: 1) The WSL is currently only intended as a developer tool:
There’s no way to package Windows software for end users such that it uses
the WSL transparently.  And 2) It’s only available on recent updates of
Windows 10–it will never be available on older Windows versions.  So to
reach the most users, and provide the most hassle-free user experience, the
WSL is not currently a solution.  However, it may still prove useful for
developers as a way to do Sage &lt;em&gt;development&lt;/em&gt; on Windows. And in the future
it may be the easiest way to install UNIX-based software on Windows as well,
especially if Microsoft ever expands its scope.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;development-challenges&quot;&gt;Development challenges&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main challenge with porting Sage to Windows/Cygwin has relatively little
to do with the Sage library itself, which is written almost entirely in
Python/Cython and involves relatively few system interfaces (a notable
exception to this is the advanced signal handling provided by
&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/sagemath/cysignals&quot;&gt;Cysignals&lt;/a&gt;, but this has been found
to work almost flawlessly on Cygwin thanks to the Cygwin developers’ heroic
efforts in emulating POSIX signal handling on Windows).  Rather, most of the
effort has gone into build and portability issues with Sage’s more than 150
dependencies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The majority of issues have been build-related issues.  Runtime issues are
less common, as many of Sage’s dependencies are primarily mathematical,
numerical code–mostly CPU-bound algorithms that have little use of
platform-specific APIs.  Another reason is that, although there are some
anomalous cases, Cygwin’s emulation of POSIX (and some Linux) interfaces is
good enough that most existing code just works as-is.  However, because
applications built in Cygwin are native Windows applications and DLLs, there
are Windows-specific subtleties that come up when building some non-trivial
software.  So most of the challenge has been getting all of Sage’s
dependencies building cleanly on Cygwin, and then &lt;em&gt;maintaining&lt;/em&gt; that support
(as the maintainers of most of these dependencies are not themselves testing
against Cygwin regularly).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, maintenance was the most difficult aspect of the Cygwin port (and
this is one of the main reasons past efforts failed–without a sustained
effort it was not possible to keep up with the pace of Sage development).  I
had a snapshot of Sage that was fully working on Cygwin, with all tests
passing, as soon as the end of summer in 2016.  That is, I started with one
version of Sage and added to it all the fixes needed for that version to
work.  However, by the time that work was done, there were many new
developments to Sage that I had to redo my work on top of, and there were
many new issues to fix.  This cycle repeated itself a number of times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;continuous-integration&quot;&gt;Continuous integration&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The critical component that was missing for creating a sustainable Cygwin
port of Sage was a &lt;em&gt;patchbot&lt;/em&gt; for Cygwin.  The Sage developers maintain a
(volunteer) army of patchbots–computers running a number of different OS
and hardware platforms that perform continuous integration testing of all
proposed software changes to Sage.  The patchbots are able, ideally, to
catch changes that break Sage–possibly only on specific platforms–before
they are merged into the main development branch.  Without a patchbot
testing changes on Cygwin, there was no way to stop changes from being
merged that broke Cygwin.  With some effort I managed to get a Windows VM
with Cygwin running reliably on UPSud’s OpenStack infrastructure, that
could run a Cygwin patchbot for Sage.  By continuing to monitor this
patchbot the Sage community can now receive prior warning if/when a change
will break the Cygwin port.  I expect this will impact only a small number
of changes–in particular those that update one of Sage’s dependencies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In so doing we are, indirectly, providing continuous integration on Cygwin
for Sage’s many dependencies–something most of those projects do not have
the resources to do on their own.  So this should be considered a service to
the open source software community at large. (I am also planning to
piggyback on the work I did for Sage to provide a Cygwin buildbot for
Python–this will be important moving forward as the official Python source
tree has been broken on Cygwin for some time, but is one of the most
critical dependencies for Sage).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;runtime-bugs&quot;&gt;Runtime bugs&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All that said, a few of the runtime bugs that come up are non-trivial as
well.  One particular source of bugs is subtle synchronization issues in
multi-process code, that arise primarily due to the large overhead of
creating, destroying, and signalling processes on Cygwin, as compared to
most UNIXes.  Other problems arise in areas of behavior that are not
specified by the POSIX standard, and assumptions are made that might hold on,
say, Linux, but that do not hold on Cygwin (but that are still
POSIX-compliant!)  For example, a difference in (undocumented, in both
cases) memory management between Linux and Cygwin made for a particularly
challenging &lt;a href=&quot;https://trac.sagemath.org/ticket/22633&quot;&gt;bug in PARI&lt;/a&gt;.
Another &lt;a href=&quot;https://trac.sagemath.org/ticket/21388&quot;&gt;interesting bug&lt;/a&gt; came up in
a test that invoked a stack overflow bug in Python, which only came up on
Cygwin due to the smaller default stack size of programs compiled for
Windows.  There are also occasional bugs due to small differences in
numerical results, due to the different implementation of the standard C
math routines on Cygwin, versus GNU libc.  So one should not come away with
the impression that porting software as complex as Sage and its dependencies
to Cygwin is completely trivial, nor that similar bugs might not arise in
the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;challenges-with-32-bit-windowscygwin&quot;&gt;Challenges with 32-bit Windows/Cygwin&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The original work of porting Sage to Cygwin focused on the 32-bit version of
Cygwin.  In fact, at the time that was the only version of Cygwin–the first
release of the 64-bit version of Cygwin was not until 2013.  When I picked
up work on this again I focused on 64-bit Cygwin–most software developers
today are working primarily on 64-bit systems, and so from many projects
I’ve worked on the past my experience has been that they have been more
stable on 64-bit systems.  I figured this would likely be true for Sage and
its dependencies as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, after getting Sage working on 64-bit Cygwin, when it came time to
test on 32-bit Cygwin I hit some significant snags.  Without going into too
many technical details, the main problem is that 32-bit Windows applications
have a user address space limited to just 2 GB (or 3 GB with a special boot
flag).  This is in fact not enough to fit all of Sage into memory at once.
The good news is that for most cases one would never try to use all of Sage
at once–this is only an issue if one tries to load every library in both
Sage, and all its dependencies, into the same address space.  In practical
use this is rare, though this limit can be hit while running the Sage test
suite.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With some care, such as reserving address space for the most likely to be
used (especially simultaneously) libraries in Sage, we can work around this
problem for the average user.  But the result may still not be 100% stable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It becomes a valid question whether it’s worth the effort.  There are
unfortunately few publicly available statistics on the current market share
of 64-bit versus 32-bit Windows versions among desktop users.  Very few new
desktops and laptops sold anymore to the consumer market include 32-bit
OSes, but it is still not too uncommon to find on some older, lower-end
laptops.  In particular, some laptops sold not too long ago with Windows 7
were 32-bit.  According to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.netmarketshare.com/operating-system-market-share.aspx?qprid=10&amp;qpcustomd=0&quot;&gt;Net Market
Share&lt;/a&gt;,
as of writing Windows 7 still makes up nearly 50% of all desktop operating
system installments.  This still does not tell us about 32-bit versus
64-bit.  The popular (&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.gamespot.com/articles/steam-reaches-new-concurrent-user-record/1100-6431895/&quot;&gt;12.5 million concurrent
users&lt;/a&gt;)
Steam PC gaming platform publishes the results of their &lt;a href=&quot;http://store.steampowered.com/hwsurvey/&quot;&gt;usage statistics
survey&lt;/a&gt;, which as of writing shows
barely over 5% of users with 32-bit versions of Windows.  However, computer
gamers are not likely to be representative of the overall market, being more
likely to upgrade their software and hardware.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So until some specific demand for a 32-bit version of SageMath for Windows
is heard, we will not likely invest more effort into it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;conclusion-and-future-work&quot;&gt;Conclusion and future work&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Focusing on Cygwin for porting Sage to Windows was definitely the right way
to go.  It took me only a few months in the summer of 2016 to get the vast
majority of the work done.  The rest was just a question of keeping up with
changes to Sage and fixing more bugs (this required enough constant effort
that it’s no wonder nobody managed to quite do it before).  Now, however,
enough issues have been addressed that the Windows version has remained
fairly stable, even in the face of ongoing updates to Sage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Porting more of Sage’s dependencies to build with MinGW and without Cygwin
might still be a worthwhile effort, as Cygwin adds some overhead in a few
areas, but if we had started with that it would have been too much effort.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the near future, however, the priority needs to be improvements to user
experience of the Windows Installer.  In particular, a better solution is
needed for installing Sage’s optional packages on Windows (preferably
without needing to compile them). And an improved experience for using Sage
in the Jupyter Notebook, such that the Notebook server can run in the
background as a Windows Service, would be nice. This feature would not be
specific to Sage either, and could benefit all users of the Jupyter Notebook
on Windows.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, I need to better document the process of doing Sage development on
Cygwin, including the typical kinds of problems that arise.  I also need to
better document how to set up and maintain the Cygwin patchbot, and how to
build releases of the Sage on Windows installer so that its maintenance does
not fall solely on my shoulders.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
		<author>
			<name>The OpenDreamKit consortium</name>
			<email>contact@opendreamkit.org</email>
			<uri>http://opendreamkit.org/</uri>
		</author>
		<source>
			<title type="html">OpenDreamKit</title>
			<link rel="self" href="http://opendreamkit.org/atom.xml"/>
			<id>http://opendreamkit.org/</id>
			<updated>2017-10-17T17:06:20+00:00</updated>
		</source>
	</entry>

	<entry>
		<title type="html">DataDog's pricing: don't make the same mistake I made</title>
		<link href="http://sagemath.blogspot.com/2016/07/datadogs-pricing-dont-make-same-mistake.html"/>
		<id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-6365588202025292315.post-6949985998313614355</id>
		<updated>2017-09-22T13:03:54+00:00</updated>
		<content type="html">(I wrote a 1-year &lt;a href=&quot;http://sagemath.blogspot.com/2017/09/datadog-dont-make-same-mistake-i-did.html&quot;&gt;followup post here.&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;I stupidly made a mistake recently by choosing to use &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.datadoghq.com/&quot;&gt;DataDog&lt;/a&gt; for monitoring the infrastructure for my startup (&lt;a href=&quot;https://cloud.sagemath.com/&quot;&gt;SageMathCloud&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;I got bit by their pricing UI design that looks similar to many other sites, but is different in a way that caused me to &lt;strong&gt;spend far more money than I expected.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;I'm writing this post so that you won't make the same mistake I did. &amp;nbsp;As a product, DataDog is of course a lot of hard work to create, and they can try to charge whatever they want. However, my problem is that &lt;strong&gt;what&lt;/strong&gt; they are going to charge was confusing and misleading to me.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;I wanted to see some nice web-based data about my new autoscaled Kubernetes cluster, so I looked around at options. DataDog looked like a new and awesomely-priced service for seeing live logging. And when I looked (not carefully enough) at the pricing, it looked like only $15/month to monitor a bunch of machines. I'm naive about the cost of cloud monitoring -- I've been using Stackdriver on Google cloud platform for years, which is completely free (for now, though that will change), and I've also used self hosted open solutions, and some quite nice solutions I've written myself. So my expectations were way out of whack.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Ever busy, I signed up for the &quot;$15/month plan&quot;:&lt;br /&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;separator&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://1.bp.blogspot.com/-NK09JkZDOD0/V5Jyf6jYy2I/AAAAAAABYNA/l_LP-NJv6hgODAvvaO868frbtJ4hP9SUQCLcB/s1600/dd-pricing.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img border=&quot;0&quot; height=&quot;225&quot; src=&quot;https://1.bp.blogspot.com/-NK09JkZDOD0/V5Jyf6jYy2I/AAAAAAABYNA/l_LP-NJv6hgODAvvaO868frbtJ4hP9SUQCLcB/s400/dd-pricing.png&quot; width=&quot;400&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;One of the people on my team spent a little time and installed datadog on all the VM's in our cluster, and also made DataDog automatically start running on any nodes in our Kubernetes cluster. That's a lot of machines.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Today I got the first monthly bill, which is for the month that just happened. The cost was $639.19 USD charged to my credit card. I was really confused for a while, wondering if I had bought a year subscription.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;separator&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://3.bp.blogspot.com/-LK7iRxeqMKI/V5JymhrBN-I/AAAAAAABYNE/lCA0YC3cfSMJ9LuTsFgsrt8vTUR4rvRIQCLcB/s1600/dd-invoice.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img border=&quot;0&quot; height=&quot;198&quot; src=&quot;https://3.bp.blogspot.com/-LK7iRxeqMKI/V5JymhrBN-I/AAAAAAABYNE/lCA0YC3cfSMJ9LuTsFgsrt8vTUR4rvRIQCLcB/s400/dd-invoice.png&quot; width=&quot;400&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;After a while I realized that the cost is per host! When I looked at the pricing page the first time, I had just saw in big letters &quot;$15&quot;, and &quot;$18 month-to-month&quot; and &quot;up to 500 hosts&quot;. I completely missed the &quot;Per Host&quot; line, because I was so naive that I didn't think the price could possibly be that high.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;I tried immediately to delete my credit card and cancel my plan, but the &quot;Remove Card&quot; button is greyed out, and it says you can &quot;modify your subscription by contacting us at success@datadoghq.com&quot;:&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;separator&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://3.bp.blogspot.com/-iohuYjKf3_A/V5JzPDN7qHI/AAAAAAABYNM/QBn6pqJ_OL0roteJIyxHWx5wajJRs4_EwCLcB/s1600/dd-cancel.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img border=&quot;0&quot; height=&quot;318&quot; src=&quot;https://3.bp.blogspot.com/-iohuYjKf3_A/V5JzPDN7qHI/AAAAAAABYNM/QBn6pqJ_OL0roteJIyxHWx5wajJRs4_EwCLcB/s400/dd-cancel.png&quot; width=&quot;400&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;So I wrote to success@datadoghq.com:&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;Dear Datadog,&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Everybody on my team was completely mislead by your&lt;br /&gt;horrible pricing description.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Please cancel the subscription for wstein immediately&lt;br /&gt;and remove my credit card from your system.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;This is the first time I've wasted this much money&lt;br /&gt;by being misled by a website in my life.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;I'm also very unhappy that I can't delete my credit&lt;br /&gt;card or cancel my subscription via your website.  It's&lt;br /&gt;like one more stripe API call to remove the credit card&lt;br /&gt;(I know -- I implemented this same feature for my site).&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;hr /&gt;And they responded:&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;Thanks for reaching out. If you'd like to cancel your&lt;br /&gt;Datadog subscription, you're able to do so by going into&lt;br /&gt;the platform under 'Plan and Usage' and choose the option&lt;br /&gt;downgrade to 'Lite', that will insure your credit card&lt;br /&gt;will not be charged in the future. Please be sure to&lt;br /&gt;reduce your host count down to the (5) allowed under&lt;br /&gt;the 'Lite' plan - those are the maximum allowed for&lt;br /&gt;the free plan.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Also, please note you'll be charged for the hosts&lt;br /&gt;monitored through this month. Please take a look at&lt;br /&gt;our billing FAQ.&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;They were right -- I was able to uninstall the daemons, downgrade to Lite, remove my card, etc. all through the website without manual intervention.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;When people have been confused with billing for &lt;a href=&quot;https://cloud.sagemath.com/&quot;&gt;my site&lt;/a&gt;, I have apologized, immediately refunded their money, and opened a ticket to make the UI clearer. &amp;nbsp;DataDog didn't do any of that.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;I wish DataDog would at least clearly state that when you use their service you are potentially on the hook for an &lt;strong&gt;arbitrarily large&lt;/strong&gt; charge for any month. Yes, if they had made that clear, they wouldn't have had me as a customer, so they are not incentivized to do so.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;A fool and their money are soon parted. I hope this post reduces the chances you'll be a fool like me. &amp;nbsp;If you chose to use DataDog, and their monitoring tools are very impressive, I hope you'll be aware of the cost.  &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;ADDED:&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;On &lt;a href=&quot;https://news.ycombinator.com/threads?id=williamstein&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Hacker News&lt;/a&gt; somebody asked: &quot;&lt;span&gt;How could their pricing page be clearer? It says per host in fairly large letters underneath it.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;I'm asking because I will be designing a similar page soon (that's also billed per host) and I'd like to avoid the same mistakes.&quot; &amp;nbsp;My answer:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;[EDIT: This pricing page by the top poster in this thread is way better than I suggest below -- https://www.serverdensity.com/pricing/]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;1.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;span&gt;VERY clearly&lt;/span&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;nbsp;state that when you sign up for the service, then you are on the hook for up to $18*500 = $9000 + tax in charges for any month. Even Google compute engine (and Amazon) don't create such a trap, and have a clear explicit quota increase process.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;div&gt;2. Instead of &quot;HUGE $15&quot; newline &quot;(small light) per host&quot;, put &quot;HUGE $18 per host&quot; all on the same line. It would easily fit. I don't even know how the $15/host datadog discount could ever really work, given that the number of hosts might constantly change and there is no prepayment.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;3. Inform users clearly in the UI at any time how much they are going to owe for that month (so far), rather than surprising them at the end. Again, Google Cloud Platform has a very clear running total in their billing section, and any time you create a new VM it gives the exact amount that VM will cost per month.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;4. If one works with a team, 3 is especially important. The reason that I had monitors on 50+ machines is that another person working on the project, who never looked at pricing or anything, just thought -- he I'll just set this up everywhere. He had no idea there was a per-machine fee.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;comment&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;c00&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;reply&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;comment&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;c00&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;u&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://news.ycombinator.com/reply?id=12146416&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D12145879%2312146416&quot;&gt;reply&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/u&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;comment&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;c00&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;</content>
		<author>
			<name>William Stein</name>
			<email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
			<uri>http://sagemath.blogspot.com/</uri>
		</author>
		<source>
			<title type="html">Sage: Open Source Mathematics Software</title>
			<subtitle type="html">This is my blog about things related to Sage.</subtitle>
			<link rel="self" href="http://sagemath.blogspot.com/feeds/posts/default"/>
			<id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-6365588202025292315</id>
			<updated>2017-10-10T19:05:18+00:00</updated>
		</source>
	</entry>

	<entry>
		<title type="html">DataDog: Don't make the same mistake I did -- a followup and thoughts about very unhappy customers</title>
		<link href="http://sagemath.blogspot.com/2017/09/datadog-dont-make-same-mistake-i-did.html"/>
		<id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-6365588202025292315.post-8893535883917863217</id>
		<updated>2017-09-22T12:32:15+00:00</updated>
		<content type="html">This is a followup to &lt;a href=&quot;http://sagemath.blogspot.com/2016/07/datadogs-pricing-dont-make-same-mistake.html&quot;&gt;my previous blog post about DataDog billing&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;TL;DR:&lt;br /&gt;- I don't recommend DataDog,&lt;br /&gt;- dealing with unhappy customers is hard,&lt;br /&gt;- monitoring for data science nerds?&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=15315028&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Hacker News Comments&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;datadog-at-google-cloud-summit&quot;&gt;DataDog at Google Cloud Summit&lt;/h2&gt;I was recently at the &lt;a href=&quot;https://cloudplatformonline.com/summit-seattle-2017.html&quot;&gt;Seattle Google Cloud Summit&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.datadoghq.com/&quot;&gt;DataDog&lt;/a&gt; was well represented, with the biggest booth and top vendor billing during the keynote. Clearly they are doing something right. I had a past &lt;a href=&quot;http://sagemath.blogspot.com/2016/07/datadogs-pricing-dont-make-same-mistake.html&quot;&gt;unpleasant experience&lt;/a&gt; with them, and I had just been auditing my records and discovered that last year DataDog had actually charged me a&lt;b&gt; lot &lt;/b&gt;more than I thought, so was kind of annoyed. Nonetheless, they kept coming up and talking to me, server monitoring is life-and-death important to me, and their actual software is very impressive in some ways.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Nick Parisi started talking with me about DataDog. He sincerely wanted to know about my past experience with monitoring and the DataDog product, which he was clearly very enthuisiastic about. So I told him a bit, and he encouraged me to tell him more, explaining that he did not work at DataDog last year, and that he would like to know what happened. So he gave me his email, and he was &lt;em&gt;very genuinely concerned and helpful&lt;/em&gt;, so I sent him an email with a link to my post, etc. I didn't receive a response, so a week later I asked why, and received a followup email from Jay Robichau, who is DataDog's Director of Sales.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;conference-call-with-datadog&quot;&gt;Conference Call with DataDog&lt;/h2&gt;Jay setup a conference call with me today at 10am (September 22, 2017). Before the call, I sent him a summary of my blog post, and also requested a refund, especially for the suprise bill they sent me nearly 6 weeks after my post.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;During the call, Jay explained that he was &quot;protecting&quot; Nick from me, and that I would mostly talk with Michelle Danis who is in charge of customer success. My expectation for the call is that we would find some common ground, and that they would at least appreciate the chance to make things right and talk with an unhappy customer. I was also curious about how a successful startup company addresses the concerns of an unhappy customer (me).&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;I expected the conversation to be difficult but go well, with me writing a post singing the praises of the charming DataDog sales and customer success people. A few weeks ago &lt;a href=&quot;https://cocalc.com/&quot;&gt;CoCalc.com&lt;/a&gt; (my employer) had a very unhappy customer who got (rightfully) angry over a miscommunication, told us he would no longer use our product, and would definitely not recommend it to anybody else. I wrote to him wanting to at least continue the discussion and help, but he was completely gone. &lt;em&gt;I would do absolutely anything I could to ensure he is a satisfied, if only he would give me the chance.&lt;/em&gt; Also, there was &lt;a href=&quot;https://cre8math.com/2017/08/27/to-processing-i/comment-page-1/&quot;&gt;a recent blog post&lt;/a&gt; from somebody unhappy with using CoCalc/Sage for graphics, and I reached out to them as best I could to at least clarify things...&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;In any case, here's what DataDog charged us as a result of us running their daemon on a few dozen containers in our Kubernetes cluster (a contractor who is not a native English speaker actually setup these monitors for us):&lt;br /&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;07/22/2016  449215JWJH87S8N4  DATADOG 866-329-4466 NY  $639.19&lt;br /&gt;08/29/2016  2449215L2JH87V8WZ DATADOG 866-329-4466 NY  $927.22&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;br /&gt;I was shocked by the 07/22 bill which spured my post, and discovered the 8/29 one only later. We canceled our subscription on July 22 (cancelling was difficult in itself).&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Michelle started the conference call by explaining that the 08/29 bill was for charges incurred before 07/22, and that &lt;strong&gt;their billing system has over a month lag&lt;/strong&gt; (and it does even today, unlike Google Cloud Platform, say). Then Michelle explained at length many of the changes that DataDog has made to their software to address the issues I (and others?) have pointed out with their pricing description and billing. She was very interested in whether I would be a DataDog customer in the future, and when I said no, she explained that they would not refund my money since the bill was not a mistake.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;I asked if they now provide a periodic summary of the upcoming bill, as Google cloud platform (say) does. She said that today they don't, though they are working on it. They do now provide a summary of usage so far in an admin page.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Finally, I explained in no uncertain terms that I felt misled by their pricing. I expected that they would understand, and pointed out that they had just described to me many ways in which they were addressing this very problem. Very surprisingly, Michelle's response was that she absolutely would not agree that there was any problem with their pricing description a year ago, and they definitely would not refund my money. She kept bringing up the terms of service. I agreed that I didn't think legally they were in the wrong, given what she had explained, just that -- as they had just pointed out -- their pricing and billing was unclear in various ways. They would not agree at all.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I can't recommend doing business with DataDog. I had very much hoped to write the opposite in this updated post. Unfortunately, their pricing and terms are still confusing today compared to competitors, and they are unforgiving of mistakes. This dog bites. &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;(&lt;strong&gt;Disclaimer:&lt;/strong&gt; I took notes during the call, but most of the above is from memory, and I probably misheard or misunderstood something. I invite comments from DataDog to set the record straight.)&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Also, for what it is worth, I definitely&amp;nbsp;&lt;b&gt;do&amp;nbsp;&lt;/b&gt;recommend Google Cloud Platform. &amp;nbsp;They put in the effort to do many things right regarding clear billing.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-do-startups-deal-with-unhappy-customers&quot;&gt;How do Startups Deal with Unhappy Customers?&lt;/h2&gt;I am very curious about how other&lt;b&gt;&lt;i&gt; startups&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/b&gt; deal with unhappy customers. At CoCalc we have had very few &quot;major incidents&quot; yet... but I want to be as prepared as possible. At the Google Cloud Summit, I went to some amazing &quot;war storries by SRE's&quot; session in which they talked about situations they had been in years ago in which their decisions meant the difference between whether they would have a company or job tomorrow or not. These guys clearly have amazing instincts for when a problem was do-or-die serious and when it wasn't. And their deep preparation &quot;in depth&quot; was WHY they were on that stage, and a big reason why older companies like Google are still around. Having a strategy for addressing very angry customers is surely just as important.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;separator&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-91tgUApR4-0/WcVgtf2unPI/AAAAAAABZbA/i2UM_kTIEiQNgKw6qXepuG0c-LKA1SiUQCK4BGAYYCw/s1600/sre.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img border=&quot;0&quot; height=&quot;170&quot; src=&quot;https://3.bp.blogspot.com/-91tgUApR4-0/WcVgtf2unPI/AAAAAAABZbA/i2UM_kTIEiQNgKw6qXepuG0c-LKA1SiUQCK4BGAYYCw/s400/sre.jpg&quot; width=&quot;400&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;center&gt; &lt;b&gt;Google SRE's&lt;/b&gt;: these guys are serious. &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;I mentioned my DataDog story to a long-time Google employee there (16 years!) and he said he had recently been involved in a similar situation with Google's Stackdriver monitoring, where the bill to a customer was $85K in a month just for Stackdriver. I asked what Google did, and he said they refunded the money, then worked with the customer to better use their tools.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;There is of course no way to please all of the people all of the time. However, I genuinely feel that I was ripped off and misled by DataDog, but I have the impression that Jay and Michelle honestly view me as some jerk trying to rip them off for $1500. &amp;nbsp; And they probably hate me for telling you about my experiences.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;So far, with CoCalc we charge customers in advance for any service we provide, so less people are surprised by a bill. &amp;nbsp;Sometimes there are problems with recurring subscriptions when a person is charged for the upcoming month of a subscription, and don't want to continue (e.g., because their course is over), we always fully refund the charge. What does your company do? Why? I do worry that our billing model means that we miss out on potential revenue.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;We all know what successful huge consumer companies like Amazon and Wal-Mart do.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;monitoring-for-data-science-nerds&quot;&gt;Monitoring for Data Science Nerds?&lt;/h2&gt;I wonder if there is interest in a service like DataDog, but targeted at Data Science Nerds, built on CoCalc, which provides hosted collaborative Jupyter notebooks with Pandas, R, etc., pre-installed. &lt;a href=&quot;https://promcon.io/2017-munich/talks/analyze-prometheus-metrics-like-a-data-scientist/&quot;&gt;This talk&lt;/a&gt; at PrometheusCon 2017 mostly discussed the friction that people face moving data from Prometheus to analyze using data science tools (e.g., R, Python, Jupyter). CoCalc provides a collaborative data science environment, so if we were to smooth over those points of friction, perhaps it could be useful to certain people. And &lt;a href=&quot;https://cocalc.com/policies/pricing.html&quot;&gt;much more efficient...&lt;/a&gt;</content>
		<author>
			<name>William Stein</name>
			<email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
			<uri>http://sagemath.blogspot.com/</uri>
		</author>
		<source>
			<title type="html">Sage: Open Source Mathematics Software</title>
			<subtitle type="html">This is my blog about things related to Sage.</subtitle>
			<link rel="self" href="http://sagemath.blogspot.com/feeds/posts/default"/>
			<id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-6365588202025292315</id>
			<updated>2017-10-10T19:05:18+00:00</updated>
		</source>
	</entry>

	<entry>
		<title type="html">Workshop on live structured documents</title>
		<link href="http://opendreamkit.org/2017/08/26/live-documents-workshop/"/>
		<id>http://opendreamkit.org/2017/08/26/live-documents-workshop</id>
		<updated>2017-08-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://opendreamkit.org&quot;&gt;OpenDreamKit&lt;/a&gt; is hosting a workshop on live structured documents
to take place at Simula Research Laboratory in Oslo, Norway
from Monday 16. October to Friday 20. October.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The workshop is dedicated to various aspects of live documents, including:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Authoring language and tools (ReST, XML, latex, …),&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Converters (Sphinx, pandoc, docbook, …),&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Infrastructure for rendering documents,&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Infrastructure for interacting with the computing backends (e.g.  &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/oreillymedia/thebe&quot;&gt;Thebe&lt;/a&gt; based on the Jupyter protocol, &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/sympy/sympy-live/&quot;&gt;sympy live&lt;/a&gt;, …),&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Online services providing computing backends (e.g. &lt;a href=&quot;http://opendreamkit.org/try.jupyter.org&quot;&gt;tmpnb&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://sagecell.sagemath.org/&quot;&gt;sagecell&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://opendreamkit.org/mybinder.org&quot;&gt;binder&lt;/a&gt;, …),&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Integrated collaborative authoring environments (sharelatex, SMC, texmacs, …)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Participants can register &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.eventbrite.com/e/opendreamkit-workshop-on-live-structured-documents-tickets-37364670736&quot;&gt;via eventbrite&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
		<author>
			<name>The OpenDreamKit consortium</name>
			<email>contact@opendreamkit.org</email>
			<uri>http://opendreamkit.org/</uri>
		</author>
		<source>
			<title type="html">OpenDreamKit</title>
			<link rel="self" href="http://opendreamkit.org/atom.xml"/>
			<id>http://opendreamkit.org/</id>
			<updated>2017-10-17T17:06:20+00:00</updated>
		</source>
	</entry>

	<entry>
		<title type="html">OpenDreamKit at Groups St Andrews in Birmingham</title>
		<link href="http://opendreamkit.org/2017/07/29/GroupsStAndrews/"/>
		<id>http://opendreamkit.org/2017/07/29/GroupsStAndrews</id>
		<updated>2017-07-29T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<content type="html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;opendreamkit-at-groups-st-andrews-in-birmingham&quot;&gt;OpenDreamKit at Groups St Andrews in Birmingham&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.groupsstandrews.org/&quot;&gt;Groups St Andrews&lt;/a&gt; is a conference series with
a conference every four years. This year’s Groups St Andrews will be in
Birmingham, and I will attend, bring
a &lt;a href=&quot;http://opendreamkit.org/public/groups-st-andrews-2017.pdf&quot;&gt;poster&lt;/a&gt;, give a contributed talk
about computing in permutation groups, and teach a course on GAP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post serves the main purpose of providing a page on the OpenDreamKit website
that can hold all the links that will appear on the poster, and possible further
information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;links&quot;&gt;Links&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://opendreamkit.org&quot;&gt;OpenDreamKit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://jupyter.org&quot;&gt;Jupyter&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.gap-system.org&quot;&gt;GAP&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://opendreamkit.org/GAP GitHub&quot;&gt;https://github.com/gap-system&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://opendreamkit.org/GAP Packages on GitHub&quot;&gt;https://github.com/gap-packages/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/gap-packages/jupyter-kernel-gap&quot;&gt;GAP Jupyter Kernel&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://sagemath.org&quot;&gt;SageMath&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://cocalc.com&quot;&gt;CoCalc (formerly SageMathCloud&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://openmath.github.io&quot;&gt;OpenMath&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://mathhub.info&quot;&gt;MathHub&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://uniformal.github.io&quot;&gt;MMT&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://mathhub.info/MitM&quot;&gt;Maths in the Middle&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://mathhub.info/mh/mmt/graphs/tgview.html&quot;&gt;Theory Graphs&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://lmfdb.org&quot;&gt;L-Functions and Modular Forms Database&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content>
		<author>
			<name>The OpenDreamKit consortium</name>
			<email>contact@opendreamkit.org</email>
			<uri>http://opendreamkit.org/</uri>
		</author>
		<source>
			<title type="html">OpenDreamKit</title>
			<link rel="self" href="http://opendreamkit.org/atom.xml"/>
			<id>http://opendreamkit.org/</id>
			<updated>2017-10-17T17:06:20+00:00</updated>
		</source>
	</entry>

	<entry>
		<title type="html">Sphinx documentation of Cython code using &quot;binding=True&quot;</title>
		<link href="http://opendreamkit.org/2017/06/09/CythonSphinx/"/>
		<id>http://opendreamkit.org/2017/06/09/CythonSphinx</id>
		<updated>2017-06-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;One of the deliverables (&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/OpenDreamKit/OpenDreamKit/issues/87&quot;&gt;D4.13&lt;/a&gt;)
of the OpenDreamKit project is refactoring the documentation system of &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sagemath.org/&quot;&gt;SageMath&lt;/a&gt;.
The SageMath documentation is built using a heavily customized &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sphinx-doc.org/en/stable/&quot;&gt;Sphinx&lt;/a&gt;.
Many of the customizations are neccessary to support autodoc
(automatically generated documentation from docstrings) for &lt;a href=&quot;http://cython.org/&quot;&gt;Cython&lt;/a&gt; files.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks to some changes I made to Sphinx, autodoc for Cython now works provided that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You use Sphinx version 1.6 or later.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Cython code is compiled with the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;binding=True&lt;/code&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://cython.readthedocs.io/en/latest/src/reference/compilation.html#compiler-directives&quot;&gt;directive&lt;/a&gt;.
See &lt;a href=&quot;http://cython.readthedocs.io/en/latest/src/reference/compilation.html#how-to-set-directives&quot;&gt;How to set directives&lt;/a&gt;
in the Cython documentation.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A small monkey-patch is applied to &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;inspect.isfunction&lt;/code&gt;.
You can put this in your Sphinx &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;conf.py&lt;/code&gt; for example:&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt; def isfunction(obj):
     return hasattr(type(obj), &quot;__code__&quot;)

 import inspect
 inspect.isfunction = isfunction
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was used successfully for the documentation of
&lt;a href=&quot;http://cysignals.readthedocs.io/en/latest/&quot;&gt;cysignals&lt;/a&gt;
and &lt;a href=&quot;http://fpylll.readthedocs.io/en/latest/&quot;&gt;fpylll&lt;/a&gt;.
There is &lt;a href=&quot;https://trac.sagemath.org/ticket/22747&quot;&gt;ongoing work&lt;/a&gt; to do the same for SageMath.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;implementation-of-functions-in-python&quot;&gt;Implementation of functions in Python&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To understand why items 2 and 3 on the above list are needed,
we need to look at how Python implements functions.
In Python, there are two kinds of functions
(we really mean functions here, not methods or other callables):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;User-defined functions, defined with &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;def&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;lambda&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt; &amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; def foo(): pass
 &amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; type(foo)
 &amp;lt;class 'function'&amp;gt;
 &amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; type(lambda x: x)
 &amp;lt;class 'function'&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Built-in functions such as &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;len&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;repr&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;isinstance&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt; &amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; type(len)
 &amp;lt;class 'builtin_function_or_method'&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the CPython implementation, these are completely independent classes
with different behaviours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;user-defined-functions-binding-as-methods&quot;&gt;User-defined functions binding as methods&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just to give one example, built-in functions do not have a
&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;__get__&lt;/code&gt; method, which means that they do not become methods when used in a class.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s consider this class:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;class X(object):
    def printme(self):
        return repr(self)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is essentially equivalent to&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;class X(object):
    printme = (lambda self: repr(self))

&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; X().printme()
'&amp;lt;__main__.X object at 0x7fb342f960b8&amp;gt;'
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, directly putting the built-in function &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;repr&lt;/code&gt; in the class
does not work as expected:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;class Y(object):
    printme = repr

&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; Y().printme()
Traceback (most recent call last):
  File &quot;&amp;lt;stdin&amp;gt;&quot;, line 1, in &amp;lt;module&amp;gt;
TypeError: repr() takes exactly one argument (0 given)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is simply something that built-in functions do not support.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;user-defined-vs-built-in-functions&quot;&gt;User-defined vs. built-in functions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is a list of the main differences between user-defined and built-in functions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;User-defined functions are implemented in Python,
built-in functions are implemented in C.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Only user-defined functions support &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;__get__&lt;/code&gt; and can become methods
(see above).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Only user-defined functions support introspection such as
&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;inspect.getargspec()&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;inspect.getsourcefile()&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;CPython has specific optimizations for calling built-in functions.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;inspect&lt;/code&gt; module and profiling make
a difference between the two kinds of functions.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cython generates C code, so Cython functions must be built-in functions.
This has unfortunate disadvantages, such as the lack of introspection support,
which is particularly important for Sphinx.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-cython-function-type-cyfunction&quot;&gt;The Cython function type: cyfunction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Luckily, the Cython developers came up with a solution:
they invented a completely new function type (called &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;cyfunction&lt;/code&gt;),
which is implemented like built-in functions
but which behaves as much as possible like user-defined functions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By default, functions in Cython are built-in functions.
With the directive &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;binding=True&lt;/code&gt;, functions in Cython become cyfunctions.
Since cyfunctions are not specifically optimized by CPython,
this comes with a performance penalty.
More precisely, calling cyfunctions from Python is slower than
calling built-in functions from Python.
The slowdown can be significant for simple functions.
Within Cython, cyfunctions are as fast as built-in functions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since a &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;cyfunction&lt;/code&gt; is not a built-in function
nor a user-defined function (those two types are not subclassable),
the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;inspect&lt;/code&gt; module (and hence Sphinx) does not recognize it as being a function.
So, to have full inspect support for Cython functions,
we need to change &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;inspect.isfunction&lt;/code&gt;.
After various attempts, I came up with &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;hasattr(type(obj), &quot;__code__&quot;)&lt;/code&gt;
to test whether the object &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;obj&lt;/code&gt; is a function (for introspection purposes).
This will match user-defined functions and cyfunctions
but not built-in functions, nor any other Python type that I know of.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-future-a-pep-to-change-the-function-types&quot;&gt;The future: a PEP to change the function types?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have some vague plans for a Python Enhancement Proposal (PEP)
to change the implementation of the Python function types.
The goal is that Cython functions can be implemented
on top of some standard Python function type,
with all features that cyfunctions currently have,
the performance of built-in functions
and introspection support of user-defined functions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point, it is too early to say anything about the implementation
of this hypothetical future Python function type.
If anything happens, I will surely post an update.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
		<author>
			<name>The OpenDreamKit consortium</name>
			<email>contact@opendreamkit.org</email>
			<uri>http://opendreamkit.org/</uri>
		</author>
		<source>
			<title type="html">OpenDreamKit</title>
			<link rel="self" href="http://opendreamkit.org/atom.xml"/>
			<id>http://opendreamkit.org/</id>
			<updated>2017-10-17T17:06:20+00:00</updated>
		</source>
	</entry>

	<entry>
		<title type="html">RethinkDB must relicense NOW</title>
		<link href="http://sagemath.blogspot.com/2016/10/rethinkdb-must-relicense-now-what-is.html"/>
		<id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-6365588202025292315.post-6758158987467701094</id>
		<updated>2017-06-01T13:25:01+00:00</updated>
		<content type="html">&lt;h2&gt;What is RethinkDB?&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;b&gt;UPDATE:&lt;/b&gt; &amp;nbsp;Several months after I wrote this post, RethinkDB was relicensed. &amp;nbsp;For &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/sagemathinc/cocalc&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;the CoCalc project&lt;/a&gt;, it was too late, and by then we had &lt;a href=&quot;http://blog.sagemath.com/2017/02/09/rethinkdb-vs-postgres.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;already switched to PostgreSQL&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;RethinkDB is a &lt;strong&gt;INCREDIBLE&lt;/strong&gt; high quality polished open source realtime database that is easy to deploy, shard, replicate, and supports a reactive client programming model, which is useful for collaborative web-based applications. Shockingly, the 7-year old company that created RethinkDB &lt;a href=&quot;https://rethinkdb.com/blog/&quot;&gt;has just shutdown&lt;/a&gt;. I am the CEO of a company, &lt;a href=&quot;https://cloud.sagemath.com/&quot;&gt;SageMath, Inc.,&lt;/a&gt; that uses RethinkDB very heavily, so I have a strong interest in RethinkDB surviving as an independent open source project.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;three-types-of-open-source-projects&quot;&gt;Three Types of Open Source Projects&lt;/h2&gt;There are many types of open source projects. &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/rethinkdb/rethinkdb/graphs/contributors?from=2015-09-10&amp;to=2016-10-10&amp;type=c&quot;&gt;RethinkDB was&lt;/a&gt; the type of open source project where most work on RethinkDB has been fulltime focused work, done by employees of the RethinkDB company. RethinkDB is licensed under the AGPL, but the company &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.rethinkdb.com/faq/&quot;&gt;promised to make&lt;/a&gt; the software available to customers under other licenses.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Academia:&lt;/strong&gt; I started the &lt;a href=&quot;http://sagemath.org/&quot;&gt;SageMath&lt;/a&gt; open source math software project in 2005, which has &lt;a href=&quot;https://trac.sagemath.org/&quot;&gt;over 500 contributors&lt;/a&gt;, and a relatively healthy volunteer ecosystem, with about hundred contributors to each release, and many releases each year. These are mostly volunteer contributions by academics: usually grad students, postdocs, and math professors. They contribute because SageMath is directly relevant to their research, and they often contribute state of the art code that implements algorithms they have created or refined as part of their research. Sage is licensed under the GPL, and that license has worked extremely well for us. Academics sometimes even get significant grants from &lt;a href=&quot;https://groups.google.com/forum/#!topic/sage-edu/9FP4mR_Pjbc&quot;&gt;the NSF&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;http://opendreamkit.org/&quot;&gt;the EU&lt;/a&gt; to support Sage development.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Companies:&lt;/strong&gt; I also started the &lt;a href=&quot;http://cython.org/&quot;&gt;Cython&lt;/a&gt; compiler project in 2007, which has had dozens of contributors and is now the defacto standard for writing or wrapping fast code for use by Python. The developers of Cython mostly work at companies (e.g., Google) as a side project in their spare time. (Here's a &lt;a href=&quot;https://mail.python.org/pipermail/cython-devel/2016-October/004948.html&quot;&gt;message today about a new release&lt;/a&gt; from a Cython developer, who works at Google.) Cython is licensed under the Apache License.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-rethinkdb-will-become&quot;&gt;What RethinkDB Will Become&lt;/h2&gt;RethinkDB will no longer be an open source project whose development is sponsored by a single company dedicated to the project. Will it be an academic project, a company-supported project, or dead?&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;A friend of mine at Oxford University surveyed his &lt;strong&gt;academic&lt;/strong&gt; CS colleagues about RethinkDB, and they said they had zero interest in it. Indeed, from an academic research point of view, I agree that &lt;strong&gt;there is nothing interesting about RethinkDB&lt;/strong&gt;. I myself am a college professor, and understand these people! Academic volunteer open source contributors are definitely not going to come to RethinkDB's rescue. The value in RethinkDB is not in the innovative new algorithms or ideas, but in the high quality carefully debugged implementations of standard algorithms (largely the work of bad ass German programmer Daniel Mewes). The RethinkDB devs had to carefully tune each parameter in those algorithms based on extensive automated testing, user feedback, the Jepsen tests, etc.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;That leaves companies. Whether or not you like or agree with this, many companies will &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/search?q=google+agpl+will+not+touch&amp;rlz=1C5CHFA_enUS691US691&amp;oq=google+agpl+will+not+touch&amp;aqs=chrome..69i57j69i64.4391j0j7&amp;sourceid=chrome&amp;ie=UTF-8&quot;&gt;not touch AGPL licensed code&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;br /&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;em&gt;&quot;Google open source guru Chris DiBona says that the web giant continues to ban the lightning-rod AGPL open source license within the company because doing so &quot;saves engineering time&quot; and because most AGPL projects are of no use to the company.&quot;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;This is just the way it is -- it's psychology and culture, so deal with it. In contrast, companies very frequently embrace open source code that is licensed under the Apache or BSD licenses, and they keep such projects alive. The extremely popular PostgreSQL database is &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.postgresql.org/about/licence/&quot;&gt;licensed under an almost-BSD license&lt;/a&gt;. MySQL is freely licensed under the GPL, but &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.mysql.com/about/legal/licensing/oem/&quot;&gt;there are good reasons&lt;/a&gt; why people buy a commercial MySQL license (from Oracle) for MySQL. Like RethinkDB, MongoDB is AGPL licensed, but they are &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mongodb.com/community/licensing&quot;&gt;happy to sell&lt;/a&gt; a different license to companies.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;With RethinkDB today, the only option is AGPL. This very strongly discourage use by the only possible group of users and developers that have any chance to keep RethinkDB from death. If this situation is not resolved as soon as possible, I am &lt;strong&gt;extremely afraid&lt;/strong&gt; that it never will be resolved. Ever. If you care about RethinkDB, you should be afraid too. Ignoring the landscape and culture of volunteer open source projects is dangerous.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-proposal&quot;&gt;A Proposal&lt;/h2&gt;I don't know who can make the decision to relicense RethinkDB. I don't kow what is going on with investors or who is in control. I am an outsider. Here is a proposal that might provide a way out &lt;strong&gt;today&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PROPOSAL:&lt;/strong&gt; Dear RethinkDB, sell me an Apache (or BSD) license to the RethinkDB source code. Make this the last thing your company sells before it shuts down. Just do it.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=12680444&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Hacker News Discussion&lt;/a&gt;</content>
		<author>
			<name>William Stein</name>
			<email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
			<uri>http://sagemath.blogspot.com/</uri>
		</author>
		<source>
			<title type="html">Sage: Open Source Mathematics Software</title>
			<subtitle type="html">This is my blog about things related to Sage.</subtitle>
			<link rel="self" href="http://sagemath.blogspot.com/feeds/posts/default"/>
			<id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-6365588202025292315</id>
			<updated>2017-10-10T19:05:18+00:00</updated>
		</source>
	</entry>

	<entry>
		<title type="html">SageMath GSoC 2017 Projects</title>
		<link href="http://blog.harald.schil.ly/2017/05/sagemath-gsoc-2017-projects.html"/>
		<id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3473399517246044360.post-5304490995105111973</id>
		<updated>2017-05-05T18:03:53+00:00</updated>
		<content type="html">&lt;div dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;&lt;h2&gt;&lt;span&gt;6 GSoC SageMath Projects&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;span&gt;During the past couple of summers, SageMath successfully managed many &lt;a href=&quot;https://summerofcode.withgoogle.com/&quot;&gt;Google Summer of Code&lt;/a&gt; projects. This year we are again &lt;a href=&quot;https://summerofcode.withgoogle.com/organizations/5790079692832768/&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;happy to have six projects&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;h3&gt;&lt;span&gt;Implementing matroid classes and plotting improvements&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;span&gt;(Zachary Gershkoff /&amp;nbsp;Stefan van Zwam)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;blockquote class=&quot;tr_bq&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;This project seeks to implement several common matroid classes in SageMath, along with algorithms for their display and relevant computations. The graphic matroid class in particular will be implemented with a representative graph with methods for Whitney switching and minor operations. This will be accompanied by improvements to the graph theory library, with methods relevant to matroids enabled to support multigraphs. Other modules for this project include improved plotting of rank 3 matroids to eliminate false colinearities, computation of a matroid's automorphism group using SageMath's group theory libraries, and faster minor testing based on an existing trac ticket.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;h3&gt;&lt;span&gt;Expanding the Functionality of Dynamical Systems&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;span&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;Rebecca Lauren Miller / Paul Fili and Ben Hutz)&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;blockquote class=&quot;tr_bq&quot;&gt;As a member of the sage-dynamics community, researchers have compiled a wishlist for algorithms and functionality they would like added. I would like to shorten the wish list for us.For my project I will be completing some desired additions to SAGE from the Sage Dynamics Wiki. I will implement Well’s Algorithm, strengthen the numerical precision in cannonical_height, as well as implement reduced_form for higher dimensions.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Improvement of Complex Dynamics in Sage&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;(Ben Barros / Adam Towsley and Ben Hutz)&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;blockquote class=&quot;tr_bq&quot;&gt;There are three major things that I would like to implement to improve the functionality of Sage in the area Complex Dynamics. The details of the project are summarized in the following list:&lt;br /&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Complex Dynamics Graphical package: &lt;/b&gt;Integrate or implement a complex dynamics software such as Mandel into Sage. This will be done by creating an optional package for Sage. If there is enough demand, the package may become a standard package for Sage at some point.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Spider Algorithm:&lt;/b&gt; The object of the Spider Algorithm is to construct polynomials with assigned combinatorics. For example, we may want to find a polynomial that has a periodic orbit of period 7. The Spider Algorithm provides a way for us to compute this polynomial efficiently. I plan to implement this algorithm into Sage.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Coercion: &lt;/b&gt;If you have a map defined over Q, you should be able to take the image of a point over C (i.e. somewhere you have a well-defined embedding) without having to use the command &quot;change_ring()&quot;. Something similar works for polynomials in Sage but it does not work for morphisms/schemes.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Linear-time Implementation of Modular Decomposition of Undirected and Directed Graphs&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;div&gt;(Lokesh Jain / Dima Pasechnik)&lt;/div&gt;&lt;blockquote class=&quot;tr_bq&quot;&gt;This project is aimed at providing linear time implementation for modular decomposition of graphs and digraphs. Modular decomposition is decomposition of graph into modules. A module is a subset of vertices and it is a generalization of connected component in graph. Let us take for example a module X. For any vertex v ∉ X it is either connected or not connected to every vertex of X. Another property of module is that a module can be subset of another module. There are various algorithms which have been published for modular decomposition of graphs. The focus in this project is on linear time complexity algorithms which can be practically implemented. The project further aims to use the modules developed for modular decomposition to implement other functionality like skew partitions. Skew partition is partition of graph into two sets of vertices such that induced graph formed by one set is disconnected and induced graph formed by other set is complement of the first. Modular decomposition is a very important concept in Graph Theory and it has a number of use cases. For instance it has been an important tool for solving optimization and combinatorics problems.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Modular Decomposition of graphs and digraphs&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;div&gt;(Maria Ioanna Spyrakoy /&amp;nbsp;Dima Pasechnik)&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;blockquote class=&quot;tr_bq&quot;&gt;Modular decomposition of (di)graphs is a generalization of the concept of the decomposition of (di)graphs into connected components. Its current implementation in Sage relies on badly broken abandoned C code, and badly needs to be replaced by something that works and is not too slow. However, the only open-source implementations of some of these procedures are either in Java or in Perl, and thus aren't really useful for Sage.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;b&gt;Note:&lt;/b&gt; A attentive reader might notice the similarity between those projects. They will be split regarding the type of graph and be coordinated to not overlap but to augment each other.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Visualizing constructs in cluster algebras and quiver representations&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;div&gt;(Bryan Wang / Travis Scrimshaw)&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;blockquote class=&quot;tr_bq&quot;&gt;I aim to implement visualizations of several key constructs in cluster algebras and quiver representations. The first is Auslander-Reiten quivers, for at least the A_n and D_n cases. The second is labelled endomorphism quivers and mutations within a cluster category, focusing on the A_n case. The third is posets of down-mutations for the A_n case. These features will be useful not only for research purposes, but also as nice examples to play around with and learn from. Aside from these features, I am interested in implementing features for the Quantum Cluster Algebras project.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;All the best for this summer, thank you to Google for making this possible, and sorry to all those candidates who didn't make it ...&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
		<author>
			<name>Harald Schilly</name>
			<email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
			<uri>http://blog.harald.schil.ly/search/label/sage</uri>
		</author>
		<source>
			<title type="html">Harald Schilly</title>
			<link rel="self" href="http://blog.harald.schil.ly/feeds/posts/default/-/sage"/>
			<id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3473399517246044360</id>
			<updated>2017-09-08T10:36:15+00:00</updated>
		</source>
	</entry>

	<entry>
		<title type="html">Release: nbdime 0.3.0</title>
		<link href="http://opendreamkit.org/2017/05/05/nbdime-0.3.0/"/>
		<id>http://opendreamkit.org/2017/05/05/nbdime-0.3.0</id>
		<updated>2017-05-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;We are happy to announce release 0.3.0 of &lt;a href=&quot;https://nbdime.readthedocs.io&quot;&gt;nbdime&lt;/a&gt;,
continuing to improve the process of working with Jupyter notebooks in version control.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The highlight of 0.3 is much improved integration with git, making it easier than ever
to get started with nbdime in git:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;pip install --upgrade nbdime # install nbdime
nbdime config-git --global --enable # tell git to use nbdime when it sees notebooks
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and you can get nice GUI diffs directly from git refs on the command-line:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;nbdiff-web master mynotebook.ipynb
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content>
		<author>
			<name>The OpenDreamKit consortium</name>
			<email>contact@opendreamkit.org</email>
			<uri>http://opendreamkit.org/</uri>
		</author>
		<source>
			<title type="html">OpenDreamKit</title>
			<link rel="self" href="http://opendreamkit.org/atom.xml"/>
			<id>http://opendreamkit.org/</id>
			<updated>2017-10-17T17:06:20+00:00</updated>
		</source>
	</entry>

	<entry>
		<title type="html">Debriefing from a successful Formal Project Review by the EU Commission</title>
		<link href="http://opendreamkit.org/2017/04/26/first-project-review-debriefing/"/>
		<id>http://opendreamkit.org/2017/04/26/first-project-review-debriefing</id>
		<updated>2017-04-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;On April 26th, OpenDreamKit underwent its first formal review by the
European Commission. We presented the achievements of the first 18
months of the project, including
&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/OpenDreamKit/OpenDreamKit/issues?q=label%3AReportingPeriod1&quot;&gt;30 deliverables&lt;/a&gt;
(&lt;a href=&quot;http://opendreamkit.org/events_activities/reports/&quot;&gt;reports&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://opendreamkit.org/meetings/2017-04-26-ProjectReviewPresentations/&quot;&gt;slides&lt;/a&gt;).
Overall, &lt;strong&gt;the feedback was very positive&lt;/strong&gt;, with language such as
“enthusiast”, “brilliant”, “amazing job”, or “things have come along
fantastically”. We made a strong point in our reports and
presentations that a vast majority of what’s happening comes from the
ecosystem we support. All we do is exploit the special resources the
EU is entrusting us to knock down some tough hurdles that are
preventing the ball to roll. &lt;strong&gt;Kudos to our communities!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;debriefing-notes-i-sent-to-the-opendreamkit-participants&quot;&gt;Debriefing notes I sent to the OpenDreamKit participants&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;About twenty of us were in Brussels early this week for the
OpenDreamKit Month 18 formal review. After two days of intensive
preparation, we presented our work on Wednesday to our project officer
and reviewers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are a few points that we need to think about (not unexpected).
But otherwise the hard work we all put since the beginning of the
project came out as quite a show. The panel gave very constructive
feedback and were overall really happy. They appreciate our approach,
our work, our spirit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now is the time to enjoy that appreciation and build on that energy to
do even better in the coming years. Pass this on to our communities!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking of funding: the reviewers made a strong point that we bear a
big responsibility: apparently mathematics does not have a good press
in the high spheres these days. We were &lt;em&gt;very lucky&lt;/em&gt;, as a math
project, to be funded; it’s really because they appreciated so much
the strength of the proposal and our “clever and creative
interpretation of the call” that we made it through. “No other math
project is being funded” (this quote obviously does not apply to
ERCs; the scope is plausibly that of H2020 projects).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They now need strong ammunition to make sure that future calls leave
room for mathematics. So not only do we have to succeed because we
care so much about our aims (and should investigate followups to
pursue them further), but also for the sake of other projects
elsewhere in mathematics. We also need to proactively explain and
highlight to a wider audience what we do in collaboration with our
communities. There is very good stuff going on, let it be seen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some further thoughts needs to be put in how to achieve that. For now,
the take home message is simple: &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;If you witness something nice
happening, from a technical achievement with a wow factor to a thought
provoking anecdote, write a blog post about it&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;. See the
&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/OpenDreamKit/OpenDreamKit.github.io/blob/master/_posts/README.md&quot;&gt;instructions&lt;/a&gt;,
or even just send a brief draft text by e-mail to
&lt;a href=&quot;mailto:m.croucher@sheffield.ac.uk&quot;&gt;Mike Croucher&lt;/a&gt; with
&lt;a href=&quot;mailto:Nicolas.Thiery@u-psud.fr&quot;&gt;me&lt;/a&gt; in CC.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me conclude by thanking the whole band that came to Brussels (with
a special nod to the presenters on which we dumped the most delicate
presentations). I was frustrated as you all were spending all this
time together without tackling what we all really care most. However
we built on our image in the Commission, and used the occasion to
strengthen our group around a joint vision. This is a worthwhile long
term investment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you everybody for all the enthusiastic, dedicated and beautiful
work. It’s an honor and a pleasure to be working with such a team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Remember: pass it on to those supporting you and to your communities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cheers,
		Nicolas&lt;/p&gt;</content>
		<author>
			<name>The OpenDreamKit consortium</name>
			<email>contact@opendreamkit.org</email>
			<uri>http://opendreamkit.org/</uri>
		</author>
		<source>
			<title type="html">OpenDreamKit</title>
			<link rel="self" href="http://opendreamkit.org/atom.xml"/>
			<id>http://opendreamkit.org/</id>
			<updated>2017-10-17T17:06:20+00:00</updated>
		</source>
	</entry>

	<entry>
		<title type="html">Formal Project Review for OpenDreamKit's first reporting period (Sept. 2015 to Feb. 2017)</title>
		<link href="http://opendreamkit.org/2017/04/24/first-project-review/"/>
		<id>http://opendreamkit.org/2017/04/24/first-project-review</id>
		<updated>2017-04-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;At the occasion of its first
(&lt;a href=&quot;http://opendreamkit.org/2017/04/26/first-project-review-debriefing/&quot;&gt;very successful&lt;/a&gt;!)
&lt;a href=&quot;http://opendreamkit.org/meetings/2017-04-26-ProjectReviewPresentations/&quot;&gt;formal review&lt;/a&gt;
by the EU commission, twenty OpenDreamKit participants met on the last
week of April 2017 at the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.clora.eu/en/accueil&quot;&gt;CLORA&lt;/a&gt;
(Club of associated research organisations) headquarters in Brussels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;monday-24-tuesday-25&quot;&gt;Monday 24, Tuesday 25&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Brief Steering Committee (&lt;a href=&quot;http://opendreamkit.org/2017/04/24/brussels-steering-committee/&quot;&gt;Agenda &amp;amp; Minutes&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://mensuel.framapad.org/p/vQTnSyplRr&quot;&gt;Pad&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/OpenDreamKit/OpenDreamKit/issues/222&quot;&gt;Preparation for the review&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;wednesday-26&quot;&gt;Wednesday 26&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://opendreamkit.org/meetings/2017-04-26-ProjectReviewPresentations/&quot;&gt;Formal review&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;a href=&quot;http://opendreamkit.org/2017/04/26/first-project-review-debriefing/&quot;&gt;debriefing notes&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;thursday-27-friday-28&quot;&gt;Thursday 27, Friday 28&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/OpenDreamKit/OpenDreamKit/issues/223&quot;&gt;Coding sprints&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content>
		<author>
			<name>The OpenDreamKit consortium</name>
			<email>contact@opendreamkit.org</email>
			<uri>http://opendreamkit.org/</uri>
		</author>
		<source>
			<title type="html">OpenDreamKit</title>
			<link rel="self" href="http://opendreamkit.org/atom.xml"/>
			<id>http://opendreamkit.org/</id>
			<updated>2017-10-17T17:06:20+00:00</updated>
		</source>
	</entry>

	<entry>
		<title type="html">Steering Committee meeting before the 1st Project Review</title>
		<link href="http://opendreamkit.org/2017/04/24/brussels-steering-committee/"/>
		<id>http://opendreamkit.org/2017/04/24/brussels-steering-committee</id>
		<updated>2017-04-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<content type="html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;participants&quot;&gt;Participants&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A framadate &lt;a href=&quot;https://framadate.org/MPxYiQTu1JZjHuJp&quot;&gt;poll&lt;/a&gt; was created&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;were-present-on-the-steering-committee-day&quot;&gt;Were present on the steering committee day:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nicolas THIERY; Benoît PILORGET; Erik BRAY; Viviane PONS; Vincent DELECROIX; Michael KOHLHASE; Dennis MUELLER; Florian RABE; Tom WIESING; Clément PERNET; Wolfram DECKER; William HART; Dmitrii PASECHNIK; Marcin KOSTUR; Mike CROUCHER; Hans FANGOHR; Alexander KONOVALOV; Stephen LINTON; Luca DE FEO; John CREMONA; Paul-Olivier DEHAYE; Benjamin RAGAN-KELLEY; Jeroen DEMEYER; Konrad HINSEN&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;agenda&quot;&gt;Agenda&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Second amendment to the Grant&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;WP7: overview of the situation and of the measures taken and to be planned&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Overview of the deliverables due for M18&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Best practice for the Project Review&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;minutes&quot;&gt;Minutes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;second-amendment-to-the-grant&quot;&gt;Second amendment to the Grant&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Benoît Pilorget (BP) announced that the Second Amendment should be over in April-May. All the modifications concerning deliverables and the scientific context were accepted. The remaining blocking points were purely administrative and require some time. At the moment these notes are being written (19/05/2017), the Commission seems to have fully agreed on all terms and is about to sign the amendment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Related to this amendment, the consortium expressed their congratulations to Hans Fangohr (HF) for his new position at XFEL, in Hamburg.
All points of the amendment can be found on the github issue &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/OpenDreamKit/OpenDreamKit/issues/193&quot;&gt;#193&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;wp7-overview-of-the-situation-and-of-the-measures-taken-and-to-be-planned&quot;&gt;WP7: overview of the situation and of the measures taken and to be planned:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An open brainstorming session took place.
Resulting from the retirement of Ursula Martin, it appears that some aspects of WP7 that require research-grade  expertise in sociology will be hardly achievable as it is organised today with the current consortium. Therefore solutions must be found so that we don’t just tick the boxes but actually deliver high quality material.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Several options have been discussed:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1) Hire new staff specialised in sociology or likewise field. This solution would probably lead to the transfer of some funding within the consortium, unless it turns out enough Person-Months are planned at UOXF&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2) Subcontract the planned work not feasible. For this solution to work out, one must find an adequate subcontractor (providing enough funds are available within UOXF or the consortium) and sign an amendment to the Grant with the Commission&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;3) Rethink the scientific content (objectives, tasks, deliverables), to take into account all we have learned since the writing of the proposal, and make the best use of the available ressources and consortium expertise. This of course would require a negotiation with the EU and probably a new amendment to the grant agreement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The consortium is expecting official feedback from the Project Officer and reviewers after the formal review. In the meantime, the Coordinator and Principal Investigators of WP7 will be informally brainstorming all possibilities. Were an amendment necessary, it will be written after the current amendment for the addition of FAU Erlangen and XFEL is signed by the Commission.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;overview-of-the-deliverables-due-for-m18-and-24&quot;&gt;Overview of the deliverables due for &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/OpenDreamKit/OpenDreamKit/milestone/62?closed=1&quot;&gt;M18&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/OpenDreamKit/OpenDreamKit/milestone/65&quot;&gt;24&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a tour de table, the Coordinator ensured that all deliverables due for Month 24 (31/08/2017) have a leader and a definite working plan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;best-practice-for-the-project-review&quot;&gt;Best practice for the Project Review:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;BP reminded the consortium of the &lt;a href=&quot;http://opendreamkit.org/meetings/2017-01-19-EdinburghSteeringCommittee/Review-presentation/&quot;&gt;support slides&lt;/a&gt; for the Review that were presentend at the Edinburgh steering committee meeting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;feedback-from-the-quality-review-board&quot;&gt;Feedback from the Quality Review Board&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;HF, the chair of the Quality Review Board (QRB), expressed rough positive feedback from the first QRB meeting. A full report will be made available for all participants.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
		<author>
			<name>The OpenDreamKit consortium</name>
			<email>contact@opendreamkit.org</email>
			<uri>http://opendreamkit.org/</uri>
		</author>
		<source>
			<title type="html">OpenDreamKit</title>
			<link rel="self" href="http://opendreamkit.org/atom.xml"/>
			<id>http://opendreamkit.org/</id>
			<updated>2017-10-17T17:06:20+00:00</updated>
		</source>
	</entry>

	<entry>
		<title type="html">The story behind our website</title>
		<link href="http://opendreamkit.org/2017/04/06/website/"/>
		<id>http://opendreamkit.org/2017/04/06/website</id>
		<updated>2017-04-06T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;OpenDreamKit uses a &lt;em&gt;static website&lt;/em&gt; powered by Jekyll and GitHub. Ever wondered
what it means? &lt;a href=&quot;http://openpyviv.com/2017/04/05/static/&quot;&gt;Read this post&lt;/a&gt; to discover.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
		<author>
			<name>The OpenDreamKit consortium</name>
			<email>contact@opendreamkit.org</email>
			<uri>http://opendreamkit.org/</uri>
		</author>
		<source>
			<title type="html">OpenDreamKit</title>
			<link rel="self" href="http://opendreamkit.org/atom.xml"/>
			<id>http://opendreamkit.org/</id>
			<updated>2017-10-17T17:06:20+00:00</updated>
		</source>
	</entry>

	<entry>
		<title type="html">Report on WomenInSage</title>
		<link href="http://opendreamkit.org/2017/04/06/WomenInSage/"/>
		<id>http://opendreamkit.org/2017/04/06/WomenInSage</id>
		<updated>2017-04-06T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Last January, Viviane Pons, Jessica Striker and Jennifer Balakrishnan organized 
 the first &lt;a href=&quot;https://wiki.sagemath.org/days82&quot;&gt;WomenInSage&lt;/a&gt;
 event in Europe with OpenDreamKit. 20 women spent a week together coding and learning in a rented
house in the Paris area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://opendreamkit.org/public/images/womenInSage/group_photo.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Group picture&quot; class=&quot;img-responsive&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;the-workshop&quot;&gt;The Workshop&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;opening-event&quot;&gt;Opening event&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To open the workshop, Viviane, Jessica, and Jennifer gave a series of &lt;a href=&quot;https://wiki.sagemath.org/days82_sageintro&quot;&gt;introduction 
to Sage&lt;/a&gt; lectures at the Institut Henri Poincaré in Paris,
covering combinatorics and number theory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-week&quot;&gt;The Week&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The workshop then moved to the rented house. There, we organized
&lt;em&gt;short talk sessions&lt;/em&gt; to get to know our respective research fields and expectations
for the week. After that, we were able to split into small groups to work on many different
projects: STL export, Krummer surfaces, Kuznyechik cipher, Motzkin words, Shioda invariants,
and more. We also had presentations on &lt;em&gt;How to contribute to Sage&lt;/em&gt; (with a crash course 
on git) and &lt;em&gt;How to write a Sage package&lt;/em&gt;. Every evening, we had a &lt;em&gt;Status report&lt;/em&gt;
session to share our progress with the group. You can read our program and final status
reports on &lt;a href=&quot;https://wiki.sagemath.org/days82&quot;&gt;the event wikipage&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;special-pyladies-coding-cafe&quot;&gt;Special PyLadies coding cafe&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Viviane Pons is one of the organizer of the local Paris chapter for &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.pyladies.com/&quot;&gt;PyLadies&lt;/a&gt;.
She organized a meeting between the WomenInSage mathematician and the PyLadies developers.
We were welcomed by Algolia for an afternoon of coding-and-chatting with the PyLadies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://opendreamkit.org/public/images/womenInSage/pyladies-WIS.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Group picture with PyLadies&quot; class=&quot;img-responsive&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;impact&quot;&gt;Impact&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The data presented here come from a post-event questionnaire sent to the participants.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The gender gap is very important in the mathematic development community. In the 
OpenDreamKit project, among the 54 participants we are only 3 women. This reflects
the global situation in the field. Many mathematician women are still hesitant to join
our community and lack confidence in their abilities as developers. Organizing a
women targeted event is a way to motivate them and building up self-confidence in a safe
and casual atmosphere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The women who attended the conference had various level of programming experience
ranging from 1 (no experience) to 5 (a lot of experience).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://opendreamkit.org/public/images/womenInSage/programming-knowledge.png&quot; alt=&quot;1: 1 people, 2: 7 people, 3: 3 people , 4: 5 people, 5: 1 people&quot; class=&quot;img-responsive&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This disparity also reflected in their knowledge of Sage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://opendreamkit.org/public/images/womenInSage/sage-knowledge.png&quot; alt=&quot;1: 1 people, 2: 8 people, 3: 3 people , 4: 3 people, 5: 2 people&quot; class=&quot;img-responsive&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As for contributions, only 4 participants had contributed to Sage in the past 
which included the 3 organizers. Also, a majority of participants had never attended
a Sage Days before. Actually, 6 of them had never even heard of Sage Days and 2 
of them said they did not think it was “for them”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://opendreamkit.org/public/images/womenInSage/sage-days-attendance.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To the question “How did the fact that the event was targeted to women impact your decision to come?  (Would you have participated in a classical SageDays)”,
Many participants answered that it was indeed a factor a their decision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;cite&gt;Yes, but it helped. I didn´t feel so sure about my skills and being surrounded by women made things easier.&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;cite&gt;It was a new experience that I don’t regret at all.&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;cite&gt;I might have participated, but would have been less confident.&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;cite&gt;I have participated in and benefited from classical SageDays, but found this event to be even better at creating an atmosphere where everyone felt empowered to learn and contribute.&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;cite&gt;I made a special effort I would not have done for regular sage days.&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the participant said she would not have felt comfortable sharing a house
with men but that this event was such positive experience that she would now consider
it for other Sage days. The event helped building up the confidence of the participants, 9 of them said 
they felt more confident to attend classical Sage Days after the event.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://opendreamkit.org/public/images/womenInSage/future_sage_days.png&quot; alt=&quot;What are the chances you attend a &quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We took advantage of the diverse knowledge background of our group to work together
and learn from each other. It was an occasion for many “first times” among participants
who had very little experience with Sage:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;5 participants installed a source version of Sage for the first time (so that they could edit the source).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;3 used git for the first time.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;5 used git within Sage for the first time.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;11 got their first Trac account .&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;5 got their first contribution to a Sage ticket.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;8 are in the process of getting their first code integrated to Sage.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We worked on &lt;a href=&quot;https://trac.sagemath.org/search?q=days82&quot;&gt;14 tickets&lt;/a&gt; during the week, 
6 of those which have been merged since the conference. All participants said they
had learned new things and it would impact their careers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://opendreamkit.org/public/images/womenInSage/learn_new_things.png&quot; alt=&quot;Did you learn new things at this conference? 1:0 people, 2: 0 people, 3: 2 people, 4: 6 people, 5: 9 people&quot; class=&quot;img-responsive&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://opendreamkit.org/public/images/womenInSage/impact.png&quot; alt=&quot;Did you think what you learned will have an impact on your future research/career? 1:0 people, 2: 0 people, 3: 1 people, 4: 10 people, 5: 6 people&quot; class=&quot;img-responsive&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This also was an occasion to start projects and form more research and development collaborations for future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://opendreamkit.org/public/images/womenInSage/people.png&quot; alt=&quot;Did you meet interesting people? 1:0 people, 2: 0 people, 3: 0 people, 4: 2 people, 5: 15 people&quot; class=&quot;img-responsive&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://opendreamkit.org/public/images/womenInSage/projects.png&quot; alt=&quot;Have you started (or carried on) any project that could lead to more research and development in the future? I have started things and will try to follow up: 38.8%. I have started things and willdefinitely follow up: 35.3%. Nothing: 5.3%.&quot; class=&quot;img-responsive&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of this happened in a very casual and welcoming atmosphere. We used the common
rooms of the house to work. We cooked international, vegetarian friendly meals (some
participants had brought food and recipes from their home countries). We got to know
each other and shared more than code. All participants agreed that it was a very 
positive experience. When asked to rate the general atmosphere of the conference,
all of them gave a 5.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://opendreamkit.org/public/images/womenInSage/atmosphere.png&quot; alt=&quot;How did you like the general atmosphere of the conference? 1:0 people, 2: 0 people, 3: 0 people, 4: 0 people, 5: 17 people&quot; class=&quot;img-responsive&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As an organizer, it was also very rewarding and it motivates me to do it again. To
the question: “Any other comment you might have?”, we only got one answer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;cite&gt;All three organizers were so very generous with their time and expertise, and created a wonderful supportive environment. Thank-you!&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>
		<author>
			<name>The OpenDreamKit consortium</name>
			<email>contact@opendreamkit.org</email>
			<uri>http://opendreamkit.org/</uri>
		</author>
		<source>
			<title type="html">OpenDreamKit</title>
			<link rel="self" href="http://opendreamkit.org/atom.xml"/>
			<id>http://opendreamkit.org/</id>
			<updated>2017-10-17T17:06:20+00:00</updated>
		</source>
	</entry>

	<entry>
		<title type="html">Exporting mathematical knowledge from Sage</title>
		<link href="http://opendreamkit.org/2017/03/25/Sage-MMT-export/"/>
		<id>http://opendreamkit.org/2017/03/25/Sage-MMT-export</id>
		<updated>2017-03-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;berlin-workshop&quot;&gt;Berlin workshop&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This week the KWARC team (Michael Kohlhase, Florian Rabe, Dennis Müller) and myself met in Berlin at the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wias-berlin.de/&quot;&gt;WIAS&lt;/a&gt;. The goal was to meet some of the modelers working there, who are very interested in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://uniformal.github.io/doc/&quot;&gt;MMT system&lt;/a&gt; and the work in &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.opendreamkit.org&quot;&gt;OpenDreamKit&lt;/a&gt;. Their entry point is &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/OpenDreamKit//OpenDreamKit/tree/master/WP6&quot;&gt;Work Package 6&lt;/a&gt; (interoperability), motivated by the benefits they would get intrinsically from formalizing the mathematical work they do into the OMDoc/MMT language (&lt;em&gt;e.g.&lt;/em&gt; addressability of mathematical models), but also with an eye on all the other work packages from OpenDreamKit (&lt;em&gt;e.g.&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/OpenDreamKit//OpenDreamKit/tree/master/WP4&quot;&gt;interactive documents&lt;/a&gt;). Personally, I was focused on working out what I could of a semantic interchange between Sage and GAP of mathematical objects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;formalization-of-mathematical-concepts&quot;&gt;Formalization of mathematical concepts&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To start, we decided to do a bit of prototyping around transitive groups. The first step in the Math-in-the-Middle methodology for interoperability between computer algebra systems is to formalize the mathematical concept itself. Recent progress on the MMT language has actually made this very practical (see also &lt;a href=&quot;https://gl.mathhub.info/MitM/smglom/blob/master/source/permutation-group.mmt&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://opendreamkit.org/assets/transitive_groups.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;MMT syntax for transitive groups&quot; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A mathematician should be able to point to this and get near universal agreement in the community on what that means.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Line 24 is of course critical to the definition, but one can see that the rest is well structured and readable. I have omitted here the first five lines, which consist of &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;include&lt;/code&gt; statements, and make the whole thing a completely formal definition yet implemented at a very high level of abstraction. You could slim down those &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;include&lt;/code&gt;s and build the same thing on flexiformal foundations, &lt;em&gt;e.g.&lt;/em&gt; not bother with the logic “deep down”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, not many mathematicians might be able to write this, but almost any mathematician can navigate her way through it. It also helps that the jEdit editor and the MathHub webserver have drastically improved, especially in ease of use (work done as part of &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/OpenDreamKit//OpenDreamKit/tree/master/WP4&quot;&gt;Work Package 4&lt;/a&gt;), but also installation and resilience (work done as part of &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/OpenDreamKit//OpenDreamKit/tree/master/WP3&quot;&gt;Work Package 3&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;math-in-the-middle-methodology&quot;&gt;Math-in-the-Middle methodology&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://opendreamkit.org/assets/mitm.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;MitM paradigm&quot; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that we have a target formalization, the idea is to separately make Sage and GAP interact with it. In the &lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/1603.06424&quot;&gt;Math-in-the-Middle (MitM) formalism&lt;/a&gt; adopted for Work Package 6, we think of having in the “center” a system-independent flexiformalization of the mathematical domains (represented in this diagram in blue; replace in your head EC for elliptic curves with TG for transitive groups).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next step is to work on the reddish clouds, which are the interface theories between this center and the other systems. These interface theories mainly flexiformalize the system-specific aspects of the domain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the GAP side, GAP generates for those interfaces OMDoc/MMT Content Dictionaries (CDs) that contain name, type, and documentation for all API functions (constructors, predicates, methods, …). This is automated, has good coverage and is very rich semantically (more on that towards the end of the post). The next step of the plan is then to align the generated system CDs with the MitM formalization by the MMT &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;implements&lt;/code&gt; relation of aligment (&lt;em&gt;e.g.&lt;/em&gt; an aligment could be: GAP-&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;transitive_group&lt;/code&gt; MMT-&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;implements&lt;/code&gt; MitM-&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;transitive group&lt;/code&gt;). If equivalent Sage CDs were available, as well as Sage alignments, we would get a semantic crosswalk between GAP and Sage by composing the MitM alignments between all those different CDs. This would provide the necessary framework for interoperability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the moment Sage does export some of its knowledge into CDs, thanks to what was implemented by Nicolas Thiéry, leveraging his &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;category&lt;/code&gt; framework. This is unfortunately not enough to cover transitive groups, which have rich structure as category objects (but the “Category of Transitive Groups” does not exist in Sage). Given the circumstances of this workshop, I thus decided to focus on the Sage side, and see what information I could extract about transitive groups.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;exporting-knowledge-from-sage&quot;&gt;Exporting knowledge from Sage&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you look at Sage’s &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;TransitiveGroup&lt;/code&gt;, a lot of mathematical knowledge is acquired from elsewhere through the class hierarchy lying above &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;TransitiveGroup&lt;/code&gt;, and the category framework that instruments that hierarchy. This lead me to first try to build a model of how the Sage class &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;TransitiveGroup&lt;/code&gt; was actually implemented and what it was doing, but this was a mistake. Indeed, it was very difficult, as I got lost between meta-logics and what I was actually trying to do: modeling Sage? modeling how Sage models math? how python uses Sage to model math? I was trying to do too much, too early and was probably the wrong person to do that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you look back at the methodology, the MitM CDs don’t need to link up to the Math-in-the-Middle content dictionary right away. This is actually up to the alignments, that come later (and could be done by a different person). I was trying to do both at once, while my focus should really have been: “how do I export, but not align, as much of the math knowledge as possible embedded into Sage into a language that can easily be processed by the KWARC team?” (for the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;categories&lt;/code&gt; export built by Nicolas Thiéry, the export went through JSON).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;OK then, the question now becomes: “where is math knowledge embedded in Sage that is relevant to the mathematical concept of transitive group?” The first response is of course still “Everywhere!”, but where are actually the low hanging fruits?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;a-math-skeleton&quot;&gt;A math skeleton&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I found that the best way to communicate around this issue with the KWARC team is by extracting from Sage code a “math skeleton”. For this, the Sage-specific module &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;sageinspect&lt;/code&gt; was very useful. I thus introspected the sage object corresponding to the class &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;TransitiveGroup&lt;/code&gt;, and related objects:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;# sage/src/sage/structure/sage_object.pyx
cdef class SageObject:

# sage/local/lib/python2.7/site-packages/sage/categories/category.py
class Category(UniqueRepresentation, SageObject):

# sage/src/sage/structure/category_object.pyx
cdef class CategoryObject(SageObject):

# sage/local/lib/python2.7/site-packages/sage/structure/parent.pyx
cdef class Parent(category_object.CategoryObject):

# sage/src/sage/groups/group.pyx
cdef class Group(Parent):

# sage/src/sage/groups/group.pyx
cdef class FiniteGroup(Group):

# sage/local/lib/python2.7/site-packages/sage/groups/perm_gps/permgroup.py
class PermutationGroup_generic(group.FiniteGroup):

# sage/local/lib/python2.7/site-packages/sage/groups/perm_gps/permgroup_named.py
class PermutationGroup_unique(CachedRepresentation, PermutationGroup_generic):

# sage/local/lib/python2.7/site-packages/sage/groups/perm_gps/permgroup_named.py
class TransitiveGroup(PermutationGroup_unique):
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What is mathematical here? Clearly, just about everything, but that is because I was selective in the printout given above: I worked up the class hierarchy from &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;TransitiveGroup&lt;/code&gt; by hand, but excluded all the python objects that &lt;em&gt;don’t&lt;/em&gt; inherit from &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;SageObject&lt;/code&gt;. For instance, you don’t see in that list:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;# sage/local/lib/python2.7/site-packages/sage/structure/unique_representation.py
class CachedRepresentation:
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;CachedRepresentation&lt;/code&gt; is only relevant, from a mathematical standpoint, in &lt;em&gt;where&lt;/em&gt; it appears as a superclass. Its own internals are pure design decisions for CAS software, not mathematics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The criterion to use for “related objects” is thus that only objects inheriting from &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;SageObject&lt;/code&gt; need to be navigated. So we are navigatin in the class hierarchy diamond between &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;TransitiveGroup&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;SageObject&lt;/code&gt;, collecting classes, which I manually imported from the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;sage&lt;/code&gt; library (obviously this could be automated):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;from sage.structure.sage_object import SageObject
from sage.structure.category_object import Category     # not strictly in the class hierarchy, but included to facilitate discussion
from sage.structure.category_object import CategoryObject
from sage.structure.parent import Parent
from sage.groups.group import Group
from sage.groups.group import FiniteGroup
from sage.groups.perm_gps.permgroup import PermutationGroup_generic
from sage.groups.perm_gps.permgroup_named import PermutationGroup_unique
from sage.groups.perm_gps.permgroup_named import TransitiveGroup
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is how I selected the objects from which I wanted to extract more information, producing the list of class definitions above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[Note by the way the weird changes in the path to &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;sageinspect.sage_getsource&lt;/code&gt; in the listing above (why??? because of interactions between &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;import&lt;/code&gt; statements?)]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;more-flesh-on-the-skeleton&quot;&gt;More flesh on the skeleton&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next step is to add a bit of flesh to that skeleton export. Obviously this is going to be more intricate. I have included &lt;a href=&quot;https://gl.mathhub.info/ODK/Sage/blob/master/sage/transitive_group_example.py&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; what you get when you look at all the methods &lt;em&gt;coming out of the source code&lt;/em&gt; for &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;TransitiveGroup&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;PermutationGroup_unique&lt;/code&gt;, etc. In other words, a completely static navigation to the specific methods. This was the right thing to do for communicating with the KWARC team, but is wrong for our ultimate purpose. It was the right thing to do to communicate with KWARC (or in a blog post) as it distilled Sage to its most interesting bits, and we could fill the gaps relying on comment concepts (like “class hierarchy”). However, as a quicker way to get more consistent and richer Sage output, I could have navigated dynamically to the relevant classes, and extracted all the methods available from the live objects. This is of course because tons of methods get added when the object gets created, with a lot of mathematics packed into that. The same math could be reconstructed from the source code, but obviously that would be harder to do as we would be re-emulating a lot of what python does.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In any case, here is the full printout of what I get for just the method declarations for &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;PermutationGroup_generic&lt;/code&gt;, the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Parent&lt;/code&gt; that is most interesting:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;
# sage/local/lib/python2.7/site-packages/sage/groups/perm_gps/permgroup.py
class PermutationGroup_generic(group.FiniteGroup):
    def __init__(self, gens=None, gap_group=None, canonicalize=True, domain=None, category=None):
    def construction(self):
    def _has_natural_domain(self):
    def _gap_init_(self):
    def _magma_init_(self, magma):
    def __cmp__(self, right):
    def _element_class(self):
    def __call__(self, x, check=True):
    def _coerce_impl(self, x):
    def list(self):
    def __contains__(self, item):
    def has_element(self, item):
    def __iter__(self):
    def gens(self):
    def gens_small(self):
    def gen(self, i=None):
    def identity(self):
    def exponent(self):
    def largest_moved_point(self):
    def degree(self):
    def domain(self):
    def _domain_gap(self, domain=None):
    def smallest_moved_point(self):
    def representative_action(self,x,y):
    def orbits(self):
    def orbit(self, point, action=&quot;OnPoints&quot;):
    def transversals(self, point):
    def stabilizer(self, point, action=&quot;OnPoints&quot;):
    def base(self, seed=None):
    def strong_generating_system(self, base_of_group=None):
    def _repr_(self):
    def _latex_(self):
    def _order(self):
    def order(self):
    def random_element(self):
    def group_id(self):
    def id(self):
    def group_primitive_id(self):
    def center(self):
    def socle(self):
    def frattini_subgroup(self):
    def fitting_subgroup(self):
    def solvable_radical(self):
    def intersection(self, other):
    def conjugacy_class(self, g):
    def conjugacy_classes(self):
    def conjugate(self, g):
    def direct_product(self, other, maps=True):
    def semidirect_product(self, N, mapping, check=True):
    def holomorph(self):
    def subgroup(self, gens=None, gap_group=None, domain=None, category=None, canonicalize=True, check=True):
    def as_finitely_presented_group(self, reduced=False):
    def quotient(self, N):
    def commutator(self, other=None):
    def cohomology(self, n, p = 0):
    def cohomology_part(self, n, p = 0):
    def homology(self, n, p = 0):
    def homology_part(self, n, p = 0):
    def character_table(self):
    def irreducible_characters(self):
    def trivial_character(self):
    def character(self, values):
    def conjugacy_classes_representatives(self):
    def conjugacy_classes_subgroups(self):
    def subgroups(self):
    def _regular_subgroup_gap(self):
    def has_regular_subgroup(self, return_group = False):
    def blocks_all(self, representatives = True):
    def cosets(self, S, side='right'):
    def minimal_generating_set(self):
    def normalizer(self, g):
    def centralizer(self, g):
    def isomorphism_type_info_simple_group(self):
    def is_abelian(self):
    def is_commutative(self):
    def is_cyclic(self):
    def is_elementary_abelian(self):
    def isomorphism_to(self, right):
    def is_isomorphic(self, right):
    def is_monomial(self):
    def is_nilpotent(self):
    def is_normal(self, other):
    def is_perfect(self):
    def is_pgroup(self):
    def is_polycyclic(self):
    def is_simple(self):
    def is_solvable(self):
    def is_subgroup(self, other):
    def is_supersolvable(self):
    def non_fixed_points(self):
    def fixed_points(self):
    def is_transitive(self, domain=None):
    def is_primitive(self, domain=None):
    def is_semi_regular(self, domain=None):
    def is_regular(self, domain=None):
    def normalizes(self, other):
    def composition_series(self):
    def derived_series(self):
    def lower_central_series(self):
    def molien_series(self):
    def normal_subgroups(self):
    def poincare_series(self, p=2, n=10):
    def sylow_subgroup(self, p):
    def upper_central_series(self):
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are things a semi-intelligent mathematician can deduce from this fleshed-out skeleton, and that we might be able to export automatically:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The arity of all those functions is useful. Unfortunately, this being python (2.x), the type cannot simply be read. Michael Kohlhase has some interesting ideas regarding mathematicians, types and the modeling necessary for MMT. I think he is right, partly, and there is much to look forward to in the services MMT can provide around type inference. Note that it will be core to this process that MMT allows for flexiformalisation as well!&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I omitted docstrings in this export, but of course this is also useful for semantic information in natural language. Often the docstring contains structured information too, for instance some typing information (see above).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;There is, as often, a method called &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;__init__&lt;/code&gt; that specifies a constructor. In other words, some combination of maps from some parameter space into the object modeled by &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;PermutationGroup_generic&lt;/code&gt;. That relationship is messy though, most of the time. Note that the GAP team took the opportunity over last summer to have an intern refactor/regularize the way they did constructors into a more “semantic” way”: essentially instead of using the elementary &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;__init__&lt;/code&gt;, they made a &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;defconstructor&lt;/code&gt; and gave it documentation, type information,… as parameters. Of course &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;defconstructor&lt;/code&gt; elaborates to a call to &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;__init__&lt;/code&gt; but the parameters can be used in the CD generation (and for static type-based optimizations later; ask Markus Pfeiffer @ St. Andrews if you are interested in the details).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;_gap_xxxx&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;_magma_xxxx&lt;/code&gt; indicate that the relevant “stuff” exists in the corresponding CASes. This is thus indicating a good place to bootstrap the alignment process between &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;gap&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;sage&lt;/code&gt;, and therefore extract KPIs and generally optimize our progress. This would be best done by instrumenting at the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;SageObject&lt;/code&gt; level, since this is where all those &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;_other-computer-algebra-system_xxxx&lt;/code&gt; methods are first located, as abstract methods.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the presence of magic methods &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;__xxxxxxx__&lt;/code&gt; indicates the existence of a relation of some kind on the elements of &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;PermutationGroup_generic&lt;/code&gt;, which is a Sage &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Parent&lt;/code&gt;. However, this information is best extracted from the categories export itself, presumably all(?) the time.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;is_xxxx&lt;/code&gt; methods indicate the existence of a test and thus a property.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;after some very basic pruning, all the other methods indicate the existence of clear mathematical objects, often relatively simple maps.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many of the deductions made above will be done in the same way for all &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Parent&lt;/code&gt;s (at least if we go for the easiest information to grab), so that’s where the instrumentation should go. Most of that instrumentation actually makes sense to have in a CAS, beceause it exposes mathematically relevant concepts. It would simply be used by the exporter generating the Content Dictionary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Remark:&lt;/strong&gt; Ultimately we want to extract information from live objects. It should not be lost, however, that what we are trying to do is partly a social process (the study of this process is itself the topic of &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/OpenDreamKit//OpenDreamKit/tree/master/WP7&quot;&gt;Work Package 7&lt;/a&gt;). Humans have built the code from which we are trying to extract information, and now we want to communicate that with other humans so they can in turn code on top of that. Those other humans are familiar with different tools. For instance the KWARC team uses MMT related tools, like MathHub, but not Sage. Presumably other CAS developers or even “plain” mathematicians will just see Sage through an interface built on top of MMT. So I would advocate that we:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Make sure to export &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; the information containing math from Sage into MMT, even that which is not readable beyond text by the system we export to;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Devise methods to make this informal export as addressable as possible from within MMT, but not necessarily runnable.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Step 1. could be useful for instance if one is working in GAP and asking “How does Sage do that?”. We should be able to access Sage source code from within GAP, and it will be useful for automating some tasks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Step 2. would be useful for students in the KWARC group, for instance, who would then be able to extract semantically richer information from a system like Sage with just verbal instructions from domain specific experts, because the data is now in MMT format. It splits the step in two: MMT extraction and semantic extraction, and requires different skills.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The process could be further accelerated, I bet, by exposing also deep sage introspection tools into MMT.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this stage self-preservation instincts kick in and I don’t want to think deeper at this proposal from a logical standpoint.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt; &lt;em&gt;I wish to thank Michael Kohlhase for suggestions that have improved the first draft of this post.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>
		<author>
			<name>The OpenDreamKit consortium</name>
			<email>contact@opendreamkit.org</email>
			<uri>http://opendreamkit.org/</uri>
		</author>
		<source>
			<title type="html">OpenDreamKit</title>
			<link rel="self" href="http://opendreamkit.org/atom.xml"/>
			<id>http://opendreamkit.org/</id>
			<updated>2017-10-17T17:06:20+00:00</updated>
		</source>
	</entry>

	<entry>
		<title type="html">Report on the WP6-WIAS Workshop on Math-in-the-Middle Content</title>
		<link href="http://opendreamkit.org/2017/03/24/WIAS/"/>
		<id>http://opendreamkit.org/2017/03/24/WIAS</id>
		<updated>2017-03-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;WP6 participants JacU (Florian Rabe), FAU (Dennis Müller, Michael Kohlhase) and UZH (Paul
Olivier Dehaye) came together with members of the
&lt;a href=&quot;http://wias-berlin.de/&quot;&gt;Weierstrass Institute for Applied Analysis and Stochastics&lt;/a&gt;
(WIAS: Thomas Koprucki and Carsten Tabelow) for a one-week code (20. 3. – 24. 3.)  sprint
on the Math-in-the-Middle Content and Logic and the encoding of mathematical Models. The
result of this was a significant extension of the MitM ontology (in particular for the
meta-theories for Sage) and a
&lt;a href=&quot;http://dx.doi.org/10.20347/WIAS.PREPRINT.2385&quot;&gt;WIAS preprint on formalizations of Models&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
		<author>
			<name>The OpenDreamKit consortium</name>
			<email>contact@opendreamkit.org</email>
			<uri>http://opendreamkit.org/</uri>
		</author>
		<source>
			<title type="html">OpenDreamKit</title>
			<link rel="self" href="http://opendreamkit.org/atom.xml"/>
			<id>http://opendreamkit.org/</id>
			<updated>2017-10-17T17:06:20+00:00</updated>
		</source>
	</entry>

	<entry>
		<title type="html">SageMathCloud for OpenDreamKit</title>
		<link href="http://opendreamkit.org/2017/03/08/SMC/"/>
		<id>http://opendreamkit.org/2017/03/08/SMC</id>
		<updated>2017-03-08T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Part of OpenDreamKit’s mission is to work on &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/OpenDreamKit//OpenDreamKit/tree/master/WP4&quot;&gt;user interfaces&lt;/a&gt;
for better collaboration and also &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/OpenDreamKit//OpenDreamKit/tree/master/WP3&quot;&gt;component architectures&lt;/a&gt;.
This is why the &lt;a href=&quot;http://cloud.sagemath.com/&quot;&gt;SageMathCloud&lt;/a&gt; platform is of special
interest for us. One of our tasks is even to &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/OpenDreamKit/OpenDreamKit/issues/55&quot;&gt;have a deeper look into its code base&lt;/a&gt;.
In this post, as part of our &lt;em&gt;Review on emerging technologies&lt;/em&gt;, we propose an overview
of the platform.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-is-sagemathcloud&quot;&gt;What is SageMathCloud?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SageMathCloud is an online platform which allows the creation of &lt;strong&gt;collaborative scientific projects&lt;/strong&gt;
including many scientific softwares and tools like &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sagemath.org/&quot;&gt;SageMath&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href=&quot;http://jupyter.org/&quot;&gt;Jupyter&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.scipy.org/&quot;&gt;SciPy&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://julialang.org/&quot;&gt;Julia&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href=&quot;https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/LaTeX&quot;&gt;Latex&lt;/a&gt;, and more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Its codebase is &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/sagemathinc/smc&quot;&gt;open-source&lt;/a&gt;, distributed under the GNU General Public
License. The platform is run by a private company (SageMath Inc.) created by William Stein
who is also the initiator of the SageMath software. The platform offers both free
and paying premium accounts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;projects&quot;&gt;Projects&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main tool of the SageMathCloud platform is the possibility to create &lt;strong&gt;projects&lt;/strong&gt;
from which you can access the many features. A single user can create as many
projects as needed. Each project is an &lt;strong&gt;independant Linux virtual machine&lt;/strong&gt;. It
thus comes with a full file system and an &lt;strong&gt;online terminal&lt;/strong&gt; that allows you to
run Linux commands. The storage of each project is limited by default but can be
extended on premium accounts. You can access the files through the SageMathCloud
web interface or also through ssh.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One key feature is that each project can be &lt;strong&gt;shared by multiple users&lt;/strong&gt;. This allows
sharing access to the files and also &lt;strong&gt;real time editing&lt;/strong&gt; though the platform. Single
files or folders can also be made &lt;strong&gt;public&lt;/strong&gt;. A link is then provided which allows
either viewing or downloading the files (even without a SageMathCloud account) and
also an easy way to copy onto a different SageMathCloud project owned by the viewer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;softwares&quot;&gt;Softwares&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you create a SageMathCloud project, your Linux virtual machine comes with many
softwares and tools especially useful for mathematicians and scientists in general.
We list here the most important ones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sage&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Sage worksheets&lt;/strong&gt;. As the name indicates, the platform was primarily
 developed as a replacement for the old Sage notebook server to allow collaborative
 online work using Sage. The &lt;strong&gt;SageMath&lt;/strong&gt; software is of course installed by default
 on the virtual machine and one can run Sage through the online terminal. The platform
 also offers its own &lt;strong&gt;Sage worksheet filetype&lt;/strong&gt; to edit and run Sage code in a cell-type
 system (as in the Jupyter notebook or the old Sage notebook) mixed with other cell types
 like text and HTML. This is used to create interactive worksheets that can be easily
 shared and copied.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Jupyter&lt;/strong&gt;. SageMathCloud includes a Jupyter notebook interface with many kernel
 options (Python 2, Python 3, Anaconda, Sage, R, Julia, and more). On top of the usual
 interface, SageMathCloud’s Jupyter offers &lt;strong&gt;real time&lt;/strong&gt; synchronization among
 multi users.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Latex&lt;/strong&gt;. The common document preparation system Latex is installed on the virtual
 machine. It also offers a multi user editor with real time synchronization and
 a dual view of both the Latex source code and pdf output.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;notebooks-smc-sage-and-jupyter&quot;&gt;Notebooks: SMC, Sage and Jupyter&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SageMathCloud offers very inovative features in terms of notebooks which should be studied
both on technichal and usability aspects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Real time notebooks&lt;/strong&gt;. Real time multi user synchronization
 is a key aspect of SageMathCloud development. In particulatr, it has been a motivation
 for the development of SageMathCloud homemade Sage worksheet. More recently, it has
 also been added to the &lt;strong&gt;Jupyer notebook&lt;/strong&gt; by &lt;em&gt;enhancing&lt;/em&gt; the original
 software. This enhancement is of particular interest for OpenDreamKit as this could
 benefit all Jupyer users.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Muli-kernel, multi-client&lt;/strong&gt;. The multi-kernel philosophy is an inherent part
 of Jupyer development. Indeed, Jupyer is a notebook interface that can be used
 with many different language kernels (python, Sage, Julia, and more). SageMathCloud
 follows the same spirit and offers a variety of kernels on the Sage worksheet. One advantage
 of the Sage worksheet is that it allows for &lt;strong&gt;many kernels&lt;/strong&gt; to be used in different
 cells of one single worksheet (in Jupyer, the kernel has to be chosen once and for all
 for the entire worksheet). Furthermore, SageMathCloud has developed what they call the &lt;strong&gt;Jupyer
 bridge&lt;/strong&gt;: allowing user to run a Jupyer kernel from within a Sage worksheet. In this
 sense, the Sage worksheet could be seen as alternative client to Jupyer the same way one
 can develop alternative kernels. More on this question can be read on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/sagemathinc/smc/wiki/sagejupyter&quot;&gt;github page&lt;/a&gt; of SageMathInc.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sharing-and-teaching-with-sagemathcloud&quot;&gt;Sharing and teaching with SageMathCloud&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;accessibility&quot;&gt;Accessibility&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The great advantage of SageMathCloud is that it offers a &lt;strong&gt;complete scientific environment&lt;/strong&gt;
without the usual setting up hassle. It makes the different software very easy to access
independently of the user personal system as long as there is an access to a good Internet
connexion. As an example, a mathematician can share a demo of code (in a Jupyter
or a Sage notebook) that could be used directly by its collaborators. Of course,
the Internet access is itself a limit. Given poor network access, for example but not only
in some developing countries where bandwidth is sometimes limited.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;teaching&quot;&gt;Teaching&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When teaching is concerned, the sharing facilities of SageMathCloud come very useful.
Moreover, the platform offers a course managing system. The principle is as follows:
the teacher has acces to a “main project” containing the class material; every student
has its own project which is shared with the teacher. The course management system
allows for automatic actions like:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Create all the student projects where the teacher is automatically added as a
 collaborator.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Create assignments by copying some material from the main project to the students
 projects.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Collecting, grading, and returning assignments by copying back and forth between
 the students projects and the main project.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An &lt;em&gt;assignment&lt;/em&gt; is just a folder. It can have multiple content depending on the class.
Of course, the system is especially interesting when the assignment is given within
an &lt;strong&gt;interactive worksheet&lt;/strong&gt; and can then be achieved by the student directly on the
interface. SageMathCloud then becomes a very good interface to initiate students
to the many scientific softwares it offers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sagemathcloud-and-opendreamkit&quot;&gt;SageMathCloud and OpenDreamKit&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The many features of SageMathCloud make it a very interesting project for OpenDreamKit
to look at. Indeed, it offers one of the leading technologies for scientists in terms of cloud
project management, teaching and sharing facilities. In particular it showcases a collection of
&lt;strong&gt;features&lt;/strong&gt; that have been selected and adopted by a wide
community.It also has some limits which
we would like to address through our project:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Accessibility&lt;/strong&gt;. As previously mentioned, the cloud based interface can not be easily
 accessed in places where the Internet connexion is not good enough. One solution
 would be to have clear easy-to-follow instructions on how to install a SageMathCloud
 platform in a local institution or on a personal machine. This is to be taken care of in D3.2 and D3.4.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Interoperability and file formats&lt;/strong&gt;. At the moment, the SageMathCloud platform
 offers two file formats for interactive worksheet: the Jupyter one and a home-made
 Sage worksheet one. It is not possible to run the Sage worksheets elsewhere than
 on the platform. Especially, there is no way to run a Sage worksheet on a local
 Sage installation. It is not yet clear what a long term unified worksheet solution
 would be and it is part of the OpenDreamKit project to work on this question. The
 technical choices made for the Sage worksheets are interesting to investigate in this
 regard, as well as, file conversions and so on.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;links&quot;&gt;Links&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://sagemath.blogspot.fr/2015/05/guiding-principles-for-sagemath-inc.html&quot;&gt;Guiding principles for SageMath Inc.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://wstein.org/talks/2016-06-sage-bp/bp.pdf&quot;&gt;The origin of SageMath&lt;/a&gt; by William Stein&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://sagemath.blogspot.fr/2014/08/what-is-sagemathcloud-lets-clear-some.html&quot;&gt;What is SageMathCloud&lt;/a&gt; by William Stein&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/sagemathinc/smc/wiki/sagejupyter&quot;&gt;Jupyter and Sage on SageMathCloud&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content>
		<author>
			<name>The OpenDreamKit consortium</name>
			<email>contact@opendreamkit.org</email>
			<uri>http://opendreamkit.org/</uri>
		</author>
		<source>
			<title type="html">OpenDreamKit</title>
			<link rel="self" href="http://opendreamkit.org/atom.xml"/>
			<id>http://opendreamkit.org/</id>
			<updated>2017-10-17T17:06:20+00:00</updated>
		</source>
	</entry>

	<entry>
		<title type="html">Jupyter Notebooks Facilitating Productivity, Sustainability, and Accessibility of Data Science</title>
		<link href="http://opendreamkit.org/2017/03/01/jupyter-cse/"/>
		<id>http://opendreamkit.org/2017/03/01/jupyter-cse</id>
		<updated>2017-03-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Min Ragan-Kelley presented a poster on Jupyter notebooks facilitating
productivity, sustainability, and accessibility of data science and computational science in general.
The poster included the role of OpenDreamKit-supported projects,
such as nbdime and nbval in facilitating reproducible science.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://figshare.com/articles/Jupyter_Notebooks_Facilitating_Productivity_Sustainability_and_Accessibility_of_Data_Science/4696414&quot;&gt;PDF of Poster&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.6084/m9.figshare.4696414.v1&quot;&gt;DOI: 10.6084/m9.figshare.4696414.v1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>
		<author>
			<name>The OpenDreamKit consortium</name>
			<email>contact@opendreamkit.org</email>
			<uri>http://opendreamkit.org/</uri>
		</author>
		<source>
			<title type="html">OpenDreamKit</title>
			<link rel="self" href="http://opendreamkit.org/atom.xml"/>
			<id>http://opendreamkit.org/</id>
			<updated>2017-10-17T17:06:20+00:00</updated>
		</source>
	</entry>

	<entry>
		<title type="html">SageMathCloud tutorial</title>
		<link href="http://opendreamkit.org/2017/02/28/SMCTutorial/"/>
		<id>http://opendreamkit.org/2017/02/28/SMCTutorial</id>
		<updated>2017-02-28T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;We just released &lt;a href=&quot;https://mikecroucher.github.io/SMC_tutorial/&quot;&gt;a tutorial for teachers using SageMathCloud&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
		<author>
			<name>The OpenDreamKit consortium</name>
			<email>contact@opendreamkit.org</email>
			<uri>http://opendreamkit.org/</uri>
		</author>
		<source>
			<title type="html">OpenDreamKit</title>
			<link rel="self" href="http://opendreamkit.org/atom.xml"/>
			<id>http://opendreamkit.org/</id>
			<updated>2017-10-17T17:06:20+00:00</updated>
		</source>
	</entry>

	<entry>
		<title type="html">Distributive Laws</title>
		<link href="http://sheaves.github.io/Distributive-Laws/"/>
		<id>http://sheaves.github.io/Distributive-Laws/</id>
		<updated>2017-02-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I’ve been participating in the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.math.jhu.edu/~eriehl/kanII/&quot;&gt;Kan Extension Seminar II&lt;/a&gt;, and this week it’s my turn to &lt;a href=&quot;https://golem.ph.utexas.edu/category/2017/02/distributive_laws.html&quot;&gt;post about Jon Beck’s “Distributive Laws”&lt;/a&gt; at the &lt;a href=&quot;https://golem.ph.utexas.edu/category/&quot;&gt;n-Category Cafe&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The post uses lots of string diagrams for monads, resulting in pictures like the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://sheaves.github.io/distributive/comp_assoc.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; title=&quot;Associativity of the composite monad&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;See you &lt;a href=&quot;https://golem.ph.utexas.edu/category/2017/02/distributive_laws.html&quot;&gt;there&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;</content>
		<author>
			<name>Liang Ze</name>
			<uri>http://sheaves.github.io/</uri>
		</author>
		<source>
			<title type="html">Sheaves</title>
			<subtitle type="html">Making math concrete with Sage</subtitle>
			<link rel="self" href="http://sheaves.github.io/feed.xml"/>
			<id>http://sheaves.github.io/feed.xml</id>
			<updated>2017-07-16T20:30:07+00:00</updated>
		</source>
	</entry>

	<entry>
		<title type="html">Reports from &quot;Computational Mathematics with Jupyter&quot; workshop</title>
		<link href="http://opendreamkit.org/2017/02/15/JupyterICMS/"/>
		<id>http://opendreamkit.org/2017/02/15/JupyterICMS</id>
		<updated>2017-02-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Jointly with the Collaborative Computational Project &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.codima.ac.uk/&quot;&gt;“CoDiMa - CCP
in the area of Computational Discrete Mathematics”&lt;/a&gt;,
we have organised the workshop
&lt;a href=&quot;http://opendreamkit.org/meetings/2017-01-16-ICMS/&quot;&gt;“Computational Mathematics with Jupyter”&lt;/a&gt;,
which took place at the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.icms.org.uk/&quot;&gt;International Centre for Mathematical Sciences&lt;/a&gt;
in Edinburgh on 16-20 January 2017. You can find some reports from the workshop here:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.software.ac.uk/blog/2017-02-07-computational-mathematics-jupyter&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Computational Mathematics with Jupyter&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
by Raniere Silva (Software Sustainability Institute) and Hans Fangohr (University of Southampton)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.software.ac.uk/blog/2017-02-13-computational-mathematics-jupyter-sprint&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Computational Mathematics with Jupyter: Sprint&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
by Raniere Silva (Software Sustainability Institute)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Storify of &lt;a href=&quot;https://storify.com/CIRCA_StAndrews/computational-mathematics-with-jupyter&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;#JupyterICMS&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; tweets&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content>
		<author>
			<name>The OpenDreamKit consortium</name>
			<email>contact@opendreamkit.org</email>
			<uri>http://opendreamkit.org/</uri>
		</author>
		<source>
			<title type="html">OpenDreamKit</title>
			<link rel="self" href="http://opendreamkit.org/atom.xml"/>
			<id>http://opendreamkit.org/</id>
			<updated>2017-10-17T17:06:20+00:00</updated>
		</source>
	</entry>

	<entry>
		<title type="html">Task based parallelization of recursive linear algebra routines using Kaapi</title>
		<link href="http://opendreamkit.org/2017/01/20/Journee-Runtime/"/>
		<id>http://opendreamkit.org/2017/01/20/Journee-Runtime</id>
		<updated>2017-01-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Clément Pernet gave a talk at the &lt;a href=&quot;http://calcul.math.cnrs.fr/spip.php?article275&quot;&gt;Journée Runtime&lt;/a&gt;, on the work of the &lt;a href=&quot;http://opendreamkit.org/partners/&quot;&gt;UGA partner&lt;/a&gt; (formerly UJF) on the parallelization of exact linear algebra using recursive tasks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://calcul.math.cnrs.fr/Documents/Journees/janv2017/runtime_pernet.pdf&quot;&gt;Pdf slides of Talk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>
		<author>
			<name>The OpenDreamKit consortium</name>
			<email>contact@opendreamkit.org</email>
			<uri>http://opendreamkit.org/</uri>
		</author>
		<source>
			<title type="html">OpenDreamKit</title>
			<link rel="self" href="http://opendreamkit.org/atom.xml"/>
			<id>http://opendreamkit.org/</id>
			<updated>2017-10-17T17:06:20+00:00</updated>
		</source>
	</entry>

	<entry>
		<title type="html">A case study of computational science in Jupyter notebooks: JOOMMF</title>
		<link href="http://opendreamkit.org/2017/01/20/JOOMMF-intro/"/>
		<id>http://opendreamkit.org/2017/01/20/JOOMMF-intro</id>
		<updated>2017-01-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Hans Fangohr gave an introduction to computational micromagnetics and
the current workflow that is used by thousands of scientists across
the planet. He then introduced a new Python interface to the
computational tool (OOMMF), and demonstrate how this can be driven
from within a Jupyter Notebook. Through the notebook, work can be
carried out more effectively, and more reproducibly. A roadmap and
update for the Jupyter-OOMMF project was presented as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://joommf.github.io/assets/2017-01-20-Edinburgh-Jupyter-workshop-joommf.pdf&quot;&gt;Pdf slides of Talk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/joommf/joommf.github.io/blob/master/assets/2017-01-20-Edinburgh-Jupyter-workshop-standard_problem3.ipynb&quot;&gt;Notebook of micromagnetic simulation (standard problem 3)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/joommf/joommf.github.io/blob/master/assets/2017-01-20-Edinburgh-Jupyter-workshop-micromagneticmodel.ipynb&quot;&gt;Notebook of micromagnetic model&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.software.ac.uk/blog/2017-02-02-computational-mathematics-jupyter&quot;&gt;Blog entry mentioning the presentation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>
		<author>
			<name>The OpenDreamKit consortium</name>
			<email>contact@opendreamkit.org</email>
			<uri>http://opendreamkit.org/</uri>
		</author>
		<source>
			<title type="html">OpenDreamKit</title>
			<link rel="self" href="http://opendreamkit.org/atom.xml"/>
			<id>http://opendreamkit.org/</id>
			<updated>2017-10-17T17:06:20+00:00</updated>
		</source>
	</entry>

	<entry>
		<title type="html">Biannual ODK Steering Committee meeting</title>
		<link href="http://opendreamkit.org/2017/01/19/EdinburghSteeringCommittee/"/>
		<id>http://opendreamkit.org/2017/01/19/EdinburghSteeringCommittee</id>
		<updated>2017-01-19T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The biannual OpenDreamKit Steering Committee meeting is taking place in Edinburgh at the occasion of the &lt;a href=&quot;http://opendreamkit.org/meetings/2017-01-16-ICMS/&quot;&gt;Computational Mathematics with Jupyter&lt;/a&gt; workshop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Date: 19/01/2017&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Location: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.icms.org.uk/&quot;&gt;ICMS&lt;/a&gt;, Edinburgh, United-Kingdom&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;10am-12am (local time), lecture hall on the 4th room&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://framadate.org/IsCZEQqctimhKiHU&quot;&gt;Participants&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://mensuel.framapad.org/p/odk-sc&quot;&gt;Pad&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://gitter.im/OpenDreamKit&quot;&gt;Gitter chat&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://appear.in/odk-sc&quot;&gt;Appear.in chat room&lt;/a&gt; (backup in case videoconference would fail)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;brief-agenda&quot;&gt;Brief agenda&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Preparation for the formal review&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Progress reports per site&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Advisory Board and Quality Review Board&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Amendment to the grant agreement&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Key Performance Indicators&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Deliverables due Month 18&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;WP7 topics in view of personnel changes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Future funding&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;detailed-agenda-and-minutes&quot;&gt;Detailed &lt;a href=&quot;http://opendreamkit.org/meetings/2017-01-19-EdinburghSteeringCommittee/steering-minutes/&quot;&gt;agenda and minutes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;progress-reports-per-site&quot;&gt;Progress reports per site&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://opendreamkit.org/meetings/2017-01-19-EdinburghSteeringCommittee/ProgressReports/ParisSud&quot;&gt;Université Paris Sud&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://opendreamkit.org/meetings/2017-01-19-EdinburghSteeringCommittee/ProgressReports/CNRS&quot;&gt;CNRS&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://opendreamkit.org/meetings/2017-01-19-EdinburghSteeringCommittee/ProgressReports/JacU&quot;&gt;Jacobs University Bremen&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://opendreamkit.org/meetings/2017-01-19-EdinburghSteeringCommittee/ProgressReports/UJF&quot;&gt;Université Joseph Fourier&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://opendreamkit.org/meetings/2017-01-19-EdinburghSteeringCommittee/ProgressReports/Kaiserslautern&quot;&gt;University of Kaiserslautern&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://opendreamkit.org/meetings/2017-01-19-EdinburghSteeringCommittee/ProgressReports/Oxford&quot;&gt;University of Oxford&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://opendreamkit.org/meetings/2017-01-19-EdinburghSteeringCommittee/ProgressReports/Silesia&quot;&gt;University of Silesia&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://opendreamkit.org/meetings/2017-01-19-EdinburghSteeringCommittee/ProgressReports/Sheffield&quot;&gt;University of Sheffield&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://opendreamkit.org/meetings/2017-01-19-EdinburghSteeringCommittee/ProgressReports/southampton.pdf&quot;&gt;University of Southampton&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://opendreamkit.org/meetings/2017-01-19-EdinburghSteeringCommittee/ProgressReports/StAndrews&quot;&gt;University of St Andrews&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://opendreamkit.org/meetings/2017-01-19-EdinburghSteeringCommittee/ProgressReports/UVersailles&quot;&gt;Université Versailles Saint-Quentin&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://opendreamkit.org/meetings/2017-01-19-EdinburghSteeringCommittee/ProgressReports/Warwick&quot;&gt;University of Warwick&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://opendreamkit.org/meetings/2017-01-19-EdinburghSteeringCommittee/ProgressReports/Zurich&quot;&gt;Universität Zürich&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://opendreamkit.org/meetings/2017-01-19-EdinburghSteeringCommittee/ProgressReports/Logilab&quot;&gt;Logilab&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://opendreamkit.org/meetings/2017-01-19-EdinburghSteeringCommittee/ProgressReports/Simula&quot;&gt;Simula Research Laboratory&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://opendreamkit.org/meetings/2017-01-19-EdinburghSteeringCommittee/ProgressReports/UGent/ugent.pdf&quot;&gt;Universiteit Gent&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content>
		<author>
			<name>The OpenDreamKit consortium</name>
			<email>contact@opendreamkit.org</email>
			<uri>http://opendreamkit.org/</uri>
		</author>
		<source>
			<title type="html">OpenDreamKit</title>
			<link rel="self" href="http://opendreamkit.org/atom.xml"/>
			<id>http://opendreamkit.org/</id>
			<updated>2017-10-17T17:06:20+00:00</updated>
		</source>
	</entry>

	<entry>
		<title type="html">Workshop: Computational Mathematics with Jupyter</title>
		<link href="http://opendreamkit.org/2017/01/16/Computational_Mathematics_with_Jupyter/"/>
		<id>http://opendreamkit.org/2017/01/16/Computational_Mathematics_with_Jupyter</id>
		<updated>2017-01-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Jointly with the Collaborative Computational Project &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.codima.ac.uk/&quot;&gt;“CoDiMa - CCP
in the area of Computational Discrete Mathematics”&lt;/a&gt;,
we are currently organising a workshop
&lt;a href=&quot;http://opendreamkit.org/meetings/2017-01-16-ICMS/&quot;&gt;“Computational Mathematics with Jupyter”&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It will take place at the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.icms.org.uk/&quot;&gt;International Centre for Mathematical Sciences&lt;/a&gt;
in Edinburgh on 16-20 January 2017. Please see the &lt;a href=&quot;http://opendreamkit.org/meetings/2017-01-16-ICMS/&quot;&gt;workshop website&lt;/a&gt; for further details.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.software.ac.uk/blog/2017-02-02-computational-mathematics-jupyter&quot;&gt;Software Sustainability Institute blog&lt;/a&gt;
is hosting a summary of the event.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
		<author>
			<name>The OpenDreamKit consortium</name>
			<email>contact@opendreamkit.org</email>
			<uri>http://opendreamkit.org/</uri>
		</author>
		<source>
			<title type="html">OpenDreamKit</title>
			<link rel="self" href="http://opendreamkit.org/atom.xml"/>
			<id>http://opendreamkit.org/</id>
			<updated>2017-10-17T17:06:20+00:00</updated>
		</source>
	</entry>

	<entry>
		<title type="html">nbdime released</title>
		<link href="http://opendreamkit.org/2017/01/13/nbdime/"/>
		<id>http://opendreamkit.org/2017/01/13/nbdime</id>
		<updated>2017-01-13T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://nbdime.readthedocs.io&quot;&gt;nbdime&lt;/a&gt; has had its first stable release.
nbdime provides tools for diffing and merging Jupyter notebooks,
and integrating notebooks into git workflow.
nbdime aims to alleviate some common difficulties when working with  Jupyter notebooks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Particular features of nbdime:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;recognizing binary outputs that cannot be reasonably interpreted in the terminal&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;recognizing transient fields and eliminating them from merge conflicts&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;ensuring that merged notebooks are always valid&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;integration with git as &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;drivers&lt;/code&gt; for passive diff/merge integration and &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;tools&lt;/code&gt; for interactive GUI integration&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tools provided by nbdime:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;nbshow&lt;/code&gt;: show a legible formatting of a notebook on the command-line&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;nbdiff&lt;/code&gt;: command-line diff of notebooks, eliding outputs that are known to not be renderable in a terminal. &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;nbdiff&lt;/code&gt; can be integrated into git as a diff driver&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;nbdiff-web&lt;/code&gt;: create a rich, rendered web view of the changes between two notebooks&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;nbmerge&lt;/code&gt;: three-way merge with automatic conflict resolution, which can be integrated into git as a merge driver, ensuring always-valid notebooks and eliminating merge conflicts on transient fields&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;nbmerge-web&lt;/code&gt;: interactive three-way merge tool for manually resolving merge conflicts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More info &lt;a href=&quot;https://nbdime.readthedocs.io&quot;&gt;on nbdime&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
		<author>
			<name>The OpenDreamKit consortium</name>
			<email>contact@opendreamkit.org</email>
			<uri>http://opendreamkit.org/</uri>
		</author>
		<source>
			<title type="html">OpenDreamKit</title>
			<link rel="self" href="http://opendreamkit.org/atom.xml"/>
			<id>http://opendreamkit.org/</id>
			<updated>2017-10-17T17:06:20+00:00</updated>
		</source>
	</entry>

	<entry>
		<title type="html">From pythran import typing</title>
		<link href="http://opendreamkit.org/2016/12/28/pythran-typing/"/>
		<id>http://opendreamkit.org/2016/12/28/pythran-typing</id>
		<updated>2016-12-28T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;As part of its OpenDreamKit deliverable &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/OpenDreamKit/OpenDreamKit/issues/117&quot;&gt;D5.4 (Make Pythran typing better to improve error information)&lt;/a&gt;, the Pythran team has written an in-depth &lt;a href=&quot;http://serge-sans-paille.github.io/pythran-stories/from-pythran-import-typing.html&quot;&gt;article about an unsound type checker&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
		<author>
			<name>The OpenDreamKit consortium</name>
			<email>contact@opendreamkit.org</email>
			<uri>http://opendreamkit.org/</uri>
		</author>
		<source>
			<title type="html">OpenDreamKit</title>
			<link rel="self" href="http://opendreamkit.org/atom.xml"/>
			<id>http://opendreamkit.org/</id>
			<updated>2017-10-17T17:06:20+00:00</updated>
		</source>
	</entry>

	<entry>
		<title type="html">Full-time open-ended research software engineer position</title>
		<link href="http://opendreamkit.org/2016/12/22/RSE-position-warwick/"/>
		<id>http://opendreamkit.org/2016/12/22/RSE-position-warwick</id>
		<updated>2016-12-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;We are seeking a full-time research software engineer at Warwick to
work with Professor John Cremona on those parts of the OpenDreamKit
project connected with the LMFDB in relation to Work Package 6.  The
position is open-ended.  The post holder will be employed within the
Scientific Computing Research Technology Platform (RTP) at Warwick,
initially under secondment to Professor Cremona for the duration of
the ODK project, together with longer-term responsibilities for the
development and support of research software across the University.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;job-advertisement&quot;&gt;Job advertisement&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The full advertisement may be found &lt;a href=&quot;https://atsv7.wcn.co.uk/search_engine/jobs.cgi?owner=5062452&amp;ownertype=fair&amp;jcode=1625541&amp;vt_template=1457&amp;adminview=1&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;deadline&quot;&gt;Deadline&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Deadline for applications: 26 January 2017.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;location&quot;&gt;Location&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The developer will work at the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www2.warwick.ac.uk/&quot;&gt;University of Warwick&lt;/a&gt;, UK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;mission-and-activities&quot;&gt;Mission and activities&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Initially, to work as part of the OpenDreamKit collaboration, on those
parts of WP6 related to the LMFDB project.  Longer term, to play a
leading role in the development of research software support at
Warwick.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;skills-requirements&quot;&gt;Skills requirements&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;See the See the full &lt;a href=&quot;https://atsv7.wcn.co.uk/search_engine/jobs.cgi?owner=5062452&amp;ownertype=fair&amp;jcode=1625541&amp;vt_template=1457&amp;adminview=1&quot;&gt;job
advertisement&lt;/a&gt;
for a detailed job description, and a list f essential and desirable
criteria for the person to be appointed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;context&quot;&gt;Context&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Until 31 August 2019, the position will be mainly funded by&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://opendreamkit.org&quot;&gt;OpenDreamKit&lt;/a&gt;, a
&lt;a href=&quot;https://ec.europa.eu/programmes/horizon2020/&quot;&gt;Horizon 2020&lt;/a&gt;
European &lt;a href=&quot;https://ec.europa.eu/programmes/horizon2020/en/h2020-section/european-research-infrastructures-including-e-infrastructures&quot;&gt;Research Infrastructure&lt;/a&gt;
project that will run for four years, starting from September&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;This project brings together the open-source computational
mathematics ecosystem – and in particular
&lt;a href=&quot;http://linalg.org/&quot;&gt;LinBox&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href=&quot;http://mpir.org&quot;&gt;MPIR&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href=&quot;http://sagemath.org/&quot;&gt;SageMath&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.gap-system.org/&quot;&gt;GAP&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href=&quot;http://pari.math.u-bordeaux.fr/&quot;&gt;PARI/GP&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href=&quot;http://lmfdb.org/&quot;&gt;LMFDB&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.singular.uni-kl.de/&quot;&gt;Singular&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href=&quot;https://mathhub.info/&quot;&gt;MathHub&lt;/a&gt;,
and the
&lt;a href=&quot;http://jupyter.org/&quot;&gt;IPython/Jupyter&lt;/a&gt; interactive computing
environment.
– toward building a
flexible toolkit for
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.2020-horizon.com/e-Infrastructures-for-virtual-research-environments-%28VRE%29-i1490.html&quot;&gt;Virtual Research Environments&lt;/a&gt;
for mathematics. Lead by Université Paris-Sud, this project involves
about 50 people spread over 15 sites in Europe, with a total budget of
about 7.6 million euros.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From 1 September 2019 the post will be funded by the University of Warwick.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;further-particulars&quot;&gt;Further particulars&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;See the full &lt;a href=&quot;https://atsv7.wcn.co.uk/search_engine/jobs.cgi?owner=5062452&amp;ownertype=fair&amp;jcode=1625541&amp;vt_template=1457&amp;adminview=1&quot;&gt;job
advertisement&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;expressions-of-interest&quot;&gt;Expressions of interest&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Interested candidates should send an email to Professor John Cremona
(j.e.cremona@warwick.ac.uk) for further information about the
position, as soon as possible.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
		<author>
			<name>The OpenDreamKit consortium</name>
			<email>contact@opendreamkit.org</email>
			<uri>http://opendreamkit.org/</uri>
		</author>
		<source>
			<title type="html">OpenDreamKit</title>
			<link rel="self" href="http://opendreamkit.org/atom.xml"/>
			<id>http://opendreamkit.org/</id>
			<updated>2017-10-17T17:06:20+00:00</updated>
		</source>
	</entry>

	<entry xml:lang="en">
		<title type="html">A time evolution picture of packages built in parallel by Sage</title>
		<link href="http://www.slabbe.org/blogue/2016/12/a-time-evolution-picture-of-packages-built-in-parallel-by-sage"/>
		<id>http://www.slabbe.org/blogue/2016/12/a-time-evolution-picture-of-packages-built-in-parallel-by-sage</id>
		<updated>2016-12-16T16:13:00+00:00</updated>
		<content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;document&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Compiling sage takes a while and does a lot of stuff. Each time I am wondering
which components takes so much time and which are fast. I wrote a module in my
&lt;a class=&quot;reference external&quot; href=&quot;https://github.com/seblabbe/slabbe&quot;&gt;slabbe&lt;/a&gt; version &lt;tt class=&quot;docutils literal&quot;&gt;0.3b2&lt;/tt&gt; package available on &lt;a class=&quot;reference external&quot; href=&quot;http://pypi.python.org/pypi/slabbe&quot;&gt;PyPI&lt;/a&gt; to figure this out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is after compiling 7.5.beta6 after an upgrade from 7.5.beta4:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;pygments_manni&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;sage&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kn&quot;&gt;from&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nn&quot;&gt;slabbe.analyze_sage_build&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kn&quot;&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;draw_sage_build&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;sage&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;draw_sage_build&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;pdf&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;



&lt;a class=&quot;reference external image-reference&quot; href=&quot;http://www.slabbe.org/Files/2016/sage_build.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;/Files/2016/sage_build.png&quot; src=&quot;http://www.slabbe.org/Files/2016/sage_build.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From scratch from a fresh git clone of 7.5.beta6, after running &lt;tt class=&quot;docutils literal&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;pre&quot;&gt;MAKE='make&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;pre&quot;&gt;-j4'&lt;/span&gt; make ptestlong&lt;/tt&gt;, I get:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;pygments_manni&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;sage&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kn&quot;&gt;from&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nn&quot;&gt;slabbe.analyze_sage_build&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kn&quot;&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;draw_sage_build&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;sage&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;draw_sage_build&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;pdf&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;



&lt;a class=&quot;reference external image-reference&quot; href=&quot;http://www.slabbe.org/Files/2016/sage_build_from_scratch.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;/Files/2016/sage_build_from_scratch.png&quot; src=&quot;http://www.slabbe.org/Files/2016/sage_build_from_scratch.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The picture does not include the start and ptestlong because there was an error
compiling the documentation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By default, &lt;tt class=&quot;docutils literal&quot;&gt;draw_sage_build&lt;/tt&gt; considers all of the logs files in
&lt;tt class=&quot;docutils literal&quot;&gt;logs/pkgs&lt;/tt&gt; but options are available to consider only log files created in a
given interval of time. See &lt;tt class=&quot;docutils literal&quot;&gt;draw_sage_build?&lt;/tt&gt; for more info.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content>
		<author>
			<name>Sébastien Labbé</name>
			<uri>http://www.slabbe.org/blogue/</uri>
		</author>
		<source>
			<title type="html">Sébastien Labbé</title>
			<subtitle type="html">Sébastien Labbé</subtitle>
			<link rel="self" href="http://www.slabbe.org/blogue/categorie/sage/feed/atom/index.xml"/>
			<id>http://www.slabbe.org/blogue/feed/atom/</id>
			<updated>2017-09-10T17:01:20+00:00</updated>
		</source>
	</entry>

	<entry>
		<title type="html">nbdime 0.1.0</title>
		<link href="http://opendreamkit.org/2016/12/16/nbdime-release-0.1.0/"/>
		<id>http://opendreamkit.org/2016/12/16/nbdime-release-0.1.0</id>
		<updated>2016-12-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;nbdime 0.1.0 has been released, implementing tools for diffing and merging Jupyter notebooks&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Key features:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;nbdiff for diffing notebooks in the terminal&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;nbdiff-web for viewing a rich, rendered diff of two notebooks&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;nbmerge for merging three notebooks, with automatic conflict resolution that should always guarantee a valid notebook, even with unresolved conflicts&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;nbmerge-web for manually resolving conflicts when merging notebooks&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;nbshow for quickly viewing a notebook in the terminal&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;git integration for using the diff and merge tools on notebook files by default&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://nbdime.readthedocs.io&quot;&gt;Read the docs!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jupyter/nbdime&quot;&gt;Contribute!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://pypi.python.org/pypi/nbdime&quot;&gt;Download!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content>
		<author>
			<name>The OpenDreamKit consortium</name>
			<email>contact@opendreamkit.org</email>
			<uri>http://opendreamkit.org/</uri>
		</author>
		<source>
			<title type="html">OpenDreamKit</title>
			<link rel="self" href="http://opendreamkit.org/atom.xml"/>
			<id>http://opendreamkit.org/</id>
			<updated>2017-10-17T17:06:20+00:00</updated>
		</source>
	</entry>

	<entry>
		<title type="html">Full-time mathematical software developer position at TU Kaiserslautern</title>
		<link href="http://opendreamkit.org/2016/12/15/developer-position-kaiserslautern/"/>
		<id>http://opendreamkit.org/2016/12/15/developer-position-kaiserslautern</id>
		<updated>2016-12-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;We are seeking a full-time mathematical software developer at TU Kaiserslautern to work with Prof. Wolfram Decker on the Singular contribution to the OpenDreamKit project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;deadline&quot;&gt;Deadline&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Deadline for applications: TBA.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;location&quot;&gt;Location&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The developer will work at TU Kaiserslautern in the city of Kaiserslautern Germany. Kaiserslautern is next to one of the largest contiguous forests in Europe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;mission&quot;&gt;Mission&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To work as part of the OpenDreamKit collaboration, to implement improvements via parallelisation of components of Singular.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;activities&quot;&gt;Activities&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To implement parallel algorithms in Singular in C/C++.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Particular deliverables include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Improving the quadratic sieve for integer factorisation.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Parallelising the new polynomial arithmetic functionality in Singular.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Depending on the skills of the applicant, the developer may also wish to contribute to other aspects of the Singular project and mathematical research in Kaiserslautern.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;skills-requirements&quot;&gt;Skills requirements&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;C/C++ programming experience&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Interest in either:&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;algebra/number theory/algebraic geometry&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;fast arithmetic&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;the design and development of computer algebra systems&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Fluency in English&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Must have an Masters degree in Mathematics fully certificated&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Experience in Open Source development and tooling (GitHub)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;context&quot;&gt;Context&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The position will be funded by&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://opendreamkit.org&quot;&gt;OpenDreamKit&lt;/a&gt;, a
&lt;a href=&quot;https://ec.europa.eu/programmes/horizon2020/&quot;&gt;Horizon 2020&lt;/a&gt;
European &lt;a href=&quot;https://ec.europa.eu/programmes/horizon2020/en/h2020-section/european-research-infrastructures-including-e-infrastructures&quot;&gt;Research Infrastructure&lt;/a&gt;
project that will run for four years, starting from September&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;This project brings together the open-source computational
mathematics ecosystem – and in particular
&lt;a href=&quot;http://linalg.org/&quot;&gt;LinBox&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href=&quot;http://mpir.org&quot;&gt;MPIR&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href=&quot;http://sagemath.org/&quot;&gt;SageMath&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.gap-system.org/&quot;&gt;GAP&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href=&quot;http://pari.math.u-bordeaux.fr/&quot;&gt;PARI/GP&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href=&quot;http://lmfdb.org/&quot;&gt;LMFDB&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.singular.uni-kl.de/&quot;&gt;Singular&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href=&quot;https://mathhub.info/&quot;&gt;MathHub&lt;/a&gt;,
and the
&lt;a href=&quot;http://jupyter.org/&quot;&gt;IPython/Jupyter&lt;/a&gt; interactive computing
environment.
– toward building a
flexible toolkit for
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.2020-horizon.com/e-Infrastructures-for-virtual-research-environments-%28VRE%29-i1490.html&quot;&gt;Virtual Research Environments&lt;/a&gt;
for mathematics. Lead by Université Paris-Sud, this project involves
about 50 people spread over 15 sites in Europe, with a total budget of
about 7.6 million euros.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;applications&quot;&gt;Applications&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Interested candidates should send an email to both decker {at} mathematik dot uni-kl dot de and goodwillhart {at} googlemail dot com with a CV and short letter of application, as soon as possible.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
		<author>
			<name>The OpenDreamKit consortium</name>
			<email>contact@opendreamkit.org</email>
			<uri>http://opendreamkit.org/</uri>
		</author>
		<source>
			<title type="html">OpenDreamKit</title>
			<link rel="self" href="http://opendreamkit.org/atom.xml"/>
			<id>http://opendreamkit.org/</id>
			<updated>2017-10-17T17:06:20+00:00</updated>
		</source>
	</entry>

	<entry>
		<title type="html">RethinkDB, SageMath, Andreessen-Horowitz, Basecamp and Open Source Software</title>
		<link href="http://sagemath.blogspot.com/2016/10/rethinkdb-sagemath-andreessen-horowitz.html"/>
		<id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-6365588202025292315.post-2555982827403411238</id>
		<updated>2016-11-17T15:57:37+00:00</updated>
		<content type="html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;rethinkdb-and-sustainable-business-models&quot;&gt;RethinkDB and sustainable business models&lt;/h2&gt;Three weeks ago, I spent the evening of Sept 12, 2016 with Daniel Mewes, who is the lead engineer of RethinkDB (an open source database). I was also supposed to meet with the co-founders, Slava and Michael, but they were too busy fundraising and couldn't join us. I pestered Daniel the whole evening about what RethinkDB's business model actually was. Yesterday, on October 6, 2016, &lt;a href=&quot;https://rethinkdb.com/blog/rethinkdb-shutdown/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;RethinkDB shut down.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;I met with some RethinkDB devs because an investor who runs a fund at the VC firm Andreessen-Horowitz (A16Z) had kindly invited me there to explain my commercialization plans for SageMath, Inc., and RethinkDB is one of the companies that &lt;a href=&quot;https://mattermark.com/companies/rethinkdb.com&quot;&gt;A16Z has invested in&lt;/a&gt;. At first, I wasn't going to take the meeting with A16Z, since I have never met with Venture Capitalists before, and do not intend to raise VC. However, some of my advisors convinced me that VC's can be very helpful even if you never intend to take their investment, so I accepted the meeting.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;In the first draft of my slides for my presentation to A16Z, I had a slide with the question: &quot;Why do you fund open source companies like RethinkDB and CoreOS, which have no clear (to me) business model? Is it out of some sense of charity to support the open source software ecosystem?&quot; After talking with people at Google and the RethinkDB devs, I removed that slide, since charity is clearly not the answer (I don't know if there is a better answer than &quot;by accident&quot;).&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;I have used RethinkDB intensely for nearly two years, and I might be their biggest user in some sense. My product &lt;a href=&quot;https://cloud.sagemath.com/&quot;&gt;SageMathCloud&lt;/a&gt;, which provides web-based course management, Python, R, Latex, etc., uses RethinkDB for everything. For example, every single time you enter some text in a realtime synchronized document, a RethinkDB table gets an entry inserted in it. I have RethinkDB tables with nearly 100 million records. I gave &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=WU6eSckPR7E&quot;&gt;a talk at a RethinkDB meetup&lt;/a&gt;, filed numerous bug reports, and have been described by them as &quot;their most unlucky user&quot;. In short, in 2015 I bet big on RethinkDB, just like I bet big on Python back in 2004 when starting SageMath. And when visiting the RethinkDB devs in San Francisco (this year and also last year), I have said to them many times &quot;I have a very strong vested interest in you guys not failing.&quot; My company SageMath, Inc. also pays RethinkDB for a support contract.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Sustainable business models were very much on my mind, because of my upcoming meeting at A16Z and the upcoming board meeting for my company. &amp;nbsp;SageMath, Inc.'s business model involves making money from subscriptions to SageMathCloud (which is hosted on Google Cloud Platform); of course, there are tons of details about exactly how our business works, which we've been refining based on customer feedback. Though absolutely all of our software is open source, what we sell is convenience, easy of access and use, and we provide value by hosting &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/sagemathinc/smc/wiki/Teaching&quot;&gt;hundreds of courses&lt;/a&gt; on shared infrastructure, so it is much cheaper and easier for universities to pay us rather than hosting our software themselves (which is also &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/sagemathinc/smc/blob/master/src/dev/docker/README.md&quot;&gt;fairly easy&lt;/a&gt;). So that's our business model, and I would argue that it is working; at least our MRR is steadily increasing and is more than twice our hosting costs (we are not cash flow positive yet due to developer costs).&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;So far as I can determine, the business model of RethinkDB was to make money in the following ways: 1. Sell support contracts to companies (I bought one). 2. Sell a closed-source proprietary version of RethinkDB with extra features that were of interest to enterprise (they had a handful of such features, e.g., audit logs for queries). 3. Horizon would become a cloud-hosted competitor to Firebase, with unique advantages that users have the option to migrate from the cloud to their own private data center, and more customizability. This strategy depends on a trend for users to migrate &lt;em&gt;away&lt;/em&gt; from the cloud, rather than to it, which some people at RethinkDB thought was a real trend (I disagree).&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;I don't know of anything else they were seriously trying right now. The closed-source proprietary version of RethinkDB also seemed like a very recent last ditch effort that had only just begun; perhaps it directly contradicted a desire to be a 100% open source company?&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;With enough users, it's easier to make certain business models work. I suspect RethinkDB does not have a lot of &lt;strong&gt;real users&lt;/strong&gt;. Number of users tends to be roughly linearly related to mailing list traffic, and the &lt;a href=&quot;https://groups.google.com/forum/#!forum/rethinkdb&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;RethinkDB mailing list&lt;/a&gt; has an order of magnitude less traffic compared to the SageMath mailing lists, and SageMath has around 50,000 users. RethinkDB wasn't even advertised to be production ready until just over a year ago, so even they were telling people not to use it seriously until relatively recently. The adoption cycle for database technology is slow -- people wisely wait for &lt;a href=&quot;https://aphyr.com/posts/330-jepsen-rethinkdb-2-2-3-reconfiguration&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Aphyr's tests&lt;/a&gt;, benchmarks comparing with similar technology, etc. I was unusual in that I chose RethinkDB much earlier than most people would, since I &lt;strong&gt;love the design of RethinkDB so much&lt;/strong&gt;. It's the first database I loved, having seen a lot over many decades.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conclusion:&lt;/strong&gt; RethinkDB wasn't a real business, and wouldn't become one without year(s) more runway.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;I'm also very worried about the future of RethinkDB &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/document/d/1Fy-drBGDTyibwEBBAX6G5otqtWiKOD2sBXmL2uVTFtE/edit&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;as an open source project&lt;/a&gt;. I don't know if the developers have experience growing an open source community of volunteers; it's incredibly hard and its unclear they are even going to be involved. At a bare minimum, I think they must switch to a very liberal license (Apache instead of AGPL), and make everything (e.g., automated testing code, documentation, etc) open source. It's insanely hard getting any support for open source infrastructure work -- support mostly comes from small government grants (for research software) or contributions from employees at companies (that use the software). Relicensing in a company friendly way is thus critical.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;company-incentives&quot;&gt;Company Incentives&lt;/h2&gt;Companies can be incentived in various ways, including:&lt;br /&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;to get to the next round of &lt;strong&gt;VC funding&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;to be a &lt;strong&gt;sustainable profitable business&lt;/strong&gt; by making more money from customers than they spend, or&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;to &lt;strong&gt;grow&lt;/strong&gt; to have a very large number of users and somehow pivot to making money later.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;When founding a company, you have a chance to choose how your company will be incentived based on how much risk you are willing to take, the resources you have, the sort of business you are building, the current state of the market, and your model of what will happen in the future.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;For me, &lt;a href=&quot;http://sagemath.org/&quot;&gt;SageMath&lt;/a&gt; is an open source project I started in 2004, and I'm in it for the long haul. I will make the business I'm building around SageMathCloud succeed, or I will die trying -- therefore I have &lt;strong&gt;very, very little tolerance&lt;/strong&gt; for risk. Failure is not an option, and I am not looking for an exit. For me, the strategy that best matches my values is to incentive my company to build a profitable business, since that is most likely to survive, and also to give us the freedom to maintain our longterm support for open source and pure mathematics software.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Thus for my company, neither optimizing for raising the next round of VC or growing at all costs makes sense. You would be surprised how many people think I'm completely wrong for concluding this.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;andreessen-horowitz&quot;&gt;Andreessen-Horowitz&lt;/h2&gt;I spent the evening with RethinkDB developers, which scared the hell out of me regarding their business prospects. They are probably the most open source friendly VC-funded company I know of, and they had given me hope that it is possible to build a successful VC-funded tech startup around open source. I prepared for my meeting at A16Z, and deleted my slide about RethinkDB.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;I arrived at A16Z, and was greeted by incredibly friendly people. I was a little shocked when I saw their nuclear bomb art in the entry room, then went to a nice little office to wait. The meeting time arrived, and we went over my slides, and I explained my business model, goals, etc. They said there was no place for A16Z to invest directly in what I was planning to do, since I was very explicit that I'm not looking for an exit, and my plan about how big I wanted the company to grow in the next 5 years wasn't sufficiently ambitious. They were also worried about how small the total market cap of Mathematica and Matlab is (only a few hundred million?!). However, they generously and repeatedly offered to introduce me to more potential angel investors.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;We argued about the value of outside investment to the company I am trying to build. I had hoped to get some insight or introductions related to their portfolio companies that are of interest to my company (e.g., Udacity, GitHub), but they deflected all such questions. There was also some confusion, since I showed them slides about what I'm doing, but was quite clear that I was not asking for money, which is not what they are used to. In any case, I greatly appreciated the meeting, and it really made me think. They were crystal clear that they believed I was completely wrong to not be trying to do everything possible to raise investor money.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;basecamp&quot;&gt;Basecamp&lt;/h2&gt;During the first year of SageMath, Inc., I was planning to raise a round of VC, and was doing everything to prepare for that. I then read some of &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@dhh&quot;&gt;DHH's books&lt;/a&gt; about Basecamp, and realized many of those arguments applied to my situation, given my values, and -- after a lot of reflection -- I changed my mind. I think Basecamp itself is mostly closed source, so they may have an advantage &amp;nbsp;in building a business. SageMathCloud (and SageMath) really are 100% open source, and building a completely open source business might be harder. Our open source IP is considered worthless by investors. Witness: RethinkDB just shut down and &lt;a href=&quot;https://stripe.com/&quot;&gt;Stripe&lt;/a&gt; hired just the engineers -- all the IP, customers, etc., of RethinkDB was evidently considered worthless by investors.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The day after the A16Z meeting, I met with my board, which went well (we discussed a huge range of topics over several hours). Some of the board members also tried hard to convince me that I should raise a lot more investor money.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;will-poole-youre-doomed&quot;&gt;Will Poole: you're doomed&lt;/h2&gt;Two weeks ago I met with Will Poole, who is a friend of a friend, and we talked about my company and plans. I described what I was doing, that everything was open source, that I was incentivizing the company around building a business rather than raising investor money. He listened and asked a lot of follow up questions, making it very clear he understands building a company very, very well.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;His feedback was discouraging -- I said &quot;So, you're saying that I'm basically doomed.&quot; He responded that I wasn't doomed, but might be able to run a small &quot;lifestyle business&quot; at best via my approach, but there was absolutely no way that what I was doing would have any impact or pay for my kids college tuition. If this was feedback from some random person, it might not have been so disturbing, but Will Poole joined Microsoft in 1996, where he went on to &lt;strong&gt;run Microsoft's multibillion dollar Windows business&lt;/strong&gt;. Will Poole is like a retired four-star general that executed a successful campaign to conquer the world; he been around the block a few times. He tried pretty hard to convince me to make as much of SageMathCloud closed source as possible, and to try to convince my users to make content they create in SMC something that I can reuse however I want. I felt pretty shaken and convinced that I needed to close parts of SMC, e.g., the new Kubernetes-based backend that we spent all summer implementing. (Will: if you read this, though our discussion was really disturbing to me, I really appreciate it and respect you.)&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.wallstreetoasis.com/forums/tomato-jos-the-extra-alternative-career-for-top-mba-grads&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;My friend&lt;/a&gt;, who introduced me to Will Poole, introduced me to some other people and described me as that really frustrating sort of entrepreneur who doesn't want investor money. He then remarked that one of the things he learned in business school, which really surprised him, was that it is &lt;strong&gt;good&lt;/strong&gt; for a company to have a lot of debt. I gave him a funny look, and he added &quot;of course, I've never run a company&quot;.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;I left that meeting with Will convinced that I would close source parts of SageMathCloud, to make things much more defensible. However, after thinking things through for several days, and talking this over with other people involved in the company, I have chosen not to close anything. This just makes our job harder. Way harder. But I'm not going to make any decisions based purely on fear. I don't care what anybody says, I do not think it is impossible to build an open source business (I think &lt;a href=&quot;https://wordpress.org/about/&quot;&gt;Wordpress&lt;/a&gt; is an example), and I do not need to raise VC.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Hacker News Discussion:&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=12663599&quot;&gt;https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=12663599&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Chinese version:&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.infoq.com/cn/news/2016/10/Reflection-sustainable-profit-co&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;http://www.infoq.com/cn/news/2016/10/Reflection-sustainable-profit-co&lt;/a&gt;</content>
		<author>
			<name>William Stein</name>
			<email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
			<uri>http://sagemath.blogspot.com/</uri>
		</author>
		<source>
			<title type="html">Sage: Open Source Mathematics Software</title>
			<subtitle type="html">This is my blog about things related to Sage.</subtitle>
			<link rel="self" href="http://sagemath.blogspot.com/feeds/posts/default"/>
			<id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-6365588202025292315</id>
			<updated>2017-10-10T19:05:18+00:00</updated>
		</source>
	</entry>

	<entry>
		<title type="html">OpenDreamKit Virtual Research Environment</title>
		<link href="http://opendreamkit.org/2016/11/17/OpenScience-conference/"/>
		<id>http://opendreamkit.org/2016/11/17/OpenScience-conference</id>
		<updated>2016-11-17T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://joommf.github.io/assets/2016-11-17-openscience-ljubljana.pdf&quot;&gt;Pdf slides of Talk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>
		<author>
			<name>The OpenDreamKit consortium</name>
			<email>contact@opendreamkit.org</email>
			<uri>http://opendreamkit.org/</uri>
		</author>
		<source>
			<title type="html">OpenDreamKit</title>
			<link rel="self" href="http://opendreamkit.org/atom.xml"/>
			<id>http://opendreamkit.org/</id>
			<updated>2017-10-17T17:06:20+00:00</updated>
		</source>
	</entry>

	<entry>
		<title type="html">Jupyter Day in Orsay:</title>
		<link href="http://opendreamkit.org/2016/11/04/jupyterday-orsay/"/>
		<id>http://opendreamkit.org/2016/11/04/jupyterday-orsay</id>
		<updated>2016-11-04T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<content type="html">&lt;h1 id=&quot;-subscriptions-are-closed&quot;&gt;!!! SUBSCRIPTIONS ARE CLOSED&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The LoOPS network, DevLog and OpenDreamKit are organising a day for the various tools available in the &lt;a href=&quot;http://jupyter.org/&quot;&gt;Jupyter environment&lt;/a&gt;.
Notebooks are more and more used among research communities thanks to their ease of use and their interactivity. They allow
an easy access to class documentation and appealing practical exercises for students, to share ideas between colleagues and
to initiate a reflexion to allow reproducible research works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Where: Room 1-2-3 of the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ias.u-psud.fr/&quot;&gt;Institut d’Astrophysique Spatiale&lt;/a&gt;, Orsay, France&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;When: 6th of December 2016&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Who: four core developers of Jupyter tools will be present (S. Corlay, A, Darian, T. Kluyver, B. Ragan-Kelley) and V. Pons who is working on SageMathCloud.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Event organisation: Loïc Gouarin&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://indico.lal.in2p3.fr/event/3319/registration/register#/register&quot;&gt;Subscriptions&lt;/a&gt; are free but mandatory. Most of
talks and workshops will be given in English. You may need to bring your own training materials, in which case we will
warn you in advance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;agenda&quot;&gt;Agenda:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;9h15-9h45: Welcome&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;9h45-12h45 Presentations
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;A. Darian et S. Corlay : JupyterLab and third-party extensions, featuring ipywidgets: the next generation of Jupyter notebooks.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;B. Ragan-Kelley : JupyterHub: Deploying Jupyter Notebooks for students and researchers.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;V Fauske : nbdime: diffing and merging notebooks.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;V. Pons : the SageMathCloud platform&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;12h45-14h00 Buffet&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;14h00-14h30 T. Kluyver: Nbconvert: make things from notebooks&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;14h30-17h30 Workshops run in parallel&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;presentations&quot;&gt;Presentations:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1) A. Darian et S. Corlay : JupyterLab and third-party extensions, featuring ipywidgets: the next generation of Jupyter notebooks&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This talk will consist of an architectural overview and the current state of affairs of the new JupyterLab and ipywidgets.
It will feature demos of the master branch of these projects, reflecting the latest developments&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2) B. Ragan-Kelley : JupyterHub: Deploying Jupyter Notebooks for students and researchers&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since the Jupyter notebook is a web-based environment, the notebook server can be run remotely, not just on your local
machine. JupyterHub is a multi-user server, aimed at helping research groups and instructors host notebook servers for
their users or students. By default, JupyterHub uses the local system users and PAM authentication, but it can be
customized to use any authentication system, including GitHub, CILogon, Shibboleth, and more. The way single-user
servers are spawned can also be customized to use services such as Docker, Kubernetes, or HPC cluster queuing systems.
The tutorial will cover a basic deployment of JupyterHub on a single machine, then extending it to use docker and GitHub
authentication, as well as general best practices for JupyterHub deployment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;3) V. Fauske : nbdime: diffing and merging notebooks&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jupyter notebooks are JSON documents containing a combination of code, prose, and output. These outputs may be rich
media, such as HTML or images. The use of JSON and including output can present challenges when working with version
control systems and code review. The JSON structure significantly impedes the readability of diffs, and simple line-based
merge tools can produce invalid results. nbdime aims to provide diff and merge tools specifically for notebooks. For diffs,
nbdime shows rendered diffs of notebooks, so that the content can be compared efficiently, rather than the raw JSON. Merges
performed with nbdime will guarantee a valid notebook as a result, even in the event of conflicts. nbdime integrates with
existing tools, such as git, so you shouldn’t need to change how you work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;4) V. Pons : the SageMathCloud platform&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will present the open-source interactive platform SageMathCloud and its many useful aspects for research collaboration
and teaching:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;creation of a collaborative project;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;sharing files and worksheets;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;using Jupyter in SageMathCloud;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;multi-user real time editing;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;course management with Jupyter and SageMathCloud&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;5) T. Kluyver : Nbconvert: make things from notebooks&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nbconvert is a set of tools to convert notebooks to other file types, such as HTML,
Latex, or executable scripts. We’ll cover how to use it at the command line and in the
notebook interface, along with an overview of how it works. Nbconvert is also designed to be highly extensible,
and we’ll describe some of the things that can be done by building on nbconvert, such as extra converters, reports
based on input, and cross-linking between converted notebooks.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
		<author>
			<name>The OpenDreamKit consortium</name>
			<email>contact@opendreamkit.org</email>
			<uri>http://opendreamkit.org/</uri>
		</author>
		<source>
			<title type="html">OpenDreamKit</title>
			<link rel="self" href="http://opendreamkit.org/atom.xml"/>
			<id>http://opendreamkit.org/</id>
			<updated>2017-10-17T17:06:20+00:00</updated>
		</source>
	</entry>

	<entry>
		<title type="html">OOMMF Python interface presentation</title>
		<link href="http://opendreamkit.org/2016/11/02/oommf-python-mmm2016/"/>
		<id>http://opendreamkit.org/2016/11/02/oommf-python-mmm2016</id>
		<updated>2016-11-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Hans Fangohr presented the first prototype of the Python OOMMF interface at the 61st international meeting on magnetism and magnetic materials in New Orleans (US).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://joommf.github.io/assets/2016-11-02-MMM2016-CF-03-Python-OOMMF.pdf&quot;&gt;Pdf slides of Talk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>
		<author>
			<name>The OpenDreamKit consortium</name>
			<email>contact@opendreamkit.org</email>
			<uri>http://opendreamkit.org/</uri>
		</author>
		<source>
			<title type="html">OpenDreamKit</title>
			<link rel="self" href="http://opendreamkit.org/atom.xml"/>
			<id>http://opendreamkit.org/</id>
			<updated>2017-10-17T17:06:20+00:00</updated>
		</source>
	</entry>

</feed>
